<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Decreet of separation, the apothecaries of Edinburgh, against the chyrurgeons there.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D807A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R176403</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299042</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179812</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179812)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2804:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Decreet of separation, the apothecaries of Edinburgh, against the chyrurgeons there.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Scotland --  History --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Pharmacists --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:179812:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179812:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Decreet of Separation, The <hi>Apothecaries</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Againſt The <hi>Chyrurgeons</hi> there.</head>
            <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the 24th day of <hi>March</hi> 1682 years. Anent the Libel firſt intented and purſued before the Provoſt and Baillies of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and thereafter Advocat of conſent of both Parties Procurators after-named, to the Lords of Council and Seſſion, and which Summonds is raiſed at the inſtance of Mr. <hi>James Nisbet</hi> then Deacon of Chyrurgeons of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and in name and behalf of the remanent Brethren and Friends Chyrurgeons and Barbers of the ſaid Burgh, againſt <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> Apothecary in the ſaid Burgh, Touching the ſaid Defender his hearing and ſeeing of himſelf Unlawed and Fined by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet of the ſaids Baillies, for his alledged Operating in Chyrurgery, he not being a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of that Trade and Calling, as in the ſaid Libel, Summonds, or Precept raiſed in the ſaid Matter at more length is contained. As alſo, anent the two mutual Summonds and Actions of Declarator, raiſed and purſued before the ſaids Lords, the one thereof being als well an Action of Reduction as Declarator at the inſtance of the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> and haill Freemen Apothecaries in the ſaid Burgh, <hi>Viz. John Kennedy</hi> Viſitor, <hi>James Foulis</hi> elder, <hi>Robert Campbell, Hugh Neilſon, Thomas Dalrymple, John Hepburn, James Aikenhead, John Foulis</hi> younger, Mr. <hi>Alexander Hay,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Macmath</hi> &amp; <hi>James Lothian,</hi> Freemen Apothecaries, Burgeſſes &amp; Gild-brethren of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> lawfully entered, admitted &amp; received, to whoſe great hurt and prejudice in the free Exerciſe of their Imployment as Apothecaries, the Acts, Ratifications, and other Writs after-mentioned, are alledged, purchas'd and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, at the leaſt are made uſe of by the ſaids Chyrurgions, againſt the ſaids Apothecaries, to the prejudice of the juſt Priviledges of their Imployment as Apothecaries, and their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous attendance upon the Kings Subjects their Patients in their ſaids Imployments, as for the Health of his Majeſties Subjects is requiſite; and ſwa having good and undoubted Right to Purſue the Action of Reduction and Declarttor underwritten, againſt the ſaid Mr. <hi>James Nisbet</hi> preſent Deacon of the Chyrungeons, <hi>Alexander Pennicook, John Forrest, George Scot, James Hopki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k, William Semple, Robert Kennedy, Thomas Scot, James Cleiland, Thomas Edgar, John Carmichael,</hi> and <hi>Peter Norie</hi> ſimple Chyrurgeons and Chyrurgeon Barbers in the ſaid Burgh; And ſicklike, <hi>Thomas Kincaid, William Borthwick, John Joiſſie, Hugh Broun, George Stirling, David Pringle, James Ogilvie, Walter Turnbull,</hi> and <hi>James Crawfoord</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary-Chyrurgeons in the ſaid Burgh; and als againſt Sir <hi>Thomas Murray</hi> of <hi>Glendoick</hi> then Clerk Regiſter, and Mr. <hi>Alexander Gibſon</hi> of <hi>Adiſtoun</hi> his Deput, and the Provoſt, Baillies, and Town-Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Fainburgh,</hi> and Mr. <hi>James Rockheid</hi> of <hi>Innerleith</hi> their Town Clerk for their Intereſts, and all others having or pretending to have Intereſt in the ſaid matter under-written, Toutching the ſaid Chyrurgeons and others Defenders in the foreſaid Action, their bringing with them, exhibiting and producing before the ſaids Lords of Council and Seſſion. <hi>Imprimis,</hi> An Ratification alledged paſt by the pretended Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 1641 years, whereby certain Priviledges, Writs and Rights, are alledged ratified to and in favours of the Chyrurgeons of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> &amp; particularly giving them Power to take, apprehend, and impriſon unfreemen Contraveeners of their Priviledges, ay and while they enact themſelves under the pain 20 pounds <hi>Scots toties quoties,</hi> which Ratification is dated the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> one thouſand ſix hundred and fourty one years fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Town-Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> of the date the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> one thouſand ſix hundred and fourty three years, Wherein the applying of Cere-Cloaths are decerned properly to belong to the Chyrurgeons. <hi>Item,</hi> Another Act of Town-Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> dated the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> day of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 1655. Whereby the ſeveral Diſtempers therein enumerat in the whole Cure, and Accidents of the ſamine, are allowed to Chyrurgeons allenarly. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act and Ratification paſt in favours of the Chyrurgeons in his Majeſties late Parliament 1670 years, or of whatſoever dates, tenor, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179812:2"/> contents the ſamine are of, to be ſeen and conſidered by the ſaids Lords, and to have heard and ſeen the ſamine reduced, retreated, reſcinded, caſſed, annulled and decerned and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to have been from the beginning, to be now and in all time-coming null, and of none avail, force, ſtrength, nor effect, with all that has followed, or may follow thereupon, and the ſaids Purſuers reponed and reſtored <hi>in integrum</hi> there-againſt <hi>cum omni cauſa,</hi> ſicklike as if the ſamine had never been made given nor granted in <hi>return natura.</hi> And whilks Acts, Ratifications and others above-written, being ſwa reduced, the ſaid Defenders to hear and ſee it by Decreet of the ſaids Lords found and declared, that it ſhall be no ways lawful for them to moleſt and trouble the Purſuers, or their Succeſſors, in the free exerciſe of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Imployments as Apothecaries, as they queſtionably are, and formerly have been in uſe of exerciſing the ſamine, until the ſaids Lords ſhall by the advice and council of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſted, learned and capable Phyſicians, and with a due regard to the Intereſt of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Subjects, ſhall in their Decreet to follow thereupon, preſcrive ſuch Rules and Orders for the regulation and diſtinguiſhing of the ſaid two Callings of Apothecaries and Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, as the ſaids Lords ſhall in Juſtice, and by Advice foreſaid, think moſt fit and proper for the health, eaſe and conveniency of his Majeſties Subjects, and due incouragement, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and improvement of that ſo noble and neceſſary Faculty of Medicine, in all the parts and branches thereof, in due and beſeeming order within this ancient Kingdom. And which two Callings of Apothecary and Chyrurgery being ſua diſtinguiſhed by the ſaids Lords as ſaid is, all ſuch Apothecaries and Chyrurgeons who take upon them to uſe and confound both Callings, while as yet undiſtinguiſhed, to hear and ſee themſelves decerned and reſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make their choice and election, which of the ſaids two Callings they will exerciſe and practiſe in time-coming; And to hear and ſee themſelves decerned lyable to obſerve the Rules and Orders ſua to be preſcrived, either as ſimple Chyrurgeons, or ſimple Appothecaries without confuſion of the two Callings in one, as ſhould be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the ſaids Lords thereintill, as alſo to hear and ſee it found and declared, that the making and applying of Cerecloaths doth only belong unto the Apothecaries, and that the Chyrurgeons ought neither to make or apply the ſame, and als that it's lawful and leiſum to the Apothecaries to uſe Phlebotomie when the ſamen is asked upon occaſion of inward diſtempers, and to give Dyetts and Medicaments at all occaſions; As alſo to hear and ſee it found and declared, that it ſhal not be lawfull or competent upon any pretended contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of the ſaids Rules, to trouble or moleſt the members of either calling, except they be taken in the Act of contravention <hi>per manus injectionen in crimine flagranti</hi> as is allowed to and practiſed by other Trades and Incorporations allenerly; And that it it ſhal not be lawful to parties to give their Oaths for any ſuch alledged contraventions, and to hear and ſee it found and declared that the Defenders have done wrong to moleſt and trouble <hi>Patrick Cunninghamé</hi> and of the parties above-named, in withdrawing him from the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar atendance upon Patients, His Majeſties Subjects, by acquiring him to atend a Law ſuit for giving his Oath, upon pretence of his contraveening of the alledged priviledges of the Chyrurgeons, not as yet by His Majeſty, or the ſaids Lords upon a full hearing of all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties concerned, Cleared, Setled, or Determined, and to hear and ſee themſelves decerned to deſiſt and ceaſe from all furder troubling of the ſaid <hi>Patrick,</hi> or any other Freeman A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for giving of their Oaths upon any ſuch like account, in all time coming, and that for the Reaſons and Cauſes following in the firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Noble and Supream Faculty of Medicine is in it ſelf, a free and liberal ſcience, and ought in all the Branches thereof, be keept and uſed als freely as any other liberal Science, with a juſt Reſpect to good ordour, and the decent conſtitution of the Kingdom, ſeing the Admiſtrators thereof have nixt under GOD and great care of the Health and Lives of the Subjects, under Diſeaſes and Diſtempers; and therefore ought not upon any needleſs or freevelous pretences. be by unneceſſary legal Purſuits withdrawn from the aſſiduus atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon their Patients, for gratefying the humor or intereſt of a few for their own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and ends concerned; And therefore all Limitations or Reſtrictions upon the Phiſician Apothecary, or Chyrurgon, either in their common or proper Imployments as contrair diſtinguiſhed one from an other does belong and ought only to be given by His Majeſty and his Supream Judicatories as the King, and they with the advice of able, learned, skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diſintereſſed Phyſicians, ſhal find moſt conſiſtant with His Majeſties honour, the Laws of the Kingdom, and moſt convenient for the eaſe, health and conveniency of His Majeſties good Subjects, and ſo ought not to be preſumed upon, to be determined and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrived by Acts of Particular Burghs and their Councils, the Members whereof are many times Perſons altogether ignorant of the very names and terms of Art uſed in Phyſick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179812:2"/> Pharmacie or Chyrurgery, and ſo very unfit and unqualified Judges, to ſet Limits and Marches betwixt Pharmacie and Chyrurgie, or to preſcrive Rules to the Phyſicians Pharmacian and Chyrurgeon in their proper or diſtinct Imployments; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that pretended ratification Abovewritten, paſt in the pretended Parliament 1641. ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be reſcinded, becauſe it contains a Clauſe for apprehending incarcerating, enacting that ſuch apprehendit ſhould not uſe Chyrurgical operations, which upon many ſupervenient exigencies, they may become oblidged to, eſpecially if they be Freemen Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> And that the foreſaid ratification was but ſureptitiouſly purchaſt by the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeans, from the ſaid pretended Parliament without calling of the Phyſicians or Apothecaries thereto. And hearing them for their Intereſt there againſt at the leaſt, the ſame ought to be Reſtricted to unfree men, Jurney-men &amp; Apprentices, and that only when they are ſealed upon <hi>in crimine flagranti,</hi> and not to be extended to Skilful and Experienced Free-men A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries, als weel lawfully admitted Burges and Gild-Brethren of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as Maſters of Publick Appothecaries Shops there. <hi>Secundo,</hi> And for the Reaſons foreſaid the Above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Towns Act in <hi>anno</hi> 1643. ought to be reduced, becauſe it is given <hi>a non compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenti Judice</hi> as ſaid is, and it's againſt common ſence and reaſon, to think that the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Cere-cloath to a dead Body, whereupon there is no Anatomical deſſection uſed, can be a Chyrurgical operation, and ſo ought never to have been decerned to belong pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to the Chyrurgeons, <hi>excluſive</hi> of the Apothecaries; and ſeing the Subject matter of Chyrurgery is to mend, recover and reſtore Luxations fractors and <hi>diſſolutionem continuii,</hi> it is rediculous to allow the Apothecarie the making of Cereclothes, and yet to deny him the Applacation thereof, to the ſaid Body of his own Patient, when no antomical diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection is uſed, which tends to nothing but to extort and oppreſs the good Subjects, and to render the making of Cere-cloaths, in favours of the Apothecaries altogether eluſory and ineffectuall, for ſeing by a late Invention, ſome Apothecaries have crept in to be Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, ſuch Chyrurgeons will never make uſe of Cere-cloaths made by ſimple Apothecaries, but will force the Friends of the Defunct to make uſe of Cere-cloaths, to be made by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as hath been ſeveral times of late experimented in ſundry Inſtances, to the great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes and Extortion of the Subjects, and to the detrement and diſcouragement of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Apothecary. <hi>Tertio,</hi> The Towns Act in <hi>anno</hi> 1655. Above-written ought to be <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus</hi> reduced, not only becauſe it is an high incroatchment upon what properly belongs to His Majeſty &amp; his Highneſſes <hi>ſupream Judicatories</hi> as ſaid is, for the Council of a Burgh to preſume to take upon them to find and declare what property belongs to Chyrurgie and <hi>Pharmacy</hi> as contrair diſtinguiſhed from an nother, but that the ſamen being pronounced in the time of Uſurpation is in it ſelf moſt unjuſt abſurd and unwarrantable: As <hi>firſt,</hi> In turning all the Diſtempers therein innumerated Statutory in Favours of the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenarly, which is but meerly narratory in the <hi>Act</hi> 1643; and theſe contraverted as indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently uſed, als well by the <hi>Appothecaries</hi> as by the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> of the Burgh, as in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Conſent and Conceſſions alledged for a few <hi>Appothecaries</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1643, Binding u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon all Succeeding Appothercaries contrary to all Law and Juſtice, and in debaſeing of the Honour of the Phyſician in his <hi>directive faculty</hi> in preſcriving dyet and Medicament, and all other requiſite for perfecting of the Cures of the Diſtempers therein-mentioned with their accidents, which near comprehends all Phyſick to the Chirurgeons allenarlie, and to none others for which no ſhadow of Reaſon can be given, except the unwarrantable Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieing of the Chirurgeons, for the countenancing and continuing of the Factions deſigns of the then Magiſtrats, thoſe endeavouring what in them lay to Eſtabliſh in the time of an Uſurpation, a certain Mock Borrow Colledge of Phyſicians, by Inhancing all Phyſick and Medicine, als well in the directing, compounding, and operating parts thereof, by this their <hi>Act</hi> 1655, procured before the Erecting of the Appothecaries, who was by the Towns grant being Erected, ought only to Enjoy the Priveledges by the acclaimed as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and only competent to their Art and Calling. And therefore, the ſaids pretended <hi>Acts,</hi> Ratifications and others reſpective above-written, ought and ſhould be Reduced, Retreated, Reſcinded, Caſſed, Annulled, Decerned, and Declaired to have been from the Beginning to be now, and in all time coming Null and of none avail, Force, Strength, nor Effect with all that has followed, or may follow thereupon: And the ſaids Purſuers Reponed and Reſtored <hi>in Integrum</hi> there againſt, <hi>cum omni cauſa;</hi> Sicklike, as if the ſamen had never been Made, Given nor Granted <hi>in rerum natura;</hi> and whilk Acts, Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications and others above-writen being ſua Reduced, the ſaids Defenders to hear and ſee it by Decreet of the ſaids Lords, found and declaired that it ſhall be no ways lawful for them to moleſt and trouble the Purſuers, or their Succeſſors in the free exerciſing of their Calling and Imployments as Appothecaries as they preſently are, and formerly have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179812:3"/> been in uſe of Exerciſing of the ſamen, until the ſaids Lords ſhall by the Advice and Counſel of diſ-intereſted Learned and able Phyſicians, and with a due regard to the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Subjects in their Decree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o follow hereupon, preſcrive Rules and Orders for the Regulation and diſtinguiſhing of theſe two Callings of Appothecaries and Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as the ſaids Lords ſhall in Juſtice, and by Advice foreſaid think moſt fit and proper for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ealth, eaſe and conveniency of the Subjects, and due Incouragement, Preſervation and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>roving of that ſo Noble and neceſſary Faculty of Medicine, in all the parts and Branches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>theof, in due and beſeeming Order within this antient Kingdom; and which two Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Appothecary and Chirurgery, being ſua diſtinguiſhed by the ſaids Lords as ſaid is, all ſuch Appothecaries and Chirurgeons, who take upon them to uſe and confound both Callings, whilk as yet undiſtinguiſhbd, to hear and ſee themſelves Decerned, and Reſtricted to make their Choice and Election, which of the ſaids two Callings they will practiſe and Exerciſe in time coming, and to hear and ſee themſelves Decerned lyable to obſerve the Rules and Orders ſua to be preſcrived, either as ſimple Chirurgeons, or ſimple Appotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries without confuſion of the two Callings in one, as ſhall be Determined by the ſaids Lords thereintil, and alſo to hear and ſee it found and declared that it ſhall not be lawful, nor competent upon any contravention of the ſaids Rules to trouble or moleſt the Members of either Calling, except they be taken in the Act of Contravention, <hi>per manus injectionem in crimine flagranti,</hi> as is allowed to, and practiſed by other Trades and Incorporations allen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly, and that it ſhall not be lawful for to Force Parties to give their Oaths, for any ſuch alledged Contraventions, and to have heard and ſeen it found, and declared that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders have done Wrong to moleſt and trouble <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> one of the Purſuers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-named, in withdrawing him from his neceſſary Employment and attendance upon his Patients His Majeſties good Subjects, by requiring him to attend a Law ſuit for giving of his Oath upon pretence of his contraveening the alledged Priviledges of the Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not as yet by His Majeſtie, or the ſaids Lords upon a full hearing of all Parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, cleared, ſettled or determined, and to hear and ſee themſelves decerned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and ceaſe from all farder troubling of the ſaid <hi>Patrick,</hi> or any other free men Appothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for giving of their Oaths upon any ſicklike account in all time coming and that for the Reaſons and Cauſes above-written as the ſaid Summonds of Reduction and Declarator; more fully bears, and the other of the ſaids Summonds at the inſtance of the ſaid Doctor <hi>James Niſbet,</hi> then deacon of the Incorporation of the ſaids <hi>Cherurgeons, Alexander Penny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cook, Thomas Kincaid, James Cleiland, Walter Turnbulls, John Joyſſie, William Borthwick,</hi> and <hi>George Stirling,</hi> then Maſters of the ſaid Incorporation, and <hi>Thomas Henderſon</hi> preſent Box maſter of the ſamen; for themſelves; and in name and behalf of the remnant Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and Freemen of the <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> and <hi>Barbars</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> their inſtances Againſt the whole <hi>Apothecaries</hi> and others unfreemen in the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh, viz. John Kennedy</hi> Appothecary there, <hi>John Foulis</hi> elder Appothecary there, <hi>Robert Campbel</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary there, <hi>John Hepburn</hi> Appothecary there, Mr. <hi>James Mackmath</hi> Apothecary there, <hi>Hugh Neilſon</hi> Arpothecary there, <hi>James Aikenhead</hi> Appothecary there, <hi>James Lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doun</hi> Apothecary there, <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> Appothecary there, Mr. <hi>Alexander Hap</hi> Appothecary there, <hi>John Foulis</hi> younger Appothecary there, <hi>Thomas Dalrymple</hi> Appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary there, <hi>Walter Porterfield</hi> Appothecary in the <hi>Cannongate, George Mackalla</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary in <hi>Leith, Edward Cunninghame</hi> Periwig-maker in <hi>Leith, James Robertſon</hi> Barbar there, <hi>John Broun</hi> Garidner in the Abbacy of <hi>Holy-rood-houſe, Andrew Jackson</hi> Gairdner at the Weſt Port, <hi>James Hughſon</hi> Gairdner at the <hi>Pleaſance,</hi> and <hi>George Bell</hi> Cherurgeon in <hi>Edinburgh, Euphan Bartine</hi> and <hi>John Biglie</hi> her Spouſe indwellers in <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> the which Summonds mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th mention, that where the Lord Provoſt, Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by their Seal of Cauſe under their common Seal, of the date at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 1. day of the Moneth of <hi>July,</hi> and year of GOD 1505 years, for the good and onerous Cauſes therein mentioned, did gift and grant to the <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> and Barbars within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for the time being, and to their Succeſſors, the Rules, Statutes and Priviledges under-written, conſonant to reaſon, known to His Majeſtie &amp; His Highneſſes Pregenitors of glorious and worthty Memory, and to the profit of the ſaid good Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and all his Majeſties Subjects and Leidges, <hi>viz, Imprimis,</hi> That the ſaids <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> might yearly choiſe amongſt themſelves, an Kirk maſter or Deacon and Overſman, to whom the whole Brethren of their Craft ſhould obey for that year. <hi>Item.</hi> That no manner of perſon ſhould occupie or uſe any points of the ſaids Crafts of <hi>Cherurgery</hi> or Barbour Crafts within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> but he that bees firſt an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179812:3"/> Burges and Freeman of the ſaid Craft, and that he be worthy and expert io all the points belonging to the ſaid Craft, diligently and adviſedly examined and Admitted by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſaid Craft, for ſerving of his Majeſties Leidges and Neighbours of the ſaid good Town, and als, that every Freeman who is to be made a Freeman and Maſter amongſt the ſaids <hi>Cherurgeons,</hi> ſhould be examined and proved in thir points following, that is to ſay. That he knew <hi>Anatomia,</hi> Nature and Complection, and every member of humane Body, and likeways than he knew all the Veins of the ſamen, that he may make <hi>Phlebotomie</hi> in due time, and als, that he knew in whilk member the ſign has Dominion for the time, in reſpect every man ought to know the ſubſtance and nature of every thing he works, unleſs he be negligent; and als, that the ſaids <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> and their ſaids Succeſſors ſhould have once in the year an condemned man after he be dead to make an <hi>Anatomia</hi> of, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>through they might have Experience ilk one to inſtruct another, and that none within the ſaid Burgh haunt, uſe nor exerce the Craft of <hi>Chirurgery,</hi> without he be expert and know perfectly the things above-written: and what perſon that ſhould happen to be Admitted Freeman or Maſters to the ſaids Crafts, or ſhould occupy any point of the ſamen, ſhould pay his Upſet at his Entry, with an Dinner to the Maſters of the ſaids Crafts, at his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and entry amongſt them, exceptand every Freeman Maſter of the ſaids Crafts, one of his lawful gotten Sons to be free of any Money paying, except the Dinner to be made to the Maſters after he be Examined and Admitted by them as ſaid is. <hi>Item.</hi> That no Maſter of the ſaid Craft ſhall take any Prentice or fied man to uſe the <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> Craft, without he could both Read and Write, and the ſaids Maſter of any of the ſaids Crafts that takes any Prentice, ſhould pay at his entry 20 ſhilling <hi>Scots</hi> Money, and that no Maſter of the ſaid Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft ſhould reſet nor receive any other Maſters Prentice nor Servant while the Iſh of his Terms be run, and who that does in the contrair thereof, als oft as he fails, ſhould pay 20 ſhilling but favour. <hi>Item,</hi> That every Maſter that is received Freeman to the ſaids Crafts, ſhould pay his weekly Pennies, with other dues mentioned in the ſad Seal of Cauſe, and every Servant that is a Fied man to the Maſters of the ſaid Craft ſhould pay ilk week one half penny, and that the ſaid Incorporation ſhould have power to choiſe their own Officer to paſs with them, for ingathering of their quarter &amp; weekly pennies, &amp; to paſs before them at their Occaſions, and gatherings, ſicklike as other Craffts within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> has, and that one of the Maſters of the ſaids Crafts, ſhould paſs with the Officer of the ſamen, at all times needful, and lift and raiſe the ſaids Quarter Payment fra every perſon that owe the ſamen, and give any diſobeys, that they might Poynd and diſtrenȝie them, therefore haveing an Officer of the ſaid good Town with. <hi>Item,</hi> that no Maſter nor Free-man of the ſaids Crafts, Purchaſs any Lordſhip in contrair the Statutes and Rules above Written in hindring Skaithing of the Crafts foreſaids, orcomon weell thereof, under the Pain of Tinſel of their Freedoms. <hi>Item</hi> that all the Maſters, Freemen and Brethren of the ſaids Crafts, reddily obey and come to their Kirk Maſter and Deacon, at all time when they ſhall be required therto, be the ſaid Officer for to hear quarter Compts, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe any thing concerning the comon weel of the ſaids Crafts, and whoſo diſobyes the ſamen ſhould pay twenty Shillings Money foreſaid, as the ſaid Seal of cauſe of the Date foreſaid containing diverſe and ſundry others Heads, Articles and Clauſes at mair lenth proports. Likeas his Majeſties Royal Progenitor, <hi>James</hi> by the Grace of God, King of Scots by his Letters of Ratification, given under his Privy Seal of the Date at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 13th day of <hi>October,</hi> 1506 years, direct to the Provoſt and Baillies of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for the time being or that ſhould happen thereafter, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for the time, and to all and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry others his Officers, Leidges and Subjects Ratified, Authorized, and confirmed for him and his Royal Succeſſors, the foreſaids Rules and Statutes, contained in the Seal of Cauſe abovementioned, and the ſamen Seal of Cauſe granted to the Maſters men of Chyrurgeon and Barbar Craft, in the haill Points and Articles thereof, after the Forme and Tennor of the ſamen, and ſtraitly Charged and Commanded the ſaids Provoſt Baillies, and others his Officers Leidges and Subjects, that they nor none of them ſhould take upon hand to do or attempt, any thing in contrair or breaking of the ſaids Statutes and Rules, or his ſaid Confirmation, made and given thereupon in any ways in time coming, under all the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Pain, and Charge that after may follow. Atour, if any of the ſaids Crafts-men, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byed or did any ways come in contrair the ſaids Satutes, the ſaids Provoſt and Baillies then preſent, and thereafter that ſhould be recommended to Compel them to obey and fulfil the ſaids Statutes, as effeirs in all things after, the Forme and Tennor of the ſaids Seale of Cauſes, under the pains foreſaids, as the ſaids Letters of Ratification of the Date foreſaid at more tenth bears. And ſicklike <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of Scots, be her Letters of Gift
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:179812:4"/> under the Privy Seal of the ſaid Kingdom of the Date the 11th day of <hi>May,</hi> the year of God, 1567 years, for the Cauſes therein nominat, gave and granted Licence to all, and ſundry Chyrurgenos, Inhabitants of the ſaid Burrows of his tRealm then preſent, and to their Poſterity for the time being Chyrurgeons, whilks ſhould be able and qualified Perſons, and who after Examination before the Deacone and Brethren of that Occupation, within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that ſhould be found able and worthie, To uſe and Exerce the ſaid Craft and no others, that they ſhould nought bear Armour, nor paſs in Battel in any Hoaſts, Roads gathering Aſſemblys, Wapon ſhawings or Weirs, to be made by the Kings and Queens of the ſaid Realme, or their Succeſſors, or their Lieutenants or wairdanes be Burgh Sea or Land, within the ſaid Realme, not out with the ſamen &amp; alſe Licence, to them fra all Compirance, and paſſing upon any Inqueſts or Aſſyzes in Actions Criminal or Civil, Juſtice Heirs, Juſtice Courts, Shireff Courts, Burrows Courts, or others for Serving of the Breives, appriſings of Lands or any other manner of Actions whatſoever, except ſua far as concerns the Judgment, and fight of their ſaid Craft, allenerly Eximand, and Diſcharging them there Frae in all time coming, and witted and granted the ſaids Chyrurgeons then preſent, and their Poſterity of that Occupation, nor none of them ſhould be called, nor accuſed therefore, nor Incurr any Danger or Skaith there thorow in their Lands, perſons or Goods or any otherways in time coming, notwithſtanding of any Acts, Statutes and Proclamations or Charges ſpeciall, or general made or to be made in the contrair, or any pains contained thereintil, anent the whilk the ſaid Queen did diſpenſe, with them and their Poſterity for ever, Diſcharging them and their Succeſſors. Chyrurgeons being for the time of all Action Crime, that may be impute to them or any of them, their throw diſcharging alſo, alland ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry our Admirals, Wardens Lieutennants, Shireffs, Stuarts, Crowners, Juſtices, Juſtice-Clerks Theſaurer, Theſaurer Clerks, Provoſts, Aldermen, and Baillies of Burrows, and all other Officers, and Miniſters of the Laws and their Deputs preſent, and to come of calling Attaching, Arreſting, Summoning, Adjourning, Poynding, Troubling or Intrometting with the ſaids Chyrurgeons then preſent, and their ſaids Succeſſors of that Craft, or any of their ſaids Lands or Goods in any ways in time coming, for the ſaid remaining at home, or not paſſing upon Aſſizes or Inqueſts as ſaid is, (except as is before accepted) and of their Offices in that part for ever, as in the ſaids Letters of Gift of the Date foreſaid at more length is contained. <hi>And in like manner,</hi> His Majeſties deareſt Grandfather King <hi>James</hi> the 6th. of ever Bleſſed Memory, by his Letters of Ratification, ſuperſcribed with his Majeſties Royal Hand, and ſubſcribed by the Lords of his Majeſties Exchequer, of the Date at <hi>Greenwich</hi> the 6th. day of <hi>June</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3 years, Ordained a Letter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Confirmation to be paſt under the Seal of the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Favours of the Incorporation of the ſaids Chyrurgions of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and their Succeſſors, Ratifying their Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges in manner after-mentioned. And accordingly his Majeſties deareſt Grandfather, by His Letters paſt and expede under the ſaid Privy Seal of the Date foreſaid, Ratified, and for His Majeſty and His Highneſs Succeſſore, perpetually Confirmed. The ſaids Letters made and granted by the ſaids Provoſt and Baillies of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Council thereof, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their ſaid common Seal of Cauſes, of the Date above-mentioned, to, and in Favours of the ſaids Chyrurgions and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> from all and ſundry the foreſaids Priviledges, Freedoms, Liberties and Immunities above-written, at length ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in the ſaid Seal of Cauſes, and Ratified and Approved, and for him and his ſaids Succeſſors, perpetually Confirmed the foreſaid Letter of Ratification and Approbation, made and granted by the ſaid dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> King <hi>James</hi> the Fourth, of moſt worthy Memory, under the Privy Seal of the ſ id ant ent Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> of the Date foreſaid where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the foreſaids Rules, Statutes and Priviledges, contained in the ſaid Seal of Cauſes, are confirmed, and in like manner Ratified and Approved, and for Him and His ſaid Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, perpetually Confirmed the ſaid Letter of Exemption, made and granted by the ſaid deceaſt Queen <hi>Mary</hi> his deareſt Mother of worthy Memory, under the Privy Seal of the ſaid Kingdom, of t e Dare above-mentioned, Exeeming the Chyrurgions from bearing of Armour, paſſing in Battel, and from Reads, Hoſts, and Gatherings, Aſſemblies, Wars, and Weapon-ſhowings, and from paſſing upon Aſſiſes and Inqueſts in Actions Criminal or Civil, and containing the other Priviledges above mentioned, together with all Acts and Decreets given by the ſaids Provoſt and Baillies of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in Favours of the Deacon and Brethren of the ſaids Chyrurgions and Barbars within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> with all that has followed, or may follow thereupon, in all and ſundry Heads, Clauſes, Articles, Conditions and Circumſtances thereof, after the Forms and Tenors of the ſamen in all Points, as the ſaids Letters of Ratification of the Date foreſaid, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Diſpenſation anent the Validity of the foreſaids Writs thereby Ratified, and the not Inſerting thereof, and ſeveral other Heads and Clauſes at more length proports. <hi>And as</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:179812:4"/> the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by an Act made and granted by them, of the Date the 20 Day of <hi>August</hi> 1575 years, mentioning, <hi>That after Adviſement had by them, with the Supplication given in to them by the Deacon and Brethren of the Chyrurgions and Barbar-Craft,</hi> bearing, <hi>That it is ſpecially provided in the Seal of Cauſes, and others, Gifts and Priviledges, that none ſhould Occupy, nor uſe the ſaid Craft, nor no Point thereof, unleſs he were a Freeman of the ſaid Craft, within any part of the Priviledges of the Burgh.</hi> Nevertheleſs the hail Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh, daily uſe &amp; exerce the ſaid Craft of Chyrurgery, they neither being Freemen thereof, nor priviledged thereto, neither having Speculation nor Knowledge thereintill, to the great hurt of the Leiges who in their Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies may come to their hands. Therefor the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies and Council of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> Ratified and Approved the foreſaid Gift under the Seal of Cauſes, of the Date a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-written, and for more ſtrengthning thereof, and haill Cauſes therein contained, they by their ſaid Act, Diſcharged the ſaids Apothecars, and all others not Freemen Chyrurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not tryed not admitted by them, of all uſing and exercing the ſaid Chyrurgion and Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar-Craft in time coming under the Pain of 40 ſhillings, ſo oft as they be apprehended in contraveening of the ſaid Gift. And ordained the Officers of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to concur with the ſaids Chyrurgions and Barbars, and their Officer, in Poynding for the ſaids Unlaws, as the ſaid Act at more length bears. And further, the ſaids Provoſt, Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by another Act dated the 10th day of <hi>September</hi> 1641 years, Conſidering that it is as well expedient for the good of the Leiges who Reſide out with the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and not within the Liberties pertaining to the ſaid Burgh, <hi>That in the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter belonging to the Art of Chyrurgery, they be provided with skilful and honeſt men, and not left to the Arbitriment and Impoſture of Women and Ignorants.</hi> Therefore the Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of the ſa d Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> did inhibit and Diſcharge all and ſundry perſons whatſomever, not being Free-Men of the Chyrurgions of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and who have not given ſufficient proof of their qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and knowledge in the ſaid Art of Chyrurgery, of all uſing and exerciſing of any point of the ſaid Art, within the Bounds and Priviledges pertaining to the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and appointed the Magiſtrats of the ſaid Burgh to be Judges in all Controverſies which ſhould ariſe betwixt the Inhabitants of the ſaids Bounds, and the Brethren of the Chyrurgeons and Barbar Craft foreſaid, as in the ſaid Act of Council of the Date foreſaid at mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e length is contained <hi>Attour</hi> His Majeſties deceaſt Father King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bleſſed Memory and His Eſtates of Parliament, conveened in <hi>Anno</hi> 164<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> years, by Act of Parliament, <hi>Intituled Act and Ratification in Favours of the Chyrurgeons and Barbars of</hi> Edinburgh, Dated at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 17 Day of <hi>November</hi> 1641 years, ratified and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, &amp; for him &amp; his Succeſſors, perpetually confirmed all &amp; whatſoever Priviledges, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Immunitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, made, given and granted by the Provoſt, Baillies and Council of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burgh</hi> under the Common Seal of Cauſes, of the Date, the 1ſt Day of <hi>July</hi> 1505 years to and in Favours of the ſaids Chyrurgeons and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and ſpecified in the ſaid Sale of Cauſe, and alſo ratified and approved the Letters of Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Ratification, granted by <hi>K. James</hi> the Fourth of moſt worthy Memory under his Highneſs Privy-Seal, of the Date, Tenor and Contents above-mentioned. And ſicklike ratified and approved, and for him and his ſaids Succeſſors, perpetually confirmed by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Approbation and Confirmation made and granted by the Deceaſt K. <hi>James</hi> the ſixth, His Majeſties ſaid Grand Father, under his Privy Seal at <hi>Greenwich</hi> of the Date a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove-written, whereby his Deceaſt Grand Father willed and granted, and for him and his Succeſſors, Decerned, Ordained and Declared the foreſaid Letter under the Common Seal of Cauſes of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Letter of Ratification thereof, made and granted by K. <hi>James</hi> the Fourth to be good, valid and effectual to the ſaids Chyrurgion &amp; Barbars in all time coming, together alſo with the ſaid Act, Dated the tenth Day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1641 years, whereby the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies and Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> did In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite and Diſcharge all and ſundrie perſons who were not Free-men Chyrurgion-Barbars, from uſing or exerciſing any point or part of the Chyrurgion or Barbar Craft, as well with out the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Liberties thereof, within the haill Bounds of the ſamen, as within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> it ſelf, and whereby the Magiſtrats of the ſaid Burgh are declared Judges competent to all Differences that may atiſe betwixt the Inhabitants of the Bounds of the Liberties foreſaids, and the Brethren of the ſaid Craft. And further, His Majeſties ſaid Deareſt Father of ever bleſſed Memory, and his Eſtates of Parliament conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the manifold inconveniencies that did ariſe, by reaſon of a number of Merchant Men and Women, who at their own hands without Liberty, never being bred in the Art
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179812:5"/> of Chyrurgery, take upon them to exerciſe the Duties and Points of that Art within the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to the great hazard and loſs of the Lives of many good Subjects, and to the great hazard; hurt and prejudice of the Brethren of the ſaid Craft: Therefore His Majeſties Deareſt Father with Advice and Conſent of the ſaids Eſtates of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, did Diſcharge all and whatſoever perſons (except the Free, Men of the ſaid Craft in <hi>Edinburgh</hi>) to uſe and exerce any Point of the ſaid Art of Chyrurgery within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or any Suburbs about the ſamen or belonging thereto, and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, with power to the Deacon and Maſters of the ſaid Art then preſent, and to their Succeſſors in all time thereafter to come at all times convenient paſs, ſearch, take and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all ſuch perſons, exercing the ſaid Art within the ſaid Burgh, Suburbs and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction thereof foreſaid, not being Free-Men of the ſaid Art within the ſaid Burgh, and to cauſe them ſet Caution to deſiſt in time coming, and if they failȝie, to unlaw them in the Sum of Twenty Pounds <hi>Scots</hi> Money <hi>toties quoties:</hi> And this was ordeined to be done with concourſe of the Magiſtrats of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and the ſaids Magiſtrats are ordained to be Judges in all contraverſies that ſhould ariſe hereanent, betwixt the ſaids Chyrurgions and Barbars, &amp; any within the ſaids Bounds, and als are ordained to concur with the ſaids Chyrurgions and Barbars, to the effect foreſaid, als the ſaid Act of Parliament of the Date foreſaid at more length proports. <hi>Moreover,</hi> the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by their Act Dated the 8th Day of <hi>December</hi> 1643 years, mentioning, that <hi>Forſomeikle as,</hi> it having come to the knowledge of the Provoſt, Baillies and Counſel of the ſaid Burgh that there were diverſe Differences likely to ariſe betwixt the Deacon and Brethren of the Chyrurgions on the one part, and the Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh upon the other part, and eſpecially anent the cureing of all kind of Impoſthumes, Ulcers, Fractures, Diſlocations; Cancers, Imbalming of Dead Corps, Applying of Spara-Draps, Cureing of Varrol, Scurvies, Water-Cankers, Diſeaſes of the Hernia, Buboes, making of Phlebotomie, applying of Ventoſes, Fomentations, Loch-leeches, Canters, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicatores, Applying of Plaiſters, and all other manual Operations, which were thought by the ſaids Chyrurgions properly to pertain to their Art, and yet were uſed indifferently by all the Apothecaries within the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and thereby was like to grow to an great Rent and Diviſion betwixt the ſaids Chyrurgions and Apothecaries, which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt and Baillies and Counſel of the ſaid Burgh fore-ſeeing, and being willing to preveen the ſamen: <hi>Therefore</hi> they appoint certain perſons of their own number to Conveen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them both the ſaids Parties, and to try and cognoſce what did properly belong to the ſaids Chyrurgions, and after conveening of both Parties, and hearing of them, and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Righls, and after Report of their procedure to the ſaid Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> &amp; after calling and compearing of both the ſaids Parties, and their conſenting to the ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, the ſaid Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Decerned and Declared, that the Application of Cere-Clothes to Dead Bodies within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Liberties contained in the ſaid Chyrurgions Gift, ſhould properly belong to the ſaids Chyrurgions, and that it ſhould not be lawful to any Apothecary nor their Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vants in their Name to apply the ſaid Cere Cloth, nor to them to direct any to apply the ſamen: And ordained the ſaids Chyrurgions if they ſhould be imployed by the ſaid Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, to apply any Cere-Clothes made by them, not to refuſe the ſamen: And alſo De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerned and Ordained that all manual Operations and Applications about Dead or Living Bodies of Men, Women or Children, ſhould properly, and only belong to the ſaids Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions, And Diſcharged the ſaids Apothecaries and their Servants from the uſing and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercing of any Operations or Applications in the particulars Above rehearſed, about the ſaids Bodies of Men, Women or Children, as the ſaid Act of the Date foreſaid at more length proports, <hi>And als</hi> the ſaid Provoſt, Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by another Act, Dated the 20 Day of <hi>April</hi> 1649 years, Taking to their conſideration the prejudice which the Free-Men Chyrurgions and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh did ſuſtain by the Un Free-Men Chyrurgions and Barbars in the <hi>Cannongate, Leith</hi> and other Suburbs &amp; Pendicles of the ſamen, They did therefore by the ſaid Act require the Baillies of the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nongate, Leith,</hi> and others Suburbs within their Juriſdiction, ilk one of them for their own parts to be aſſiſtant to and to concur with the Deacon of the Chyrurgions and Barbars within their ſeveral bounds foreſaid, and that none ſhould exerciſe the ſaid Craft, nor put out Signs nor Baſons, while they obtained Liberty from the ſaid Craft, and were ſubject to the Orders &amp; Injunctions of the Deacon and Free-Men of the ſaid Incorporation of the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as the ſaid Act at more length proports. <hi>Likeas,</hi> the ſaid Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179812:5"/> Provoſt, Baillies and remanent Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by an other Act Dated the 27 Day of <hi>June</hi> 1649 years, appointed the Deceaſt <hi>John Denholm</hi> then one of the Baillies of the ſaid Burgh to go down to the <hi>Cannongate</hi> with Umquhile <hi>James Borthwick,</hi> then Deacon of the Chyrurgeons, and to ſee Courſe and Order taken with the Unfree-Men, there, and with the Unfree Men Barbars in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> conform to the foreſaid Act and Order, of the Date the ſaid 20 Day of <hi>April</hi> 1649 years foreſaid, and that in reſpect that the Baillies of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> had ſlighted the ſaid Ordinance, as the ſaid Act of Council of the Date foreſaid at more length bears: <hi>And ſicklike</hi> the ſaid Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by an other Act, Dated the 8th Day of the Moneth of <hi>July</hi> 1649 years, did call before them <hi>Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riest<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Andrew Robertſon, John Stevenſon, and William Burn</hi> Barbars of the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> and being demanded by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> what Right they have to exerce the ſaid Art of Chy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rurgery and Barbar Craft within the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> They abſolutely denyed that they did exerciſe any point of Chyrurgery, but Barbar-craft allanerly and ingeneouſly declared in preſence of the ſaid Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that they had no Right to exerciſe that Craft, and that neither they nor that Calling were ever erected in an Company, not ſubject to a Deacon, but that they and their Authors and Predeceſſors did exerciſe the Trade at their own hand allanerly, without any Freedom, Tollerance, War and, Power, or Authority had, or obtained fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e any of their Superiors in time bygone, and therefore the Provoſt and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Fand and Declared that the foreſaids perſons Barbars in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> had no Liberty to exerciſe the Trade within no part of the Bounds, pertaining to the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as in the ſaid Act of Council at more length is contained. <hi>And likewiſe</hi> the Baillies of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> by their Act, Dated the 22 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1649 years foreſaid, Ordained the Barbars of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> to take in their Signs, until they become obedient to the Deacon and Trade of the Chyrurgions of <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly <hi>Robert Prieſt, John Stevenſtone, Andrew Robertſon, John Bowſtone, Robert Yule</hi> and <hi>Andrew Turnbul,</hi> Barbars in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> Compeared before the ſaids Baillies, and willingly, and of their own accord, did in Obedience to the foreſaids Acts and O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ders, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves thereto, and were willing to ſubject themſelves to the Deacon and Craft of the Chyrurgeons of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> their Orders and Injunctions as in the ſaid Act at more length is contained. <hi>And in like manner,</hi> the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by another Act Dated the 12th day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649 years, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the foreſaids Acts above-written, mentioning, that notwithſtanding of the ſaids Acts, the Baillies of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> had done no Diligence againſt Unfreemen; therefore the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ordain the Baillies of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> Regality and Barony of <hi>Brughtoun</hi> the Baillies of <hi>Leith,</hi> Barony of <hi>Portſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> and other Pendicles within the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and their Succeſſors, or their Officers in their Names, within their ſeveral Bounds <hi>reſpective</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to give their Concurrance to the Deacon of the Chyrurgions and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in taking Order with the Unfreemen Chyrurgions and Barbars, and all ſuch as were Diſobedient to their Orders and Injunctions, within their ſeveral bounds <hi>reſpective</hi> above written: and eſpecially ordained the Baillies of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the Perſons above-nominat, and the Barbars within their bounds and all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, from taking upon hand to exerciſe the ſaid Art of Chyru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gery or Barbar Craft, and from putting out Signs and Baſons in time coming, till they obtain Liberty from the Chyrurgions, and Barbar-Craft of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> under the Pain of Impriſonment of their Perſons, and paying of 20 <hi>lib.</hi> of Unlaw <hi>toties quoties,</hi> and farther Cenſure as effeirs. <hi>And ſicklike,</hi> ordained the Baillies to take in their Signs and Baſons, and to compel them to Obedience. And in caſe the ſaids Baillies ſhould happen to neglect or ſlight their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then, and in that caſe, the Magiſtrats of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or the Deacons of the ſaid Chyrurgions and Barbars of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> with Concurſe of the Officers of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> are Authorized by the ſaid Act, to paſs to the ſaid Burgh of the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nongate,</hi> and reſpective places foreſaid, and to Diſcharge the ſaids Unfreemen and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them, and all other Perſons whatſoever, exerciſing the ſaid Trade of Chyrurgery and Barbar-Craft, to the Obedience of the ſaid Act. And gave Power to ſearch and apprehend Unfreemen, and uſe Probation againſt them as accords of the Law, and to do all and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever other things requiſit, for curbing of the ſaids Unfreemen, and bringing them to due Obedience or Puniſhment; and ordained the ſaid Act to be extended againſt all Unfreemen within the haill Bounds of the Priviledge, and Juriſdiction of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:179812:6"/> Pendicles and Suburbs of the ſamen whatſoever, in time coming, as the ſaid Act at more length proports. <hi>And farther,</hi> the Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of the <hi>Cannon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> by an Act Dated the 2d day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649 years, did Statute and Ordain <hi>Robert Priest, Andrew Robertſon, Robert Yool, Robert Paterſon, William Wairſdail, John Forſyth, Andrew Turnbul, William Burn, John Mackmath, Charles Scot, William Wright, John Bouston, Alexander Smith,</hi> and <hi>John Stevenſtone,</hi> Unfreemen and Barbars in the <hi>Cannon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> to take in their Signs and Baſons, and to exerce no part of Chyrurgery, nor Barbar-Craft within the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> nor Priviledges thereof in no time coming, while they obtain Liberty, and were ſubject to the Orders and Injunctions of the Deacon and Freemen of the Chyrurgions and Barbars in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and ordain the Upſets and Entries of all that ſhould obtain Liberty, to exerce the Trade within the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> to the Will and Diſcretion of the Deacon and Trade of the Chyrurgions and Barbars of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and their Succeſſors, and alſo ordained that the Prentices of ſuch as ſhould enter, and give Satisfaction to the ſaid Deacon and Trade of the Chyrurgions of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhould pay no more for the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſsſhips than other Prentices, they always ſhewing a ſufficient Teſtimonial that they are Booked in the Books of the Incorporation of the Chyrurgions and Barbars of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and no otherways, as in the ſaid Act at more length is contained. <hi>Moreover,</hi> the ſaids Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> by another Act Dated the 7th Day of <hi>February</hi> 1649 years foreſaid, did Decern &amp; Ordain their haill Barbars of the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> to compear before the ſaid Deacon and Craft of the Chyrurgions of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> within their conveening houſes in the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and there to ſubſcribe an Act in the Chyrurgion and Barbar Crafts Books of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to underly and be ſubject unto all their Decreets and Ordinances bygone and to come, and to give their Oath before the ſaid Deacon and Craft for that effect, and that betwixt the date of the ſaid Act and the 13th day of the ſaid Month of <hi>September;</hi> with Certification to all theſe Unfree-men, who did not compear and give ſatisfaction to the ſaid Deacon and Craft in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and that they ſhould be left to the will and pleaſure and diſpoſing of the ſaid Deacon and Craft in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> for their Upſets and Entries, and all other Dues that ſhould happen to be impoſed upon them by the ſaid Deacon and Craft, and all other Unfreemen in time-coming, as in the ſaid Act of the date foreſaid at more length is contained. <hi>Attour,</hi> The ſaids Baillies of <hi>Cannongate,</hi> by another Act dated the 10th day of <hi>February</hi> 1654 years. Did Statute and Ordain, that every Prentice of the Barbers in the <hi>Cannongate</hi> ſhould pay no more but 10 Pounds <hi>Scots</hi> Money for their Burgeſhip of that Burgh, the ſaids Prentices always ſhowing an ſufficient Teſtimonial that they were booked in the Books of the Incorporation of the Chyrurgeons and Barbers of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and an ſufficient Teſtimonial of the Deacon and Incorporation aforeſaid that they have ſerved out their Time fully with their Maſter: And farder, the ſaids Baillies did Statute and Ordain, that the haill Prentices of the Barbers of the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> their Deſignations and their Burges Tickets, ſhould be Barbers allanerly, and not Chyrurgeons, as the ſaid Act at more length proports. And farder, the ſaid Provoſt, Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by another Act dated the 27th of <hi>June</hi> 1655 years, Did declare their ſaid Act above-written, of the date in <hi>December</hi> 1643, to extend to the whole Apothecaries, and their Servants, preſent and to come, as if they were ſpecially inſert thereintill; and alſo, that the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Unfreemen of the Chyrurgeons has no liberty but as Burgeſſes. And ſicklike, that the Operations and Applications contained in the Act of <hi>December</hi> 1643, upon the living and dead Bodies of Men, Women and Children, and the curing of the Diſeaſes therein-mentioned, as Tumors, Wounds, Ulcers, Luxations, Fractures, curing of Verols, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and their acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, by Operations Applications, Diet, Medicaments, and what elſe requiſite to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Cure, belongs properly to the Freemen Maſters Chyrurgeons of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> being tryed in Theory and Practice, ſworn and admitted to the degrees of Maſterſhip in Chyrurgery before the ſaid Incorporation allanerly, and no other perſon whatſomever: And therefore did Statute and Ordain, that whatſoever Apothecaries, or their Servants, or any other perſons whatſoever, who are not Freemen Chyrurgeons of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> ſhould be found guilty of uſing or exercing any Cure, Operation, or Application Chyrurgical foreſaid, or any part or point of their Calling, within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> Liberty, or Juriſdiction thereof, that they ſhould be puniſhed, and lyable in payment of the ſaid Unlaw of 20 Pounds Money foreſaid, conform to the Act of Parliament, ſo oft as the ſamine ſhall be proved againſt them <hi>pro ut de jure,</hi> upon Complaint one or moe <hi>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo facto</hi> without any furder Proces of Law: And ſeing that <hi>William Jackson,</hi> Servitor to <hi>John Hamilton</hi> Apothecary was found to have contraveened the ſaid Act of <hi>December</hi> 1643, the ſaid Provoſt, Baillies and Council, ordained him to pay the ſaid Unlaw of 20 Pound <hi>toties quoties</hi> for ilk Fault, and referred the furder Cenſure of his Misbehaviour to the Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. <hi>Likeas,</hi> The ſaid Provoſt, Baillies and Council, did by the ſaid Act, Ratifie and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179812:6"/> Approve the whole former Acts of Council made and granted in favours of the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as if the ſamine had been ſpecially inſert in the ſaid Act; and ordained Intimation thereof to be made to the Apothecaries, or any others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein, that none might pretend ignorance of the ſamine, as in the ſaid Act at more length is contained. Conform to the whilk Act, the ſaid <hi>William Jackson</hi> being fined by the Baillies, in the Sum of 40 Pounds <hi>Scots</hi> Money for two Faults committed by him, in apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Couters and letting of Blood at two ſeveral times, being upon a ſingle Complaint, the one Fault confeſſed by himſelf, and the other refuſed by him to declare, upon being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to his Declaration, and having payed the foreſaid Sum of 40 Pound to the Baillies of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> they did ſend by the hand of <hi>James Gray</hi> one of their Officers, the Sum of 20 Pounds, as being the equal half of the ſaid Fine, to the deceaſt <hi>William Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> Deacon of the Chyrurgeons of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> for the time, to be applyed by him for the uſe and behove of the ſaid Incorporation of the Chyrurgeons, conform to their Seal of Cauſes, Rights and Priviledges above-mentioned, as authentick Inſtruments taken thereupon in the Hands of <hi>Robert Adamſon</hi> Nottar Publick, of the date the 10th day of <hi>September</hi> 1655 years, at more length proports. <hi>And in like manner,</hi> the ſaid Provoſt Baillies &amp; Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by another Act dated the 25 day of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1657 years, proceeding upon an Supplication given in to them by the Apothecaries and the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> did Statute &amp; Ordain, that from thence-forth no perſon ſhould be admitted to the Profeſſion &amp; Practice of the Art of Apothecary within the Burgh of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> or Liberties thereof, but ſuch as (having obtained the Freedom of being Burges and Gild-Brother of the ſaid Burgh) ſhould make their Addreſs by Petition to the Council for their Recommendation to the Apothecaries and the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, and their Succe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s for their Tryal and Examined, and that Report ſhould be made by the Appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries and Appothecarie Chirurgeons and their foreſaids to the Counſel of their Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Qualifications in the ſaid Art, in which caſe the Counc l is to admit them to that Profeſſion; and for that effect the Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> gave Power, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand and Commiſſion to the ſaids Appothecaries, and Chirurgeon Appothecaries, and their foreſaids in all time coming, to Try and Examine the Abilities and Qualifications of all ſuch Perſons who intend to converſe with, profeſs and practiſe the ſaid Art within the ſaid Burgh and Liberties thereof, being recommended in manner foreſaid; And did Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and Ordain that no manner of Perſon, or Perſons whatſoever, within the ſaid Burgh and Liberties thereof, ſhould not preſume nor take upon hand to profeſs, nor practiſe the ſaid Art of Appothecary, or any part or point thereof privatly or publick y, who ſhould not be admitted and found Qualified in manner above-written, under the pain and puniſhment of the Contraveeners in their Perſons and Eſtates: And ſicklike, did Statute and Ordain, That the Baillies, one or moe for the time, with the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Gild,</hi> and two or more of the Appothecaries and Chirurgeon-Appothecaries, and their foreſaids, to be nominat &amp; appoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed by the Council, being Perſons of moſt approven Integritie &amp; Skill, ſhould from time to time viſit the Sufficiency of all ſorts of Drugs within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Liberties thereof, and Seize upon ſuch Drugs as they ſhould find inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, and Report the ſamen to the Council, whereby the Havers and Uſers thereof may be condignly puniſhed in their Perſons, Eſtates, according to the Quality of their Fault, and their Fines and Penalties to be applyed to the Uſe of the Good Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as the ſaid Act of the Date foreſaid at more length proports. And als the ſaid Provoſt and Baillies of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by their Act dated the <hi>ninth</hi> day of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1660 years, mentioning that it pleaſed the Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to make choice of the deceaſt <hi>Arthour Temple</hi> Chirurgeon, to be one of the Captains of the ſaid Good Town of <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> And ſeing that by the Laws and Cuſtoms of moſt part of Kingdoms and Nations, Men of that Profeſſion are allways Exeemed from any ſuch Charge and Office; Their Calling being ſuch, wherein the very Lives of People are concerned, beſides that the ſaid Incorporation of the Chirurgeons having many and divers antient Rights, Liberties, Priviledges and Immunities granted to them and their Succeſſors; and Ratified by Kings, Queens and Parliaments of this Kingdom. And therefore, the Deacon and Brethren of the ſaid Incorporation of the Chirurgeons, by Their Supplication given in to the Council of the Good Town, did deſire that they would make choice of others to be their Captains, and to Supplie their other Offices and Places of that ſort, and that the Chirurgeons might be Free thereof in all time coming, and that they might have the full Imployment and peaceable Poſſeſſion of all their ſeveral Rights, Priviledges, Immunities and Exemptions granted and Ratified to them, and Ratified in manner above-mentioned.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179812:7"/> The ſaid Council of the Good Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> having taken the ſaid Supplication to their conſideration, did find the ſamen Juſt and Reaſonable, and neceſſar for the Good of the Leidges, and for the Incouragement of the Chirurgeons to the due Tyes of their Callings; and therefore, did grant to the ſaids Chirurgeons, Free-men of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and their Succeſſors in that Calling, that they ſhould be free of all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or any Charge of that kind in all time coming; As alſo, that they ſhould have the full Imployment and peaceable Poſſeſſion of all their other ſeveral Rights, Privilidges, Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Exemptions granted, or Ratified to them by the Kings, Queens and Parliaments of this ſaid antient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or by the Good Town heretofore in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, within the ſaid Good Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or Liberties thereof. of whatſomever Date or Dates, as if the ſamen had been Repeated, and ſpecially Inſert in the ſaid <hi>Act,</hi> and that for them and their Succeſſors, Chirurgeons Free-men of the ſaid Burgh in all time coming. And did Statue and Ordain that none ſhould Moleſt them thereintil, nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge them of the ſame in time coming, under the Pains and Penalties, notwithſtanding of any Acts, practices, or any other thing elſe to the contrair, as the ſaid Act at more length bears; Likeas, in an Court of Juſticiary of the ſaid Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> holden within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> upon the <hi>ninth</hi> day of <hi>March</hi> 1674 years, by the Right Truſtie and well beloved Couſin and Counſellor <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Athole</hi> (now Marquiſs of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thole</hi>) His Majeſties Juſtice-General of the ſaid Kingdom for the time, and Sir <hi>James Foulis</hi> of <hi>Collingtoun</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>Robert Nairn</hi> of <hi>Strathurd</hi> Knight, Sir <hi>John Baird</hi> of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byth</hi> Knight, and Sir <hi>Thomas Wallace</hi> of <hi>Craigie</hi> Knight Lords Commiſſioners of Juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>John Joiſſie</hi> Deacon of the Chirurgeons of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> for the time for himſelf, and in Name &amp; behalf of the remanent Members of the Chirurgeons, and Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Apothecarie, within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> did preſent a Petition, ſhewing that notwithſtanding of the manifold Liberties, Priviledges, Immunities, &amp; Exemptions granted to the ſaid Incorporation of the Chirurgeons in manner above-written, Exeemand them from paſſing upon Aſſizes and Inquiſits Criminal and Civil, yet nevertheleſs ſeveral Members of the ſaid Incorporation were daily troubled and moleſted by the Officers of the Court of Juſticiary, and Summonds to compear upon Sizes without reſpect to their exemptions, as the ſaid Petition at more length bears; The ſaid Lord juſtice general, and Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Juſticiarie, having conſidered the foreſaid Petition, together with the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rights, Exemptions and Ratifications produced for inſtructing thereof, did diſcharge all Meſſengers at Arms, Macers of Court of Juſticiary and other Officers whatſomever, from Citing and Summonding of any of the <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to paſs upon Aſſizes and Inqueſts in Actions Criminal in time coming, and that conform to their Gifts and Rights above ſpecified, as an Act of adjournal made thereanent in favours of the ſaids <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> more fully bears: and ſicklike in an other Court of Juſticiary holden with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by the ſaid Sir <hi>James Foulis,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Nairn,</hi> Sir <hi>John Lockhart</hi> of <hi>Castle-hill,</hi> Sir <hi>John Baird,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Wallace</hi> above deſigned Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of Juſticiary, upon the 29 day of <hi>July</hi> 1674 years, anent criminal Letters rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, uſed and execute at the inſtance of <hi>Margaret Dalmahoy,</hi> Relict of the deceaſt <hi>James Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtone</hi> Glaſier in the <hi>Cannongate, James, Margaret, Kathrine, Agnes</hi> and <hi>Helen Ralſtone</hi> his children for themſelves, and in name and behalf of the remnant Kin and Friends of the ſaid Defunct, and his Majeſties Truſtee Counſeller Sir <hi>John Nisbet</hi> of <hi>Dirltoun,</hi> Knight then His Majeſties Advocat for his Highneſs intereſt in that matter, and <hi>William Maſon</hi> Maſon in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> then Priſoner in the Tolbooth of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> divers and ſundry of the Freemen <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> being called to give their opinion, whether the ſaid deceaſt <hi>James Ralſtone</hi> did die of wounds mentioned in the ſaids other cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal Letters, and they having given in their opinion in Write thereanent, it was alleged by the Advocats for the Purſuers, that no reſpect could be had to the foreſaid report, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the ſaids <hi>Cherurgeons</hi> were compearing perſonally and Deponing thereanent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for craved that the ſaids <hi>Chyrurgeons</hi> might be unlawed for their abſence, unto which it was anſwered, that the <hi>Chyrurgeons</hi> could not be unlawed nor forced to Depone, nor give their Oath anent their opinion, they being <hi>jurati magiſtri,</hi> and ſo the Oath given at their admiſſion behoved to have credit, as to what concerned the skill and faithfull diſcharge of their Employment, the Lords Commiſſioners of Juſticiary having conſidered the Premiſſes in reſpect that the <hi>Chyrurgeons</hi> cited in that caſe were not cited as Witneſſes to the Fact, but to give their opinion upon the quality of the wounds, and therefore by their Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitor refuſe to unlaw and amerciat the abſent <hi>Chyrurgeons,</hi> as in the Decreet and Proces led and deduced thereanent, and extracted under the Signe and Superſcription <hi>Manual</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:179812:7"/> of Mr. <hi>Robert Martine</hi> Clerk to the ſaid juſtice Court at more length is contained: and farder, His Majeſtie and Eſtates of Parliament of this ancient Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being conveened in <hi>Anno</hi> 1670 years, and taking to their conſideration, that the Art of Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie is an ancient worthy and free Art moſt neceſſary for the healths and Lives of the Subjects, and that the ſaid Incorporation of the Chirurgeons and Barbours of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi> are an able and famous incorporation, whereby the Leidges have found large experience to their great advantage, both in time of Peace and War: and that Pharmacie is an ancient free and neceſſary Art for the health of the Leidges, and that the Brotherhood of the Apothecary and Cherurgeon Apothecaries of the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> are an able and famous Brotherhood, and have given good proof thereof, Therefore, and for certain other good cauſes and conſiderations, his Majeſtie and the Eſtates of Parliament by an Act of Parliament dated the 22 day of <hi>August</hi> 1670 years, ratified and approved, and for his Majeſtie and his Succeſſors, with advice and conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually confirmed the whole Acts, Gifts, Grants, Rights, Priviledges, Liberties, Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties above and after mentioned, to wit, the ſaid Act made given and granted by the ſaid Provoſt Baillies and Council of the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> under their common Seal of cauſe, to and in favours of the Chirurgeons and Barbours of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi> dated the 1. day of <hi>july</hi> 1505 years, and whole Rights Priviledges and Liberties and Immunities therein contained, and als the ſaid Letter of Ratification and approbation made and granted by King <hi>James</hi> the fourth of worthy memory, under his Highneſs Privy Seal, of the date the ſaid 13 day of <hi>October</hi> 1506 years, and ſicklike, the ſaid Letter of Exemption made and granted by the ſaid deceaſt Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> of the date above mentioned, eximand the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> from bearing of Armour, paſſing in battle in any Hoſt, Reads, gatherings, Wars, Weapon ſhowing, and from all compearing and paſſing upon Inqueſts and Aſſizes in any Action criminal or civil, and in like manner, the ſaid Letter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation and approbation made and granted by King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth, his Majeſties Grand Father, of moſt bleſſed Memory, under his Highneſs privy Seall of the Date at <hi>Greenwitch</hi> aboveſpecified, confirmed to the ſaids Chyrurgeons and Barbars, the ſaid Act and Seall of Cauſes, Letters of Ratification granted be King <hi>James</hi> the Fourth, and Letter of Exemption foreſaid granted be the ſaid Deceaſt Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and likeas the foreſaid Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> made and granted be his Majeſties Deareſt Father of Eternal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, with advice and conſent of his ſaids Eſtates of <hi>Parliament,</hi> to and in favours of the ſaids Chyrurgeons and Barbars of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> of the Date the 17th day of <hi>November,</hi> 1641 years. And farder his Majeſtie with advice and conſent of the ſaids Eſtates of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Ratified and approved, and for his Majeſtie and his ſaid Succeſſors, perpetually confirmed to the ſaids Chyrurgeons and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that the Acts follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> Ane Act granted be the Provoſt, Baillies, and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> againſt Unfreemen Dated the ſaid 10th day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1649 years. <hi>Item,</hi> ane other Act granted be the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in their favors, anent their Rights, Priviledges, Liberties, and Immunities, and Prohibit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Unfreemen, Dated the 22 day of <hi>June,</hi> 1655 years. And alſo ane other Act anent the ſaids Chyrurgeons, and Barbars their Rights, Previledges, Liberties, and Immunities and Exemption of the ſaid Chyrurgeons fra Watchings Wardings, and others mentioned in the ſaid Act granted to them, be the ſaid Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Dated the ſaid 9th day of <hi>November,</hi> 1660 years. And farder his Majeſtie for himſelf and his ſaids Succeſſors with advice and conſent of the ſaids Eſtates of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Ratified Approved and Confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the foreſaid Act granted be the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> under the Seal of Cauſes, in favours of the Appothecars and Chyrurgeon Appothecaires, anent Viſitors, Examination of intrants, and Prohibiting of Unfreemen to Compone Drugs, and others therein mentioned, of the Date the ſaid 25th day of <hi>February,</hi> 1657 years, and one other Act granted by the ſaid Provoſt, Baillies and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for conveening, Regulating, and ordering of the ſaid Brother-Hood, Dated the firſt day of <hi>April,</hi> 1659 years. As alſo an other Act containing ane Oath tendered be the ſaid Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to the ſaids Intrants, at their Admiſſions Dated, the 18th day of <hi>March,</hi> 1664 year, and the haill Rights, Priviledges, Liberties, and Immunities reſpective contained in any of the ſaids Gifts, Grants, and Acts gaanted in favours of the Incorporation of the ſaids Chyrurgions and Barbars, and of the ſaid Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, and Apothecaries, or that may be any ways inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret, or conceaved in any of their Favours. His Majeſties with advice and conſent of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179812:8"/> Eſtates of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Ratified and approved, and for his Majeſtie and his ſaid Succeſſors, perpetually Confirmed all other Gifts, grants, Decreets, made and granted be his Majeſties Royal Predeceſſors, and all Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Acts of Borrows, and all and every one of the Acts of Courts, and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and others, and any Ratifications there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in favours of the ſaid Incorporation of the Chyrurgions and Barbars, and Brotherhood of the Apothecarie Chyrurgeons, and Apothecars of the ſaid Burgh, and every one of them, their Succeſſors, Children, Prentices reſpective, anent their Rights Liberties Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Priviledges of the ſaid Incorporation and Brother-hood reſpective of whatſomever Date, or dates Tenor or Contents, the ſamen be or bear with all that has followed or may, follow thereupon in all and ſundry the haill Heads, Points, Articles, Clauſes, proviſions circumſtances and conditions of all the ſaids Acts, Gifts, grants, Decreets, Ratifications and others particularlie and generallie abovementioned, granted in favours of the ſaid Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Brother-hood, or any of them after the Forms and Tenors of the ſamen in all Points, diſpenſand with the Generality of the ſaid Ratification. And his Majeſtie with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of the ſaids Eſtates of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Decerned and ordained the ſaid Ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Confirmation, to be alſe Valid, effectual and ſufficient to the fornamed Perſons, and their Succeſſors reſpective, as if all the ſaids Gift, grants, Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> Acts of Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows Decreets, and Acts of Court and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and others, and Ratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions foreſaids, were all and every one of them at length, and <hi>verbatim</hi> ſpeciallie and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie Inſert, ingroſſed and contained in the ſaid Ratification. Whereanent, and anent all other defects and imperfections, that could be proponed or alleadged in all Objections of Law, that could be moved againſt the ſamen. His Majeſtie with advice and conſent fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, not only Diſpenced, But alſo Renunced and Diſcharged the ſamen for ever, and gave full power to the ſaids Chyrurgeons and Barbars and Brother-hood foreſaid, of the ſaid Chyrurgion Apothecaries, and Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and their ſaid Succeſſors, to make uſe of all the ſaids Acts, or any of them without prejudice of one to other to their beſt behoofe and advantage, as they ſhal think fit, and for effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating better of the haill Premiſſes and ends foreſaids. His Majeſty with advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, ordains the Magiſtrats and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and their Succeſſors, to maintain the ſaids Chirurgeons aforeſaid, their Children, Apprentices and Servants, in their hail Rights, Liberties, Immunities and priviledges what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomever, granted in their favours; notwithſtanding that any of them ſhould exerce any other thing beſides, as Burgeſſes and Gild-brethren, and as if they did not the ſamen; And ſicklike ordained the ſaids Magiſtrats of the ſaids Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and other Judges, Sheriffs and Magiſtrats of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Sheriffdome thereof and their Officers to aſſiſt and concurr with the Deacon and Brethren of the ſaid Incorporation of the ſaids Chyrurgeons and Barbars, and with the viſitors and Brethren of the Brotherhood of the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, or any of them and their ſaid Succeſſors Reſpective, againſt any Perſon or Perſons, who ſhould exerce or practiſe any poynt or part of the ſaid Art Reſpective within the Liberties of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or any other place within the Sheriffdome thereof, without licence or freedome from them, under the Reſpective Seals and Clerks hands; the <hi>Major</hi> partie being an <hi>quorum,</hi> and againſt any perſon or perſons who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traveen any of the Reſpective Rights, Liberties and Priviledges within the Bounds fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaids; As alſo, any perſons amongſt themſelves, Contraveeners of their own Acts and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereafter, and to exact Fynes, Unlawes and Penalties therefore, from them and from other Tranſgreſſors as aforeſaid, and to ſearch, take, apprehend, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynd and waird them for the ſamen, the one half of the ſaids Fines of unfreemen, to belong to the Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and the other half of the ſaid Incorporation and the Brotherhood foreſaid Reſpective, and if any perſon ſhould find &amp; apprehend themſelves prejudged or wronged aither by the determination of the ſaid Incorporation or Brotherhood Reſpective, contrair to the Laws, Rights and Liberties, priviledges and power granted to them, or either of them, that then in that caſe, they ſhould have the recourſe of the Magiſtrats and Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> who may determine in theſe caſes for both parties, as in the ſaid Ratification and Act of Parliament at more length is contained, by vertue of the whilk Seal of Cauſes, Ratifications thereof, Letters of Exemption granted by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Letters of Confirmation and Approbation granted by King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth His Majeſties Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and Act and Ratification of Parliament granted by King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Father of eternal Memory, and hail other Acts, Gifts, Grants, Decreets of Court and Town Council of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and His Majeſties Ratification and Act of Parliament, granted in manner Above-mentioned, and be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:179812:8"/> of ſeveral other Acts, Gifts, Grants, Acts of Town Council, and Court of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Acts and Decreets of the Town Council and Court of the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> and Acts and Decreets of the Sheriff Courts of the Sheriffdome of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Acts and Decreets of the Baillie Court of <hi>Leith, Portsburgh</hi> and <hi>Poterraw,</hi> and Acts and Statutes made by the ſaid Incorporation of Chyrurgeons and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> amongſt themſelves, and by the ſaid Brotherhood of the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, and Apothecaries among themſelves, not above expreſt nor ſet down, and whilks are all holden as hereintill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and expreſt, as a part of this principal Lybel <hi>brevitatis cauſa.</hi> The ſaid Incorporation of the ſaid Chyrurgeons and Barbars of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Chyrurgeon-Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, Purſuers above-nominate, for themſelves and in name and behalf of the ſaid Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, and their ſaids Predeceſſors the Freemen Chyrurgeon Barbers and Chyrurgeons-Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> have been in peaceable Poſſeſſion of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Rights and Priviledges contained in their ſaid Seal of Cauſes, Gifts, Grants, Acts, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets, and others particularly and generally above-mentioned, paſt all memory of Man. And they and their ſaid Succeſſors Freemen Chyrurgeons and Barbers of the ſaid Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they ought and ſhould have the only Right and Priviledge to uſe and exerce the haill Operations and Applications contained in their ſaids Gifts, Grants, and others Writs and Rights, and particularly the haill Operations and Applications contained in the ſaid Act of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>December</hi> 1643, upon the living &amp; dead Bodies of Men, Women &amp; Children, and the Curing of their Diſeaſes ſpecially in their ſaids Rights, as Tumors, Wounds, Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Luxations, Fractures, curing of Verrols, and others above-written, and their Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, by Operations, Applications, Diet, Medicaments, and what elſe belongs thereunto, properly appertains to the Freemen Maſters Chyrurgeons of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> being tryed in Theory and Practice, ſworn and admitted to the Degrees of Maſterſhip in Chyrurgery by the foreſaid Incorporation allanerly, and to no other perſon or perſons whatſomever. <hi>Nevertheleſs,</hi> It is of Verity, that the perſons after nominate, ſimple Apothecaries, Unfreemen Chyrurgeons, Unfreemen Barbers, Perewig-makers, Gardiners, Country Leiches, Women, Ignorants and Impoſtures after deſigned, als well who have their actual Reſidence, Dwelling and Abode within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> and Liberties thereof, and bounds contained in the Gifts, Grants and Priviledges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovewritten, as theſe who Lurk, Skulk, Haunt and ſometimes come within and ſometimes without the Bounds foreſaid, and who are Vagrants, <hi>viz. John Kennedy</hi> Apothecary Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>E inburgh, John Fowlis</hi> Elder, <hi>Robert Campbel, Hugh Nielſon, James Aickenhead, James Laudin, Patrick Cunninghame, John Hepburn.</hi> Mr. <hi>James Mackmath,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alexander Hay, John Fowlis</hi> younger, <hi>Thomas Dalrymple,</hi> and <hi>Patrick Hepburn</hi> Apothecaries Burgeſſes of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh, Walter Porterfield</hi> Apothecary in the <hi>Cannongate, George Mackala</hi> Apothecary in <hi>Leith, Edward Cunninghame</hi> Peiriwigmaker in <hi>Edinburgh, James Robertſon</hi> Barber there, <hi>John Brown</hi> Gardiner in the Abbay of Holy-Rood-Houſe, <hi>Andrew Jackſon</hi> Gardiner in Weſt-ports burgh, <hi>James Heughſon</hi> Gardiner in the <hi>Pleaſants, George Bell</hi> pretended Chirurgeon in <hi>Edinburgh, Euphane Barton</hi> indweller in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and <hi>John Bigle</hi> her Husband for his Intereſt <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Wilſon</hi> Relict of the Deceaſt <hi>Hary Burn</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanni Baptiſta Quarantini</hi> and <hi>Johannes Michael Philo</hi> Montibanks and certain other perſons unfree Women Gardiners and Montibanks within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Liberties thereof who are holden as herein repeated <hi>brevitatis cauſa,</hi> dayly and continually take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to uſe and exerce the Practice of Chirurgerie, and all other Points and Practices uſed and exerced by the Chirurgeon Barbers and Chirurgeon Apothecaries within the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and als to uſe and exerce the hail Rights, Liberties, Immunities, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges belonging to the ſaids Purſuers Freemen foreſaids, albeit they have neither Right nor Intereſt to the ſame; And therefore it ought and ſhould not only to be found and declared by Decreet and Declarator of the Lords of Council and Seſſion, that the ſaid Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuers and their Succeſſors the Freemen Maſters, Chirurgeons and Barbers of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> being tryed in Theory and practice Sworn and admitted to the Degrees of Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in Chirurgerie by the ſaid Incorporation, and the Chirurgeon Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> have the only good and undoubted Right to bruick, enjoy and poſſeſs, uſe and practice the hail Rights, Liberties, Freedoms, Priviledges, Operations, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications and others contained in their Acts, Seals of Cauſe Exemptions, Ratifications, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets and other Writes particularly and generally abovementioned granted in their Favours and to uſe and exerce the hail Operations and Applications upon the Living and Dead Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of Men, Women and Children, and the cureing of all Deſeaſes, Incident and Accident to them particularly and generally above-mentioned and their Accidents by Operations, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:179812:9"/> Dyet, Medicaments, and others whatſomever belonging thereunto, and that the ſamen properly appertains to the ſaids Purſuers, Free-men and Maſters foreſaid and to their Succeſſors Free-men and Maſters being tryed in Theory and Practice, and Sworn and Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Degrees of Maſterſhip in time coming in manner above-written, and to no other perſon or Perſons, and farder it ought and ſhould be found and declared by the Decreet and Declarator of the ſaids Lords of Council and Seſſion, that the ſaids Purſuers may by themſelves their Deacon, officier and others not only apprehend any of the ſaids Defenders, if they can take them <hi>flagranti delicto,</hi> but that they may alſo cauſe cite them before the ſaids Provoſt, Baillies and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> or other Magiſtrats thereof, for contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening any of the foreſaids Priviledges, Liberties, Freedoms and others above-written, and refer the Contraventions foreſaid to the Oaths of the ſaid ſimple Apothecaries and others Contraveeners and Defenders above nominat, if the ſaid Purſuers think fit or to uſe all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of Probation againſt the ſaid Defenders and Contraveenrrs foreſaids <hi>pro ut de jure,</hi> and it ought and ſhould be found and declared, that the ſaids Defenders and all others concerned, ſhall be holden bound and oblidged to depone upon all the matters of Fact, that ſhall be particularly referred to their ſaid Oaths in their reſpective Purſuits. that ſhall be intented for the Contraventions, before the ſaid Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and als it ought and ſhould be found and declared, that the Provoſt, Baillies and Council of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> are the only Judges competent in the firſt inſtance to the ſaids Purſuits to be intent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt all Contraveeners, for contraveening any of the ſaids Purſuers Priviledges above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecified, and to diſcuſs the ſame Summarly, according to the Cuſtom of Burgh; And the Purſuers thier contraverted Practice in vindicating the Priviledges, but alſo, the ſaids Defenders above-mentioned, and all other Unfreemen, Gardiners, Women and others whatſoever, ought and ſhould be decerned by Decreet of the ſaids Lords of Council and Seſſion, to deſiſt and ceaſe from all uſing and practiſeing and exerciſeing of any Point, Part or Prctaice belonging to the ſaids Purſuers, and ought and ſhould be diſcharged by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet foreſaid, from taking upon them to Uſe, Exerce, or Enjoy any of the Rights, Liberties. Priviledges, Immunities and Exemptions given and granted to the ſaids Purſuers, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonging to them and their Succeſſors, after the form and Tenor of the ſaids Acts, Seals of Cauſes, Ratifications, Exemptions, Gifts, Grants, Acts of Parliament, Decreets and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Writs particularly and generally above-mentioned in all Points as is alledged as the ſaid laſt Summonds and Execution thereof likewiſe more fully bears, the ſaid Mr. <hi>James Nisbet</hi> for himſelf and in Name and behalf of the remnanent Brethren of his ſaid Trade, purſuers of the foreſaid Lybel, as likewiſe purſuers in the foreſaid Action of Declarator raiſed at their inſtance, and Defenders in the other Acton raiſed againſt them, <hi>Compearing</hi> be Sir <hi>George Mackenȝie</hi> his Majeſties Advocat, Sir <hi>John Lauder,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Colen Mackenȝie</hi> his Majeſties Advocats, their Procurators, who for inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foreſaid libel produced in preſence of the ſaids Lords, ane Condeſcendence made by the Chirurgeons upon the ſeveral acts of Contraventions done by the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame,</hi> whereby he had uſurped upon the priviledges only belonging to the free-men Maſters of the Art and Trade of Chyrurgery within the ſaid Burgh and Liberties thereof. 1. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> within this half year or thereby, did cure <hi>Barbara Hastie</hi> daughter to umquhil <hi>Heaſtie</hi> Stabler in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> of an broken Head, by applying Plaſters thereto and otherways. 2. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> did open an Vein to, and let Blood of the Lady <hi>Lee</hi> younger, within theſe five or ſix Months or thereby. 3. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninghame</hi> applyed Plaſters to the ſaid Lady <hi>Lee</hi> her Arme, the ſame being ſtrained or hurt by ſome Accident or other at or about the time foreſaid. 4. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> opened an Vein to, and let Blood of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> Servitrix to the ſaid Lady <hi>Lee</hi> within five or ſix Months or thereby. 5. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> opened a Vein to, and let Blood of the Earl of <hi>Carnwath,</hi> and applyed Lochletches one or moe, and Cauters one or moe to the ſaid Earl, within the ſpace of three years or thereby. 6. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> opened a Vein to, and let Blood of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Semple</hi> daughter to umquhil <hi>John Semple</hi> of <hi>Balgone,</hi> and applyed two Couters to her within the ſpace of this half year or thereby. 7. The ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> did frequently pance and dreſs <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> within the houſe of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> at the head of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> who had a wound in his Breaſt within theſe three or four yeass or thereby. 8. The ſaid <hi>Patrick</hi> did apply ſeveral Plaiſters, and that frequently to umquhil <hi>William Cunninghame</hi> elder Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> his fore-foot, within theſe three years or thereby, the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninghame</hi> opened an Vein to, and let Blood of umquhile <hi>Henry Cunninghame</hi> and his Spouſe, and applyed Couters, Plaſters and Oyntments to them within theſe three years or thereby,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179812:9"/> as the ſaid Condeſcendence extent in proceſs more fully bears, as alſo for verefying and inſtructing the Points and Articles of the foreſaids Summonds of Declarator, and the Rights of priviledges of the ſaid Incorporation adduced in preſence of the ſaids Lords the particular Writs under-written, conform to an Inventar thereof, whereof the Tenor follows, <hi>viz.</hi> The Seal of Cauſe, dated the 1. of <hi>July</hi> 1505, erecting the Chyrurgeons into an Incorporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> their Seal of Cauſe. <hi>Item,</hi> Letters of Ratification there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by King <hi>James</hi> the Fourth, under his Privy Seal, dated the 13 day of <hi>October</hi> 1506 years. <hi>Item,</hi> Letters of Exemption by Queen <hi>Mary</hi> under her Privy Seal, dated 13 <hi>May</hi> 1567. years. <hi>Item.</hi> Signatur by King <hi>James</hi> the 6th. ſubſcribed by the Lords of Theſaury, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining an Letter of Ratification to the above-written Rights, to be exped under his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Seal, dated 6 <hi>June</hi> 1613 years. <hi>Item,</hi> the Ratification following thereupon by King <hi>James</hi> the 6th, under his Privy Seal, dated the 6 of <hi>June</hi> 1613 years foreſaid. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in favours of the Chyrurgeons, dated 10 of <hi>September</hi> 1641 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Ratification in Parliament of the above-written Rights in favours of the Chyrurgeons, dated the 17 day of <hi>November</hi> 1641 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An other Act of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in favours of the Chyrurgeons dated the 8 of <hi>December</hi> 1643 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An other Act of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> againſt unfree-men in the <hi>Cannongate, Leith,</hi> and other Suburbs, dated the 20 of <hi>April</hi> 1649 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An other Act of the Council of <hi>Edinb.</hi> againſt the Barbers in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> dated the 27 of <hi>June</hi> 1649 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An other Act of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> againſt the Barbers in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> dated 18 day of <hi>July</hi> 1649 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Council of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> againſt their Barbers there, dated 22 day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649 years. <hi>Item,</hi> an Act of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> againſt the Unfreemen in the <hi>Cannongate,</hi> dated 12 day of <hi>August</hi> 1649 years. <hi>Item,</hi> Two Acts of the Council of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> againſt Unfreemen there, the one dated the 2d of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649, the other dated the 7 of <hi>September</hi> 1649 years, both upon one Parchment. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Council of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> in favours of the Apprentices of Barbers there dated 10 of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1654 years. An Act and Decreet of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in favours of the Chirurgeons againſt the Apothecaries, dated the 27 of <hi>June</hi> 1655. <hi>Item.</hi> An Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Deacon <hi>Burnet</hi> againſt <hi>William Jackson</hi> anent his two Fines, the one the 10 <hi>Septem.</hi> 1655. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> erecting the Chirurgeon-Apothecaries, Apothecaries into an Brother-hood under the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> their Seal of Cauſes, dated the 25 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1657 years. <hi>Item,</hi> Exemption by the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in favours of the Chirurgeons, dated 9th <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1660 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of Adjournal in favours of the Chirurgeons, dated the 9 day of <hi>March</hi> 1674 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Extract of the Proceſs purſued before the Lords of Juſticiary by <hi>Margaret Damahoy,</hi> againſt <hi>William Maſon,</hi> dated the 29 of <hi>July</hi> 1674 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Ratification in Parliament in favours of the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, of their hail Rights. dated the 22 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1670 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> againſt <hi>John Savage</hi> Unfree-man, dated the 4 day of <hi>July</hi> 1638 years. <hi>Item,</hi> An Act of the Baillies of the <hi>Cannongate</hi> againſt <hi>William Steven</hi> Unfree-man, dated the firſt of <hi>January</hi> 1653 years. <hi>Item,</hi> Condeſcendence by the Chirurgeons upon the Deeds of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travention committed by <hi>Patrick Cunninghame, Item,</hi> an Summonds of Declarator the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> againſt the haill Apothecaries and others Unfreemen, with the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof, of the Date 1681 years, as the ſaid Condeſcendence extent in proceſs more fully bears as alſo for verefying and inſtructing the Points and Articles of the ſaid Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds of Declarator, and the Rights and Priviledges of the ſaid Incorporation adduced in preſence of the ſaids Lords the particular Writs above ſpecified, and the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninghame</hi> Defender in the foreſaid Libel, &amp; he &amp; the remanent Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh, Defenders of the foreſaid Action of Declarator, raiſed at the ſaids Chyrurgeons their inſtance. &amp; Purſuers in the other Action of Reduction &amp; Declarator raiſed at their inſtance againſt them. Compearing by Sir <hi>George Lockheart,</hi> Sir <hi>John Dalrymple,</hi> and Mr. <hi>David Cunninghame</hi> Advocats their Procurators, the foreſaid Lybel and mutual Summonds of Declartor raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by both the ſaids Parties in manner above-re-hearſed with the Condſcendence above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, and particular Writs and Evidents produced for Inſtructing the ſaid Chirurgeon Apothecaries their Rights and Priviledges in manner above-ſpecified, together alſo with the ſeveral Debates and Interlocutors following thereupon in manner under-written, and together with the ſeveral Supplications and Anſwers made thereto, with the Inſtructions of the ſamen given in by either Parties in manner, and to the effect after-mentioned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all at length heard, ſeen and conſidered by the ſaids Lords; and they therewith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well and ryply adviſed; The ſaids Lords of Council and Seſſion, have found and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and hereby finds and declares that the Chirurgeons have the only Right of <hi>Phiboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:179812:10"/> within the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and upon the Burgeſſes thereof, except in the caſes of Neceſſity and charity, and that where there is no Inciſion made upon dead Bodyes, and that there is only Wrapping of the Body required, the Apothecaries makers of the Cerecloths may wrap the Bodies, but where Inciſion is made, the Application is proper to Chirurgeons of the Cerecloths to the Body; And finds and declares that the Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chirurgery and Pharmacy being two diſtinct Imployments, and both requiring a great deal of care and knowledge, ſhall hereafter (within the City of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Liberties thereof) be Exerciſed by diſtinct Perſons, and that one and the ſame Perſon ſhall not Exerciſe, or be Imployed in both Imployments; and that albeit Chirurgeons may buy and ſell Samples as any Drogeſts or Merchants may do, and Compone ſuch Drogs as are neceſſar for Chirurgical and External Applications, yet that they cannot compone any <hi>Medicament</hi> to be taken internally by the Mouth, exceptand always from this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, all the preſent Chirugeon Apothecaries that are preſently actual Maſters in both Imployments, and does actually keep Shops within the ſaid Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties thereof, as to which Bounds this Declarator extends: And no farder, as alſe, have declared, and Ordained the ſaid Chirurgeon Apothecaries Maſters, who as ſaid is, are allowed the Exerciſe of both Imployments during their Lifetime, and <hi>James Muirhead, John Lauder</hi> and <hi>Thomas Edgar,</hi> who are declared to be in that Condition, albeit they be not as yet actually entered Maſters in both Imployments, and to declare their Election betwixt and <hi>Tueſday</hi> next; And if they do not betwixt and the ſaid day, the ſaids Lords Decerns them to ſit only at the Chirurgeons Table as the Eldeſt and firſt erected Trade; and have found, and finds that no Maſter can hereafter take Prentices to make them Free-Men in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in any of the ſaids two Imployments, except that at which they ſit at the Table; and that all the Prentices already entered are to be Free only in that Imployment and Trade, at which their Maſters ſits at the Table; <hi>Becauſe</hi> that after the ſaid Libel firſt intented before the ſaids Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> being Advocat of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as ſaid is. There was an Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords by the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame, Shewing</hi> that where the Supplicant was lately Warned by one of the Town Officers to Compear before the Baillies in their Juſtice of Peace Court on the Afternoon, at the Inſtance of Mr. <hi>James Nisbet,</hi> preſent Deacon of the Chirurgeons of the ſaid Burgh, to be unlawed and Fined for alledged operating in Chirugery, and in which Procedure he was Informed, the Baillies would upon his Appearance Summarly prove his Delict by his Oath, and immediately Charge him to the Tolbooth, without ſo much as allowing him an formal or written Libel with the benefite to Anſwer there againſt, and ſo fix a fault of contravention of their alledged Priviledges upon him, by no other way of Probation, but a preſent judical Oath, which is, and ought to be Sacred to all, and more deliberately digeſted before given, then immediately to be Adminiſtrat to, and preſſed upon one hurried, but from off the Streets <hi>hoc vel maximae atento,</hi> that the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicant was herein Challenged for no nottar particular, or nominated Crime, but moſt what of Picque to pleaſe the Humours of the Chirurgeons <hi>in regenerali dubia &amp; invidioſa,</hi> their Priviledges and manner of proving the Contraveening, and incroaching thereupon, having never as yet been by the ſaids Lords of Council and Seſſion, the only Judges com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent thereto, lawfully as is requiſite declared, whereupon (with all juſt reſpect to the Magiſtrars and their Authority; but becauſe of the ſtrange and unlawful Methods of the Chirurgeans probation) having in a Bill of Advocation meaned himſelf to the ſaids Lords, the Lord <hi>Forret</hi> then Ordinary, was pleaſed to fiſt Procedure till the 24th. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, as the foreſaid Bill and Signature thereupon, here preſent to ſhow Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies: And we ſeing the Point did reſolve in that whether or not, the <hi>Petitioner</hi> was obliged ſummarly by his judicial Oath to fix delict, and we to Fine and unlaw upon the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner at the humour of, and when ever called by the <hi>Chirurgeons;</hi> whereunto it was humbly conceived, that the Petitioner could not be obliged by Law but that if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt againſt the Petitioner for operating in Chirurgery, the burden of the probation lyes upon them, and without a particular Statute and Law for that effect, it was humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived no Subject can by the act of any inferiour Court or Incorporation, be obliged to give his Oath upon a delict, either for affixing any <hi>Stigma</hi> upon the Petitioners reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or damnifying the Petitioner in a pecunial Fine, and as the Petitioner has neither ſeen by what ground law or warrand, the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> come to be authorized thus ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marly to exact Oaths, ſo might the ſaids Lords but conſider the danger of the Subjects, and what a door of temptation ſuch methods and practices may open to perjurie, eſpecially when Chirurgical operations and operating in Chirurgerie, are ſo ambiguous terms, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179812:10"/> the <hi>ultimum</hi> and <hi>minimum</hi> terms of them hath never yet been defyned; and it is hard for the Petitioner who ſerved his Apprentiſhip to <hi>James Borthwick,</hi> and with him learned and ſaw ſomething of Chirurgery, when he is with a Patient, be he never ſo near a Friend, or poor or indigent perſon who may be in a dangerous condition, and of an earneſt mind to breath a Vein or ſuch like, eſpecially performing the ſamen <hi>gratis,</hi> to know how to give an ſummar Oath upon Chirurgical operations, for in its latitude it reaches to the leaſt plaiſter for a cutted finger or ſcratch of a Pin, and although the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> ſhould have foiſted in the taking of an Oath, in ſome acts of the Town Court, yet the ſamen cannot in Law be done, either by acts of their own calling, or Acts of the Town, to introduce upon his Majeſties Leidges, ſuch a ſtrange and unuſual and dangerous manner of probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and although ſome ſuch latent Acts might be ratified in the ratification of the <hi>Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons</hi> Right and Priviledge, yet Ratifications <hi>nihil novi juris addunt,</hi> and are ſtill given <hi>ſalvo jure cujuſlibet;</hi> and this caſe being of ſo univerſal concernment to his Majeſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to prove delicts, and ſo from them exact Fines upon Oaths firſt, but impoſed by and moulded in inferiour Courts Judges and Incorporations, for their own advantage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in concerned, as the ſaid Supplication more fully bears, which being read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having heard ſeen and conſidered the ſamen, remitted the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof to the Lord <hi>Forret</hi> one of their own number, before whom the Bill of Advocation of the foreread Lybel was preſented, and to call the Deacon of the <hi>Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> before him to have anſwered thereto, and to have done therein according to Juſtice, and in caſe of difficulty to have reported: and thereafter in obedience to the foreſaid ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, both the ſaids Parties having compeared before the ſaid Lord <hi>Forret,</hi> by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Procurators above named, the ſaids Procurators for the Deacon for himſelf, and in name and behalf of the remnant Brethren of his Trade, for inſtructing the Rights and Priviledges of the ſaid Incorporation produced in preſence of the ſaids Lords, the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Writs above written conform to the Inventar thereof, particularly above narrated, with the foreſaid Condeſcendence upon the ſeveral Acts of contraventions done by the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame,</hi> and thereafter repeated the foreſaid Lybel, and craved Decreet conform to the ſaid Condeſcendence, To which it was Anſwered and alledged for the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame,</hi> and remnant Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh, by their Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors above named, that they were not oblidged to debate until the Act of Advocation were given out with the Proces, and the ſamen ſeen and returned, and come in by courſe of the Rol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Whereunto it was replyed for the ſaids <hi>Chyrurgeons,</hi> that notwithſtanding of the ſaid alledgeance, the Defenders muſt either debate, or then the Purſuers muſt have Decreet, becauſe the cauſe being advocat of conſent of the Purſuers, and <hi>eſto</hi> there were an Act of Advocation put up and Extracted, yet the only ground whereupon the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuers did Advocat was, that it was agreed to, that the cauſe ſhould be inſtantly diſcuſed, and the Lord Ordinary thereupon did cauſe the Purſuers to produce the Writs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they found their Priviledges, and two ſeveral dyets appointed by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to debate, and the above written Bill was opponed given in by the Defender himſelf, wherein he craved the point might be inſtantly diſcuſt, and the Lords thereupon remitted the ſame to the ſaid Lord <hi>Forret</hi> to have heard both Parties, and diſcuſſed the ſame, or Reported. To which it was Duplyed for the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hame</hi> by his ſaids Procurators to the foreſaid Reply, They opponed the conſtant Practique in the like Caſes, and the Bill and Deliverance thereof did only relate to the Reaſons of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; which Diſpute above-written, being heard and conſidered by the ſaid Lord <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> he made <hi>Aviſandum</hi> thereupon to the haill Lords. And upon Report thereof made by him to them, wherewith the ſaids Lords being well and ripely adviſed, they ordained the Cauſe to be ſummarly diſcuſſed (without attending the order of the Roll, in reſpect the ſaid Defender <hi>Patrick Cunninghame</hi> did deſire the ſame in his Bill,) and before the ſaid Lord Reporter, and thereafter conform to the foreſaid Interloquitor, the Cauſe being again called in preſence of the ſaid Lord <hi>Forret,</hi> and both the ſaids Parties compearing by their reſpective Procurators above-named, the Purſuers Procurators repeated the particular Condeſcendance above-written given in by them by way of Libel, and craved Decreet againſt the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, in reſpect he refuſed to depone. To which the Defenders Procurators anſwered and alledged, That there could be no Proces ſummarly ſuſtained upon any ſuch Condeſcendance, there being no previous Citation or Libel, and the Purſuers Seal of Cauſe and other Rights produced cannot ſtate them in any better condition then the reſt of the Incorporation in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh,</hi> who are not in uſe, nor cannot ſummarly attack any perſon, but red-hand, or <hi>fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granti crimine;</hi> and the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> cannot indulge the Chyrurgeons with any Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179812:11"/> contrary to Fundamental Laws, which the Purſuers pretend to by the ſummar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure, in calling free Burgeſſes, and conveening them to depone <hi>ſuper inquirendis.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it was Replyed for the ſaids Purſuers, that the foreſaid Alledgance ought to be repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, in reſpect of the Purſuers Rights ſtating them in their Rights, with their Priviledges, which cannot be taken away ſummarly: and the Purſuers by vertue of the ſaids Rights, have been in the conſtant uſe of exerciſing their ſaids Priviledges againſt all Unfreemen, and the circumſtances of their Calling, was the ground whereupon the ſaids Priviledges were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it being impoſſible to attack Unfreemen in their Calling, as in other Incorporations. And which laſt Diſpute above-written, being alſo heard and conſidered by the ſaid Lord Reporter, he made <hi>Aviſandum</hi> thereupon to the ſaids Lords; and they upon Report thereof, made by him to them. Declared they would hear the Cauſe debate in their own preſence, and to that effect ordained the ſame to be inrolled in the Roll of Cauſes to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſt; and accordingly the ſaid Action being inrolled, (and having come in by the courſe the Roll of Cauſes to be diſcuſt,) was called <hi>in preſentia;</hi> at which time both the ſaids Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties having likewiſe compeared by their reſpective Procurators above-named, the Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries repeated the foreſaid Summonds of Declarator raiſed at their inſtance, and for inſtructing thereof, repeated the production formerly made by them of the particular Writs above-mentioned, which are of the ſeveral dates, tenors and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents <hi>reſpectivè</hi> libelled upon in the foreſaid Summonds; As alſo, they repeated the foreſaid Action before the Baillies of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> againſt the ſaid <hi>Patrick Cunninghame,</hi> for the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Contraventions condeſcended on, and craved he might be holden as confeſt, in reſpect he refuſed to depone. Which Action being Advocat. They then inſiſted in the ſame, as likewiſe in the foreſaid Action of Declarator of the Chyrurgeons their privilidges, upon the ſeveral priviledges contained in the Seal of Cauſe, and other Rights granted to them by the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> who by their Erection have power from the King to grant the ſame, and which Seal of Cauſe is ratified by King <hi>James</hi> the 4th, under the privy Seal, upon the 13 day of <hi>October</hi> 1506, and by King <hi>James</hi> the 6th likewiſe under the privy Seal upon the 6th of <hi>June</hi> 1613 years, and the Act of Town-Council dated the 10th of <hi>February</hi> 1641 years, and ratified in Parliament the 17th of <hi>November</hi> the ſame year, and ſeveral other Acts of the Town-Council in their favours, for the better exerciſing their Calling, which are all ratified in parliament upon the 22 day of <hi>August</hi> 1670 years, and whereof they have been in the controverted poſſeſſion, as is inſtructed by ſeveral Sentences before the Town-Court of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinburgh</hi> againſt the Contraveeners, wherein they craved it might be declared, that the ſaids Chyrurgeons have the ſole priviledge of the exerciſing of Chyrurgery, and that all others Unfreemen might be declared, and that they might call the Contraveeners before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, and uſe all legal probation againſt them, and that ſummarly, conform to their Rights and Cuſtoms of Burgh, and the above-named Procurators for the ſaids Apothecaries likewiſe Repeated the foreſaid Summonds of Reduction and Declarator raiſed at their inſtances, by way of Defence: In which they inſiſted, <hi>Primo,</hi> Upon that Concluſion of the foreſaid Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, that they cannot be obliged to depone for thir Reaſons, 1. That it might involve the perſons alledged Contraveeners in Perjury, ſeing it cannot be imagined that they can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member every individual Act. 2. It would oblige them to diſcover the Diſeaſes &amp; Conditions of their Patients, which were abſurd &amp; contrary to that Secrecy which their Calling obliges them to. <hi>Tertio,</hi> all the other Trades within the Town, and in all other places, that have as great Priviledges as the Chrurgeons can pretend to, are not allowed to call them Freemen upon Oath, as to their Encroachments upon their ſeveral Trades, but all that is allowed them, is to Seaſe the Work, and if they can deprehend them in the Act, to puniſh them. <hi>Secundo,</hi> they Inſiſted in the ſecond Ground of Declarator, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Chyrurgeons might hold them by their own Trade, and might not exerciſe the Art of both Chyrurgery and Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy for thir Reaſons. <hi>Primo</hi> in no well governed City, one and the ſame Perſon is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to Exerce diſtinct Trades. <hi>Secundo,</hi> if the ſame were allowed here, the Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being both Chyrurgeons and Apothecaries, would render the Apothecaries Employment as <hi>de facto.</hi> They do altogether inſignificant, ſeing they as Burgeſſes can be Apothecaries when they pleaſe, and the Apothecaries cannot be Chyrurgeons, without they ſerve an Apprentiſhip, or Marry a Chyrurgeons Daughter, albeit they were never ſo well qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Art of Pharmacy being the nobler Art, as being converſant about the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the Man, ought to have rather greater, as leſs Encouragements as Chyrurgeons. <hi>Tertio,</hi> they Inſiſted on the third Ground of their Declarator, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Liberty of making and applying of Searcloths to dead Bodies, ſhould be declared proper to them, in reſpect that the Searcloth is a Drug, and is not made uſe of for any Chyrurgical Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179812:11"/> being applyed only to dead Bodies. And Inſiſted likewiſe upon the fourth Ground of Declarator, <hi>viz.</hi> That it ſhould be Declared, that the Apothecaries has the only Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Adminiſtrating of Phyſick inwardly; and that Phlebotomy common to them, is the Chyrurgeons, in reſpect that Phlebotomy is often requiſit in Inward Diſtempers, with which the Chyrurgeons does not meddle, and ſometimes muſt be ſo ſpeedily Adminiſtrat, as cannot admit of ſo much time as to ſend for a Chyrurgeon, without eminent Danger of the Patients Life, as in <hi>Pluraſies</hi> and other violent Diſeaſes. To which it was Replyed for the Chyrurgeons, That notwithſtanding of the Defence, <hi>Patrick Cuninghame</hi> muſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pone, or be holden as confeſt, nor cannot be Declared, that the Contraveeners of the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons Priviledges, ſhall not be obliged to Depone, in reſpect that by the Purſuers their Seal of Cauſes, it is expreſly provided that they may uſe all legal Probation againſt the Contraveeners, and that the Oath of Party is a legal Probation, cannot be contraverted. <hi>Secundo,</hi> They have been in conſtant Poſſeſſion of this manner of Probation, the Deeds of Contravention being always within cloſs Doors, and often under ſilence of night per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in a ſudden, and leaves not Work behind it that may be apprehended as other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Trades does. And it is of no Weight, to pretend that it would be the Occaſion of diſcovering Patients Diſeaſes, for any that has a mind to conceal their Diſeaſes may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy a Freeman, and ſo not incur the hazard. But to take off all Caval, the Purſuers do Declare, that they are content it be Declared, that Unfreemen ſhould not be obliged to Depone upon Contraventions in general, but where the Acts are particularly lybelled, as is particularly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one in <hi>Patrick Cuninghames</hi> caſe here, which is a Confeſſion more as in Law can be required, ſeing Oaths in general, are frequently taken in things of leſs concern, as Mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>-O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ths, cutting of Wood, killing of Fiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As to the ſecond Ground of the Declarator, <hi>viz.</hi> Chyrurgeons ſhould not be Apothecars. <hi>It is anſwered.</hi> That the ſame is abſurd, for thir Reaſons. <hi>Primo,</hi> For Erecting of the Fraternity produced, (for they are no Trade, and have no Seal of Cauſe as other Trades have) any Burgeſs of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> if he were a Black Smith, if free to be an Apothecary, if he be able to undergo a Tryal, and it were ſtrange to allow it to all Burgeſſes, to deny it to the Chyrurgeons, who of all Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes are preſumed to underſtand it beſt. <hi>Secundo,</hi> By the Erection of that Fraternity, it appears that the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries were the great Procurers, And that they taking to their Conſideration, that the Leiges were abuſed by unskilful Perſons, taking upon them to ſell and prepare Drugs, did procure the ſaid Erection of a Fraternity, excluding unskillful perſons that could not bide a Tryal. <hi>Tertio,</hi> By the ſaid Erection of the Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, it appears that the Apothecars were ſo far from being conſidered as a Trade, that they have not power of their own Tryal, but the Entrants muſt apply to the Town Council, and they appoint the Tryers; and they pay no Money for their Freedom, nor do they enter their Prentices amongſt the Trades but in the Gildrie as other Merchants do; and though they were a Trade as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are not, it is abſurd to pretend, that if a man ſerve a Prentice, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways acquire his Freedom in two Trades, he may not ſerve in both or either as he pleaſeth, as Merchants, Taylors, and ſeveral other Inſtances. As to the third Ground of Declarator, <hi>viz.</hi> That the making and applying Cere-Cloths ſhould be declared proper to Apothecaries, <hi>It is anſwered, Primo,</hi> The Purſuers oppones the Seal of Cauſes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rights Lybelled, whereby all the external Applications of Mens Bodies is declared properly to them. And the pretence that a Cere-Cloth is a Drugg of no Weight for the ſame may be pretended of all Plaiſters, which uncontravertedly belongs to the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons. <hi>Secundo</hi> It is already determined by the Town-Council, who by King and Parliament are declared Judges in all theſe controverſies, who have allowed the making to Apothecaries, and the application to Chyrurgeons. And have provided, that if the Chyrurgeon refuſe to apply the Cere-Cloths the Apothecaries makes, then the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are free to apply themſelves, which is more as the Apothecaries could in Law acclaim the Application being properly Chyrurgical, even where the Body is not eviſcerat, where Chyrurgical Inſtruments is neceſſar for ſtopping the Opens of the Body, and making In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions, in particular caſes where a Chyrurgeons skill is neceſſary, and Embalming is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways uſed in all Bodies, and Ligators, which are not only proper, but is one of the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lareſt Arts of Chyrurgery. And it is of no Weight that it is a burden to the Leidges, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is very well known, and is provided by the Act of the Town-Court, That the Chy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rurgeons are to be imployed by the Apothecaries, and gets their acknowledgement from them, which they cannot refuſe. <hi>Likeas,</hi> as there are many that being both Apothecaries and Chyrurgeons, where the Leidges deſires only to have one imployed, To the Fourth Ground of Declarator, <hi>viz,</hi> That it ſhould be declared that the Apothecaries have the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179812:12"/> Application of Medicine inwardly. <hi>As Likeways</hi> have the uſe of Phlebotomie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with Chyrurgeons. To which it is anſwered, That by the Erection and by all the Rights Lybelled, the Chyrurgeons have the ſole power of Applications, Operations, and Medicaments, requiſite for compleating the Cure of thoſe Diſtempers, which are particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly narated in the Act One thouſand ſix hundred and fourty three. And it were abſurd to ſay that they could have the ſole Cureing of a Diſtemper, and not the power of applying what is neceſſar for it, either outwardly or inwardly. And all that they pretend to, is the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Medicaments for Cureing of the Diſtempers contained in their Rights, which are known by proper diſtinct Names to be ſuch as falls under the Chyrurgeons skill, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the World, And it was never before alledged that Phlebotomie was not properly a Chyrurgical-Operation. And it is but a Frivolous pretence, that in ſome caſes as in Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies it can admit of no delay; For it is well known, that within <hi>Edinburgh</hi> it is more eaſie to find a Chyrurgeon as an Apothecary, nor did ever the Chyrurgeons trouble any un-Free-Man in drawing of Blood in caſes of neceſſity, nor uſing of the firſt Panſing upon bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Legs or Arms, which is always permitted to be done by them that are neareſt: and then Chyrurgeons is to be called at the ſecond Application: Whereunto it was Duplyed for the Apothecaries by their Procurators, That albeit by the Seal of Cauſes the Chyrurgeons has ſeveral priviledges; As power to make Free-Men by Prenticeſhips, to keep a Box, &amp; yet the particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riviledges now inſiſted on are not there expreſſed, and ſo are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>term<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned by the Lords. To the which Duply above-written, The ſaids Procurators for the Chyrurgeons opponed their former Reply, and their Rights whereupon they Found, which does ſufficiently determine all the points now contraverted, and remitted the ſame to the ſaids Lords their Conſideration, Which haill Diſpute above-written being heard and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered by the ſaids Lords, they before adviſeing thereof, Recommended to the Lords Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſter <hi>Newtoun</hi> and <hi>Caſtlehill,</hi> to call for Dr. <hi>Stevenſon</hi> Elder, Dr, <hi>Hay,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Balfour,</hi> and to hear their Opinions as to the points contraverted betwixt the Chyrurgeons and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries with their firſt convenience, and thereafter to report. <hi>Thereafter</hi> there was a Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords by the ſaid Dr. <hi>James Nisbit</hi> Deacon oi the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons of <hi>Ed nburgh</hi> for himſelf, and in Name of the remanent Maſters and Brethren of the ſaid Incorporation, <hi>Shewing</hi> That where in the mutual Declarator raiſed by the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons, and Chyrurgeon Apothecaries againſt the ſingle Apothecaries, and by them againſt the Petitioners. The Petitioners having Founded upon their Seal of Cauſe, and parti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cular Acts and Priviledges granted to them by the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to their Seal of Cauſe <hi>Anno</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and fourty three, and one thouſand ſix hundred and fifty five, long before the Settlement of the Fraternity of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries, Having undoubted Right and Priviledge to exerciſe all manual Operations and Applications upon the Living and Dead Bodies of Men, Women and Children, and that excluſive of all perſons within the Burgh, who are not Free-Men of their Art: And containing alſo ſeveral Specialities, whereunto the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Apothecaries at the time were conſenting, and to which all of them ſince have Acquieſced and Confirmed, except a few Claudiſtine Contraventions, of which when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice was had, the contraveeners were Fined, and being informed that the Petitioner upon conſideration of the Debate; Have thought fit to recomend to ſome of the ſaids Lords, their number to call three Phyſicians and hear their Opinion anent the proper Bounds, and limites of theſe two Arts. As to which the Petitioners humbly repreſent, to the ſaids Lords. 1. That if the Chyrurgeons, and Apothecaries had been erected in ancient and diſtinct Crafts or Arts, within Burgh in general Terms, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch an Society and Companie, ſhould be Chyrurgeons, and ſuch an Society and Company Appothecaries, and that a queſtion had then ariſen betwixt them in any Point or Points, which each of them had contended to be ane Proper Point of their Arts, or to be common to both; That in ſuch a caſe of general Gifts and conceſſions, their might be ſome ground of Calling Phyſicians to give Opinion in what might be proper to either calling or common to both, but here it is uncontravected, that the Chyrurgeons have moſt anciently formed and erected Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Craft, injoying Priviledges and Freedoms, which no Burges nor Gild Brother in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> can partake of, unleſs he Serve an Apprentiſhip in the ſaid Art, or be the Son, or Marie the Daughter of ane Free-man, and on the other ſide, that the Apothecaries were never ane diſtinct calling or Art, but allenerly Burgeſes and Gild Brother, and had never any Priviledge beyond ane Burges and Gild brother, ſo that any Gild Brother might have Set up for an Apothecarie when he pleaſed, until the year 1657 that a tryal was thought fit and neceſſar, in order to which they were Erected in a Brother-hood,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179812:12"/> jointly with the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries. And whereof, notwithſtanding of their Erection any Gild Brother, who can bide a tryal may be a Member at pleaſure, and that the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons have and injoy their calling and Craft, not only in general, as a Craft, but alſo in a clear Deſignation of the Subject of their Calling, <hi>viz.</hi> All Operations and Applications about the bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And more particularly in the Cureing of the ſpecialitys expreſt in their Gifts, and grants, and that <hi>Excluſive</hi> of all others, in that they could humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave their is no neceſſity to call for the Opinion of Phiſicians anent the Bounds or Limits of their Callings, ſeing their Gifts, and Grants, does alſe ſpeciallie, diſtinctly, and clearly deſign the ſame as Mens Wits, or words can expreſs; And therefore ſince he queſtions not whither ane Apothecary may not have alſe good Skill, to apply an Serecloth, or draw Blood as a Chyrurgion has, neither was the queſtion whether ane Apothecary, <hi>qua</hi> Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie may apply Plaiſters, as well as make them, or cure Tumors Verrols, and ſuch like, but that the only queſtion is whether manual Operations and Applications upon the Bodys, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And particularly Phlebotomie Application of Serecloths Cureing of the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialitys mentioned in their Gifts, is not only proper and due to them, to exerciſe by their ſpecial Gifts, and grants Excluſive of the Apothecaries and all others, the interpretation of their Rights, and grants needs not the Opinion of ane Phyſician, when the Terms and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are clear, for though all the Phyſicians of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhould affirm that an Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie, <hi>qua talis</hi> may aply an Searcloth, draw Blood, Cure the Verrols ſwellings or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, yet certainly the ſaids Lords in point of Right, muſt find that the Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> cannot do the ſame, becauſe the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> who by their Erection from his Majeſtie, are intruſted to give particular Seals of Cauſe, Rights and Priviledges to Crafts and Callings Excluſive of all others, having given theſe Priviledges to Chyrurgeons in clear and expreſs Terms, and they having injoyed the ſame now, theſe two hundred years Excluſive of all others, the ſame eannot be taken from them, without Violation of their Rights, even altho the Priviledge of its own nature, were Conſonant to the nature of Pharmcie, or of a mixt Nature equallie applicable to Pharmacie or Chyrurgerie, and far leſs can theſe Priviledges be drawen in queſtion by a Fraternity Erected, within theſe twenty four years, who have not the Priviledge to exclude any Burges that can bide a try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and then the Chyrurgeons Priviledges, are ſpecially declared be the Town, before their erection and conſented to be the Apothecaries, and bruiked and injoyed both before and ſince the erection, be the Chyrurgeons Excluſive of all others until this time. 2. The Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners humbly Repreſents to the ſaids Lords, that it is noture and known, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries have a greater dependance upon Phyſicians than Chyrurgeons have, for Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons do and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y by the Priviledge of their Art and Calling, operate without any depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon Phyſician, and needs not, nor are they bound and tyed, to call for any Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, but if they pleaſe whereas an Apothecarie <hi>qua talis,</hi> neither ought nor can Adminiſter Phyſick without the advice of an Phyſician, and the diſpenſatorie Art in the practiſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, abſolutly depends upon the Phyſicians Recept, ſo that with all deference and reſpect to the Phyſic ans, the Chyrurgeons have juſt reaſon to ſuſpect, that they will be more favourable in their opinion to the Apothecaries, and ready and willing to inlarge their priviledges, who have ſo abſolute an dependance upon them; And it is notour and known, that the Phyſicians have frequently endeavoured to Erect themſelves in a Colledge, and to extend their own priviledges, to the Impairing of both, and therein they have been ſtill oppoſed by the Chyrurgeons and Chyrurgeon Appothecaries, and thereupon may be preſumed to bear the Supplicants no good will, craving that the ſaids Lords would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to conſider the grounds of the Supplicants Declarator <hi>in jure</hi> as the ſamen is founded upon their Seall or Cauſe, Gifts, Grants and Acts, and their immemorial Poſſeſſion, which the Supplicants humbly conceaves, are very clear and expreſs, and which ought not to be altered upon the opinions of Phyſicians, but muſt be judged according to the Law of the Kingdom, and the nature and conception of their Gift, as the ſaid Supplication more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bears, which being Read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having heard and ſeen and conſidered the ſamen refuſed to give their Anſwer <hi>in jure</hi> until the ſaids Lords ſhould Report; But they recomended to the fore-mentioned Lords, in their ſaids laſt Interloqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to call the three Phyſicians therein named with Doctor <hi>Burnet</hi> upon Monday next thereafter, and to have heard their opinion on the contraverted poynts; And to to have made report thereof on tweſday following, in obedience to the which ordinance and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terloquitor above-written; The ſaids Lords nominated as ſaid is, having called and taken the opinion of the ſaids Phyſicians, anent the contraverted Poynts, contained in the two ſeveral Declarators Above-mentioned; And thereafter upon Report made by them to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179812:13"/> ſaids haill Lords <hi>in preſentia</hi> wherewith, &amp; with the haill Diſpute Above-written, they being well &amp; reiply adviſed; The ſaids Lords of Council &amp; Seſſion, found that the Chyrurgeons has only Right of Phlebotomie within the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and upon the Burgeſſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, except in the caiſes or neceſſity and charity: But Declared, that they would hear both Parties, if the ſaid priviledge ſhould extend to ſtrangers living within the Town, or to Burgeſſes living in the Suburbs, but found that where there was no inciſion made upon dead Bodies, and that there is only wrapping of the Body required, the Apothecaries, makers of the Cere-cloath may wrap the Bodies, but where inciſion is made, the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is proper to Chyrurgeons of the Cere-cloaths to the Body, and as to the other two poynts, <hi>viz.</hi> The probation of the contraventions by Oath, and the ſeperating of the Trades and Incorporations of Chyrurgerie and Pharmacy, the ſaids Lords declared they would thereafter hear both parties thereupon, and thereafter, there was an other Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords, in behalf of the ſaid Chyrurgeons, Shewing, that although the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners doe not contravert, but that if the matters concerning the Cere-cloaths, had not been decyded by the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> there might have been place for conſulting with Phyſicians, as to Cere cloaths; and to whom the Application thereof ſhould belong, ſo that the Petitioners conceives the ſaid Lords their Interloquitor as founded upon the nature of the Thing, and the Opinion of the Phyſicians was no way controverted, but it was hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly repreſented to the ſaids Lords, that this Debate was founded upon the Priviledges grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as having Right from his Majeſty to grant the ſame, is yet intire, and that becauſe neither did the Lords read and conſider at the adviſing of the Cauſe, the Right founded upon by the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> nor was the ſaid Interloquitor at all conſiſtant with theſe Rights, for it could not be denyed, that his Majeſty or the Town as having Right from him might have allowed no Apothecaries, but have granted all their Priviledges to the Chyrurgeons, and therefore <hi>a fortiori</hi> they might have reſtricted the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries at their erection to any particulars they pleaſed, and which is more, they ought to have reſtricted them, and they could not have taken from the Chyrurgeons the <hi>jus que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum</hi> by their Seal of Cauſe and other Rights. 2. That Point, <hi>viz.</hi> whether theſe Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Chyrurgeons ſhould hold only <hi>inter concives,</hi> was never debated and if it had, the ſaids Petitioners could by moſt unanſwerable Arguments evinced, that theſe Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhould extend to all the Priviledges of the City, as the Liberties of Baxters, Tailors, &amp; all the other Trades does, &amp; even the Juriſdiction of the Magiſtrats is extended to all within their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and not reſtricted <hi>ad concives,</hi> &amp; the ſaids Lords Juriſdiction is extended to all who are in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; not reſtricted to <hi>Scots</hi> men, or where were ever the Petitioners heard to debate why the Opinion of Phyſicians ſhould not be taken in that caſe, ſo that that Point ſhould be yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be debated, the ſaids Lords never refuſing to hear parties even after Interloquitor upon points that were not debated, and this was als great an Infringment upon their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties as that which was pleaded by the Apothecaries, and in which the ſaids Petitioners are als much concerned, Craving therefor that the ſaids Lords would be pleaſed to ſtop the extracting of the ſaid Interloquitor till the Petitioners be heard upon theſe weighty points in which they and all the Trades in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> yea and the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> it ſelf, and all the Burghs of <hi>Scotland</hi> are ſo much concerned, according to Juſtice as the ſaid Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo more fully bears; Which being likewiſe read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having heard, ſeen and conſidered the ſame, notwithſtanding of what was therein repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, Adhered to their ſaid former Interloquitor, and refuſed to ſtop the extracting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and thereafter the ſaid Action of Declarator purſued by the ſaid Apothecaries againſt the Chirurgeons being again called <hi>in preſentia,</hi> and both Parties compearing by their reſpective Procurators above named. the Procurators for the ſaid Apothecaries repeated their Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, as to the point that the Callings, <hi>viz.</hi> Pharmacy and Chirurgery ſhould be ſeparat they being two diſtinct Trades and Imployments of their own Natures, and that attending and following of either being ſufficient to take up any man, and the confounding of both theſe Trades being a late abuſe crept in ſince the year 1649 years, and was allowed by the Magiſtrats to conciliat favour with the Deacon of that Trade to favour them in the Election of the Magiſtracy, and therefore theſe two Trades and Imployments ought to be ſeparat and declared diſtinct, and the preſent Chirurgeons and their Succeſſors, who do joyntly exerciſe both imployments ſhould make their Election and be reſtricted to one of theſe in time come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſcharged to take an Apprentice with reſpect to both imployments, but only to be Booked as Apprentice in the Trade and imployment of Pharmacy or Chirurgery as their Maſters have elected and choſen the ſame. <hi>Secundo,</hi> There ought to be a Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt their Trades as well as all other Trades, and the Trade or Chirurgery being erected
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:179812:13"/> with a Seal of Cauſe and diſtinct as any Trade in the Kingdom, ought not to be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and that this ground of Declarator would be ſuſtained in other Trades as uncontraver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; And therefore it ought to be ſuſtained in this, it being a Confuſion inconſiſtent with the policy and intereſt of the Kingdom. <hi>Tertio,</hi> The Declarator is founded upon King <hi>James</hi> Decreet Arbitral which is the foundation of the Right, whereby all Trades are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to be Erected and diſtinguiſhed from others: To which it was anſwered, for the Chirurgeons by their ſaids Procurators, that the foreſaid Declarator could not be ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as to the point of Separation of theſe two Imployments of Apothecary and Chyrurgeons Firſt, Becauſe Chyrurgeons by ancient Seals of Cauſe are erected a Deaconrie as one of the Trades of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> with Liberty to receive Apprentice and to make them freemen. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo,</hi> As Burgeſſes and Gild-Brethren they were in a Capacity to exerciſe the Imployment of an Appothecary before the Erection of Apothecaries in a Fraternity, which was by an Act of the Town-Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1657. and any man in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> that was a Freeman before the ſaid Act, might have exerciſed Pharmacy without any Tryal, and may untill this Hour upon their byding a Tryal, and being found qualified, and Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is not a Trade or erected by a ſale of Cauſe as other Trades, but an Imployment, which by the Conſtitution any Freeman that is found qualified may exerciſe. <hi>Tertio,</hi> The preſent Chirurgeon Apothecaries are eminently fitted and capable for exerciſeing both Imployments, and whereof they and their Predeceſſors have been in Poſſeſſion of Exerciſeing of both paſt all Memory &amp; thereby has preſcribed a right of both. 4. That if the K. had power to erect this Trade with Priviledgs he has Delegated it to the Town, and if the Town have power, the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons have it by their Seal of Cauſe: and it is moſt conſiſtent with the Intereſt and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Nation, that the Leiges ſhould not be forced to employ both a Chyrurgeon &amp; Apothecary when one may do both. <hi>Quinto,</hi> It were Deſtructive of the Town of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burghs</hi> Power, by their Charters of Erection, to have Right to Erect Deaconries, and to Appoint the Regulat the ſeveral Trades within the Burgh, and to conjoyn and ſeparat them as they think fit. Likeas, the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries their Priviledges are Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by King and Parliament; and His Majeſty in his late Patent granted to the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, doth acknowledge Chyrurgeon-Aoothecaries, in whoſe Priviledges are Settled and Reſerved by the ſaid Patent, and Appoints them as joynt Viſators with the Phyſicians of the Drugs, to be ſold or made uſe of, Whereinto it was Replyed for the Apothecaries by their ſaids Procurators, That theſe Pretences ſounded upon by the Chyrurgeons, were moſt Frivolous, and the Apothecaries Declarator for the Separation of theſe two Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, was moſt Juſt and Rational: and though the Chyrurgeons did make a Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor and Noiſe, as if it were a Matter of State and Government, and did Alarm the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> as if their Charters of Erection and Priviledges were Impugned, &amp; Invaded; yet all ſuch Stuff and Pretences is nothing but the common Methods of amuſing of Clients, or the willful and ignorant Miſtakes of Lawyers, that muſt now reduce all privat Debates to Politicks of Government, which is fooliſh and impertinent Nonſenſe. For <hi>primo,</hi> The Declarator concerns none but the privat Right and Intereſt of the Apothecaries and Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons. <hi>Secundo,</hi> Albeit the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by their Charters of Erection from His Majeſty, and His Royal Predeceſſors, hath power to Erect Trades and Deaconries; ſo likeways all our Royal Burghs of the Kingdom have the ſame. <hi>Tertio,</hi> There hath been nothing more ordinar than Declarators before the Lords of Seſſion, of one Trade againſt another for their reſpective Liberties and Priviledges, which the Lords of Seſſion have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Determined according to Law and Juſtice, without the leaſt Invaſion of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Erection granted to Royal Burrows; nay, have many times ſuſtained Declarators, decerning the Magiſtrats to Erect and Incorporat Trades unto Deaconries, and to give them an Intereſt in the Government of the Burgh, notwithſtanding the Government had been otherwiſe exerciſed paſt all Memory, and which the Lords of the Seſſion and ſupream Judges of the Kingdom, may, and ought to do. <hi>Quarto,</hi> That as to the old Rights and Seal of Cauſe, the foreſaid Declarator did not at all Impinge, for there was nothing therein as to Pharmacy, and as to what the Chyrurgeons have obtained from the Town of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> of late, it was <hi>ultra vires,</hi> and the Town could not joyn other Trades inconſiſtent or inconvenient to be joyned, there being not two Trades or Employments within the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> that are more <hi>contra diſtinctione</hi> one from another, than Chyrurgery and Pharmacy: and therefore, according to the Practice, Example and Policy of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and of all other Royal Burghs, as all other Trades which are diſtinct in their nature, are ſeparat and not confounded, and cannot be exerciſed but by one; ſo there is the ſame and greater Reaſon for the Separation of Chyrurgery and Pharmacy. And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:179812:14"/> as to the King, his making mention of the Chirurgeon Apothecaries in the late Signature, imports nothing, it being a ſimple Deſignation, and there being an Deacon, does not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that there can be no diſtinct Trades, for there are ſeveral Deacons in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> that have many diſtinct Trades under that Deaconrie, as the Wrights have Plaiſterers, Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, Bowers, Club-makers, and many others, and the Chirurgeons cannot pretend that they exerciſe the Trade of Pharmacy upon any diſtinct Right or Priviledges granted to them by their Seal of Cauſe, or any Deed of the Town prior to the Erection of the Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Apothecaries, but only as Freemen in the Town, and have the ſame Right that all Burgeſſes have of being Apothecaries, if found qualified, and as to that which is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, there having been in Poſſeſſion of exerciſing both theſe Imployments paſt memory of Man, and that they have preſcribed a Right of both, and that any Burgeſs might have exerciſed the Art of Apothecary, and ſold Droggs before the Erection of the Apothecaries in a Fraternity in <hi>Anno</hi> 1657. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is moſt unwarrantable. For <hi>Primo,</hi> It is evident by the Report of the Phyſicians, it was but a late Abuſe, and no ſuch thing was known or practiſed but du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the late Troubles, and <hi>James Borthwick</hi> was the firſt man that ever attempted or practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame. 2. The Imployment and Art of an Apothecary is moſt groſly taken and confounded with that of a Drogiſt, which is but a common Merchant, which any Burgeſs or Gild brother may practiſe, by bringing home and ſelling Druggs as other Merchandice, whereas the Art of an Apothecary conſiſts in the Knowledge and Compoſition of Druggs. 3. Although the Chyrurgeons could pretned to any poſſeſſion of exercing both Imployments, that any ſuch Poſſeſſion being contrary to, and inconſiſtent with the publick Laws of the Kingdom, &amp; the publick good &amp; Pollicy of the Nation, &amp; the intereſt of his Majeſties Subjects, can never preſcribe any Right, but the Law looks upon each poſſeſſion to be nothing but <hi>coruptella &amp; vetuſtaserrores,</hi> and can never induce any preſcription, eſpecially ſeing there is not ſo much as the pretence of any Title or Right produced before the pretended Act in <hi>anno</hi> 1657, erecting the Apothecaries in a Fraternity, and even that Act does no ways au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize or allow the ſame perſon to exerciſe both theſe Imployments or confound the ſame but only declares that none ſhould exerciſe the Imployment nor Art of Apothecary, but ſuch as ſhould be thereafter found qualified and tryed by the perſons mentioned in the ſaid Act, and their ſucceſſors amongſt whom there were Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries at that time, but the ſaid Act does no ways allow, authorize or confound theſe two Imployments to be exerciſed by one and the ſame perſon, or hinder the Apothecaries to crave Redreſs againſt the ſame, which they now do by this juſt Declarator, and which as being a publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and <hi>actio popularis quivis depopulo competit,</hi> it being againſt the Publick Intereſt and Policy and Prudence of this and all other Nations, that diſtinct Trades and Imployments ſhould be confounded even though the Act of the Toun Council <hi>anno</hi> 1643. and 1655, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain the Apothecaries their Declarator as to the Point of Searcloaths, although they were expreſly excluded from Application of Searcloaths by the ſaids Acts, ſo the Lords of Seſſion ought to ſuſtain this Declarator as to the Separation of theſe Imployments, though there were an expreſs Act of the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to the contrair, as there is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrair to the publick good and Intereſt, and to the Acts and Conſtitutions of the Burgh as to the caſe of all other Trades, and the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by their Chartours of Erecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, having greater power in relation to other Mechanick Trades than they can or ought to pretend to Pharmacie or Chyrurgerie, which are meer liberal Arts and Imployments, and to be regulat and determined by the Lords of Seſſion as the ſupreme Judges, with the due reſpect of the publick good and Intereſt of the Subjects, and Pollicy and Prudence of other Nations; To which it was Duplyed for the Chyrurgeons by their ſaid Procurators, that the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in the year 1649, with conſent, and at the earneſt deſire of the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>othecaries, having determined the Chyrurgeons Right as to the Points controverted by any poſterior Act 1657, the Town could not by the erection of the Fraternity of Apothecaries, do any Deed in prejudice of the Chyrurgeons, tho the ſaid Erection did impinge upon their Right, as it does not, and this Declarator raiſed at the Apothecaries inſtance, being in effect a Reduction not only of the Chyrurgeons Right, but of the Towns Priviledges, the ſame cannot be ſuſtained by way of Declarator, but there muſt be Summonds of Reduction raiſed. 2. By the foreſaid Erection of the Fraternity, no Burgeſses of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> are exclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from being Pharmacians and Apothecaries, providing they can undergo a Tryal, and ſince any Burgeſs may be, why not the Chyrurgeons who are alwiſe willing to be tryed, and cannot be ſuppoſed but to be beſt qualified in reſpect of the Contingency of the Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. 3. By the ſaid Erection of the Fraternity, the Office of Apothecary is not ſettled as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:179812:14"/> any diſtinct Trade, but continues as a part of the Gildrie, and the Entrant enters as Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, by applying firſt to the Council without any Diſtinction, except as to the Trial, for they pay no Compoſition, whereas the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries their Apprentices, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they receive them, are ſeverely tryed in the Greek and Lattine Tongues, and muſt ſerve five years to the Trade and thereafter be three years in their Studie and Travelling before they can be tryed to be a Maſter. 4. In the foreſaid Erection, the Apothecaries hath acknowledged the Chirurgion Apothecaries their Right, &amp; have homologat &amp; conſented thereto by joyning with them in the <hi>Petition,</hi> whereupon the Act followed, and by which Act of Erection, it is expreſly provided that the Apothecary Chirurgeons, at leaſt ſome of their Number appointed, ſhall be Examinators to the entrant Apothecaries: As likeways, they Joyned together in obtaining an Ratification of Parliament in <hi>anno</hi> 1670, of the foreſaid Act; and ſo the Chirurgeon Apothecaries having both Priviledge and preſcription of their Poſſeſſion by vertue of the ſaid Decreet Arbitral, and Homologat by the ſaid Act of Erection, their Right and priviledge of vending and componing Drugs, cannot be taken from them without doing them unjuſtice, and the pretence of the Concluſion and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtencie of the Calling; is ridiculous, the Trade of Apothecaries being no particular Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and the Chirurgeon by his Art and Calling being oblidged to underſtand, and <hi>qua talis</hi> moſt be neceſſitat to have Skill, both of Drugs, Herbs, and other Chymical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts for the Cure of thoſe Diſeaſes that are the proper object of the Calling; and the Chirurgeon Apothecaries not being now <hi>in acquirendo jure,</hi> but in the Poſſeſſion of Rights and Priviledges Secured to them by Law, and Poſſect, paſt all Memory, the ſamen can by no means be taken from them: And as to the haill Points now contraverted are Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kd by Law; The King who has the ſole Power has divolved it upon the Town, who have already Regulat and determinat their Points, and the indeavouring to alter their Rights now determined by Authority were to unhing the Government upon apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or Reaſons, that, there might be a better Government, which would be a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to unhing all the Rights of King and People; and this beſide the convniency and Intereſt of the People, that they be not compelled to Imploy two when one may ſerve; and the ſuſtaining of this Declarator will be a preparative to all the Trades to quarrel the Conſtitutions of the Trade, and what the Town has done in this, is Ratified by King and Parliament, and that with the knowledge and concourſe of the Apothecaries, ſo that it is more as an ordinary Ratification: As likeways, the King by the Patent granted to the Phyſicians, has appointed the Chirurgeon Apothecaries to be joyned with the Phyſician in the trying of the Drug, which was not done in Stile or by chance, but was under Debate, and Quarreled before the Council; and the Reſervation in the ſaid Patent is only as to Phyſicians, and not as to Apothecaries, and by the Act of Council it is declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Chirurgeon Apothecaries, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Right ſhall be Ratified by the King, and to all the point of preſcription is opponed and joyned, which is ſtrongeſt in point of privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any thing in the World; and the Immemorial poſſeſſion is by conſent publickly open and owned in all the Judicatoris of the Nation. <hi>Quinto,</hi> It was Triplyed for the Apothecaries before the ſaid Procurators, that the Arguments founded upon the antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Chirurgeon is no Argument at all, for albeit of Old, the Chirurgeons were the only Doctors als well as Apothecaries; yet now ſeing we are Civiliſed, and are Subject to the Diſeaſes of other Nations, ſo the Supplicants policy has allowed of theſe Remedies, which in other Nations are exerciſed by ſeveral perſons, all which is cleared by the Report by the ſaids Lords their Order taken thereanent of the Cuſtoms of other Nations, and as by particular Acts of Parliament; it is provided that the different Trades ſhould be exerciſed by different perſons; So by the Cuſtom of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in all other Trades, it is obſerved, as cannot be denyed, and their Trades as being of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, ought rather to be diſtinguiſhed; and it is a Miſtake to ſay that they are by their Erection confounded, for the Apothecaries adhere to their Erection and Seal of Cauſe, for the Erection is for the Chirurgeon-Barbars: And as to what is alledged, that the King did give the Power to the Magiſtrats to diſpoſe and determine the Trades within the Town. It is Anſered, that the Power was not abſolute and unlimited, but <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum bonum &amp; aequum,</hi> the King has given the ſame Power to all the Royal Burghs in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and yet the Lords of Seſſion Decerned the Magiſtrats of <hi>Burntiſland,</hi> and gave the Burgeſſes thereof, Deacons and Gildrie, though the Magiſtrats thereof did Oppoſe it; and there is nothing in the Preſcription founded upon, for before the year 1649, this Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon Apothecary was never heard of, and their firſt Writ is in the 1657 year of GOD; and although their Arguments as to the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> their having already determined
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:179812:15"/> might als well have been applyed to the two points of Blood letting, and application of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloths, which notwithſtandig the Lords have already determined in, &amp; it were abſurd to prevent That the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by vertue of the power given to them, have power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Trades and Employments without control, or to do any thing inconſiſtent with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or the Intereſt of the people, and if they ſhould do it, the Judge Orinary may and ſhould redreſs it, but this debate is not contrary to any thing in the Erection, but moſt conſiſtent &amp; requiſite for the ſimple <hi>Chyrurgeons,</hi> in whoſe favours the Erection is, for now neither the ſimple <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> nor ſimple <hi>Apothecaries</hi> can get a Prentice, ſeing the Prentice for the ſame C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d Pains can acquire both Trades; And the concluſion of this Declartor is not only that the <hi>Chirurgeon Apothecaries</hi> now, are not only to Elect of one of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, but likeways it was craved, that thereafter they might be diſcharged to take Prentices with relation to both Trades, or to pretend to Freedom in both, and it is no weight that the Expences of the Leidges is greater by imploying of two perſons, for it is very well kown that the <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> takes both for his Drugs and Pains exorbitantly, and all the exorbitant priviledges were given the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> by the Magiſtrats, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Intereſt in the Election of the Magiſtrat, and what is now craved by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries,</hi> is not only conſiſtant with the Laws and Cuſtoms of other Nations, but agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Policy of this Burgh in all other Trades, and is much more obſerved in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and well governed Cities, and all the Poſſeſſion that the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> can pretend to before the year 1657, can operat nothing, ſeing it wants a Title which is neceſſary for Preſcription: Thereafter there was an Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords, by the ſaid <hi>Apothecaries</hi> and ſimple <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh;</hi> Shewing, that where to that Action and Declarator firſt intented at the inſtance of the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> againſt the <hi>Chirurgeon Apothecaries,</hi> and now concurred in by the ſimple <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> as to that point or ſepara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the two Callings and Employments not to be exerced by, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in one perſon, and which ſingle point hath been formerly fully Debated. It was therefore humbly craved, the ſaids Lords would adviſe the point, and give their Anſwer therein in <hi>jure,</hi> eſpecially ſeing the ſaids Apothecaries, Raiſers and Purſuers of their own Declarator, did humbly conceive they were not <hi>pro loco et tempore</hi> concerned to inſiſt any farder in the other undetermined points of their Declarator, while the ſaids Lords ſhould be pleaſed to give their determination in the point of Separation, as the ſaid Supplication more fully bears, which being read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having heard ſeen and conſidered the ſamen, Declared that before adviſing of the point as to the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Employments, they would hear the Parties upon the points reſerved to be determined in their ſaid laſt interloquitor; and therefore ordained both parties Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to be read at the next calling, and accordingly the ſaid Action being again called, and both parties compearing by their reſpective Procurators above named, the Procurators for the ſaids <hi>Apothecaries</hi> repeated the concluſion of their ſaid Declarator, as to the other two points not yet inſiſted in, <hi>viz. Primo,</hi> That it ſhould not be lawful for <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> to trouble <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and put them to their Oaths upon alledged Contraventions, and their exerceing of any operations proper to <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> but only according to the practice and obſervance of all other Trades, to deprehend them in the Act of Contravention, and which the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> craves no more againſt the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> in caſe of their Contraventions, and exerceing the Employment of <hi>Apothecaries. Secundo,</hi> That in ſo far as concerns the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Colledge of Juſtice, and others his Majeſties Subjects reſiding in, or repairing to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> not being Burgeſſes, they may without any reſtriction, make uſe either of <hi>Apothecaries</hi> or <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> and that the Acts of the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> relating to Priviledges of either of the ſaid Employments, can take no further place but <hi>inter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cives.</hi> To which it was Anſwered for the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> by their ſaid Procurators, that the foreſaid Declarator, as to theſe two points now inſiſted on cannot be ſuſtained, becauſe as to the firſt, that the proveing the Contraventions by the contraveeners their Oaths, as a thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in caſes more ordinary, and leſs importance, as in the cutting green Woods abſtracting of Multers, and lately by an Act of Sederuut, it is appointed that the Magiſtrats ſhall be Burgeſſes before them, and referr the Contraventions of the ſelling of Vivers at greater Rates than they allowed to the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veeners Oaths. And here there is nothing to ſay as in other manual Trades. And as to the ſecond point, it were againſt Reaſon to leave the ſtrangers to the mercy of unskilful per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, while the Burgeſſes are priviledged for that they ſhal be ſerved by skilful perſons. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo,</hi> All the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> has the Right, and are in the poſſeſſion of provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179812:15"/> for ſtrangers while they are in the Town, in all other things, and why not in this. <hi>Tertio.</hi> The Phyſicians their Parent does bear them to all perſons within the Town als well ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as others. And the Chyrurgeons Trade ſhould be in reaſon as far extended, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſeing their Rights and immemorial Poſſeſſions does carry them to it. And by the late Act of Parliament Merchants are allowed to be put to their Oaths for in-bringing of Good Uncuſtomed or prohibite, which is in effect a Theft. Whereunto it was Replyed for the Apothecaries, That this manner of Probation cannot be allowed; for it would ruine both the ſimple Apothecaries and the ſimple Chyrurgeons. And therefore until that point of the Separation of the Trades ſhould be firſt determined, and then the Deciſions as to the manner of probation would be equal to both. <hi>Secundo,</hi> The general intereſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is, That it ſhal not be in the power of any Trade to diſcover or bring in queſtion His Majeſties Leidges, as being ſubject to Diſeaſes; which it may be they would think ſhame of, yea ſo much as to have it ſuſpected, tho by the event it ſhould not be proven. <hi>Tertio</hi> It is contrair to the inviolable Obſervance in the caſe of all other Trades who cannot prove any pretended Contraventions, either againſt unfree Men or Members of other Trades, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>per manus ſubjectionem;</hi> and that they were actually deprehended in the Act of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travention. <hi>Quarto,</hi> If the contrair were ſuſtained, that it might be lawful for the Trades to raiſe Proceſs againſt Unfree-men, or one againſt another upon pretended Contraventions of their reſpective Priviledges. It behoved to kinde a Fyre amongſt the Trades, and each of them to ruine and deſtroy others by calumnious Proceſſes. <hi>Quinto,</hi> It behoved to open a Door to all Calumnie, Prevarication and Perjury. <hi>Sexto,</hi> There is a great Difference betwixt the caſe of general Laws or Poenal Statutes, the Contraventions whereof may be proven by Oath of Partie. And the priviledges granted to privat Trades and Incorporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: For the obſervance whereof, there is no furder allowed by the practiſe of this and all other Nations, but actual Seizure and Deprehenſion, and even by the Ratification of Parliament <hi>in anno</hi> 1641 in Favours of the Chyrurgeons. It is evident that the Parliament allowed no more but actual Seizure and Deprehenſion. <hi>Septimo,</hi> If theſe were allowed, it ſhould be in the power of Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries to ruine the ſimple Apothecaries and ſimple Chyrurgeons, by raiſing Proceſs againſt them at their pleaſure, and by calling them to attend ſuch Proceſſes, when they might be forced to go out of Town to attend their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, and ſo might Be holden as confeſt; and ſo there is far greater reaſon why Oaths ſhould not be allowed againſt Apothecaries; then in the caſe of other Trades where it is not allowed. <hi>Octavo.</hi> A thouſand caſes might occur wherein Apothecaries could not be cleared to Depone, whether the Operations done by them were Chyrurgical, or might be proper to be done by Apothecaries. All which may fully evince, that it is a moſt unjuſt and unwarrantable pretence that Apothecaries ſhould be put to give their Oaths, which is contrair to the practiſe and obſervance of all other Trades, and would be deſtructive to the Apothecaries, and is contrary and prejudicial to the intereſt and Reputation of His Majeſt es Subjects: And as to the point of Poſſeſſion and Preſcription, the firſt time that this manner of probation is mentioned was <hi>in anno</hi> 1655; which is here ſaid to be proved <hi>de jure,</hi> which imports nothing but legal probation; As the caſe requires, <hi>Secundo.</hi> They had the ſame pretenſion to the Cere-clothes, which notwithſtanding thereof is regulat by the Lords according to reaſon and Law, and no Act of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> can be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways binding, but according as they conſiſt with Juſtice and Law. And albeit they had that Act <hi>in anno</hi> 1655. Yet it was never pretended to be put in execution but twice, which appears to be meer colluſion by Reading of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aids Decreets. And as to the Extenſion, as to ſtrangers the Declarator is moſt juſt and rational. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe as to the Colledge of Juſtice and its Members, it is their undoubted and uncontraverted Priviledge that they may imploy and make uſe of any Unfree Man, and much more may imploy Apothecaries in that which is proper to Chyrurgeons, And that therefore Apothecaries or Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree-Men, ſerving any of the Colledge of Juſtice, cannot be lyable for any Puniſhment for the ſame, that being an infallible Conſequence founded upon the Priviledge of the Members of the Colledge of Juſtice. 2. The ſame alſo ought to be extended and communicat to all Strangers who are not Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, becauſe they cannot be ſubject as to the matter of their Health, to be limited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by any Diſtruction of Trades eſtabliſhed within the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> except it were <hi>ratione delicti,</hi> or <hi>ratione rejectae,</hi> or the like, which is ſubject to the Juriſdiction of the Magiſtrats, and it is not denyed but if any Stranger would build or repair a Houſe which lyes locally <hi>intra territorium &amp; diſtrictum</hi> of the Town, a Stranger behoved to make uſe of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:179812:16"/> Workmen, according to the Diſtinction of the ſeveral Trades, becauſe the Houſe is <hi>res ſitae</hi> within the Precincts of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and is the ſubject of the Operation, but what imaginable Colour of Law or Reaſon can be pretended that as to the point of a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers Health, he ſhould be ſubject to the Regulation and Diſtinction of Trades within the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> why they may not intruſt the ſame to whom they think fit, and to make uſe of the ordinary Apothecaries without the leaſt reſtraint or hazard either to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or their Apothecaries, and that the diſtinction of Apothecaries and Chyrurgeons of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhound only take place <hi>inter concives,</hi> theſe being the publick Conſtitutions of the Burgh, wherein either his Majeſties Subjects are no ways concerned, To which it was Duplyed for the Chirurgeons, that the King having given the Town Right and power to regulat the Trades, &amp; all Inhabitants within the Town, has conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly given them all things requiſite for it, and the not allowing the probation by Oath but by Seaſure, were to involve the People, the patent Trades and all in unevitable Ryots and Pleas, and as it is impoſſible to prove the Contraventions but by Oath, ſo that he not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his Probation, were to take away the Priviledge it ſelf. 2. If it be any mans right he may vindicat his Right by all legal Means, and that is a legal Probation cannot be denyed, and although this has been the Rule and way of Probtion ever until now, it cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that ever any perſon was purſued but where they were guilty, and if they ſhould have Expenſes, which is the <hi>pana temere litigantium.</hi> 3. The King having given the Power of the Magiſtracy and Government not only of Burgeſſes, but of all Strangers coming to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſo long as they are there they muſt be ſubject to the Rules and Government of the Town, and as Strangers cannot make uſe of other Artificers that are not Freemen, why ought they to make uſe of Chirurgeons, and the Chirurgeon Apothecaries being upwards of two hundred years in poſſeſſion, by vertue of good and undoubted Rights the ſamen cannot be ſummarly taken away, whereunto the Apothecaries Triplyed, That all the Towns Rules in regulating of the Trades within the Town, does extend only to the <hi>Concives,</hi> for if otherwiſe, the Priviledge granted to the Colledge of Juſtice would be rendered <hi>Eluſory</hi> and of non effect, and <hi>conceſſo aliquo concenduntur omnia ſine quibus affectum ſortire non poterit.</hi> 2. Albeit the Members of the Colledge of Juſtice, and other Strangers not being Burgeſſes, are ſubject and lyable to the Juriſdiction of the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> upon any ground of Law that founds the Competency of their Juriſdiction, and if they ſhould commit Riots, Slaughters or other Crimes, or were heretors of the Tenements or the like, yet the power and Juriſdiction of the Magiſtrats of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> cannot reſpect any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint or Revolution of the cure of their health, the Acts of the Town Council being only politick Conſtructions of the Burgh which can be valid and binding againſt none but <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concives,</hi> and it is vain and frivolous to pretend, that they have a Power to make uſe of and call Apothecaries, and yet if they come they are lyable to be puniſhed, it being abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely inconſiſtent with the other, and would render upon the matter the ſame Limitation and diſtinction of Trades, as effectual againſt the Members of the Colledge of Juſtice and Strangers, as againſt other Burgeſſes and Citizens: And therefore the Apothecaries repeat and open that Declarator, which as to the whole Concluſions thereof, is moſt juſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the Laws and Cuſtoms of other Nations, and to the conſtant obſervance and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in the caſe of all other Trades, and wherein not only the Apothecaries concur, but alſo ſix of the Chirurgeons, who have right to all the Liberties and Priviledges of the Seal of Cauſe erecting the Chyrurgeons into an Deaconrie and Incorporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Which Summonds of Declarator purſued by the ſaids Apothecaries againſt the ſaids Chirurgeon Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and haill Points therein contained, with the ſeveral Diſputes above-written following thereupon, being at length heard, ſeen and conſidered by the ſaids Lords, and they therewith being well and ripely adviſed, the ſaids Lords of Council and Seſſion, <hi>Found and Declared,</hi> that the Imployments of Chirurgery and Pharmacy being two diſtinct Imployments, and both requiring a great deal of care and knowledge, ſhall hereafter (within the City of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Liberties thereof) be exerciſed by diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and that one and the ſame perſon ſhall not exerciſe, or be imployed in both Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that albeit Chirurgeons may buy and ſell Simples as any Druggiſt or Merchant may do, and compone ſuch Druggs as are neceſſar for Chyrurgecal and and external Application, yet that they cannot compone any Medicament to be taken inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n lly by the Mouth <hi>Reſervand</hi> alwiſe from this Declarator to the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries that are preſently actual Maſters in both Imployments, and does actually keep Apothecaries Shops within the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> or Liberties thereof, as to which Bounds this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator extends and no furder. Thereafter there was an Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords at the inſtance of the ſaid Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, with the concurſe of all the other
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:179812:16"/> fourteen Deacons, <hi>ſhewing,</hi> That where King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth of Bleſſed Memory, having debarred all Tradeſmen from the Magiſtracy in which the Petitioners had then an equal ſhare He did in recompenſe thereof allow the Petitioners the Benefit of Gildry, by vertue where of it was free for the ſaids Petitioners or any of them who were comprehended in any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way under the fourteen Deaconries, to be free not only to keep Shops as Gild-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, but likeways to exerce any of theſe Trades, which were pendicles of the Gildrie; And it cannot be denyed but that the Apothecary Trade was not comprehended under any of the fourteen Deaconries, but was ſimply a pendicle of the Gildrie, and conſequently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the fourteen Deaconries were free to be of it, to which the Petitioners deſired a Speſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and formal Anſwer, it never having been anſwered yet in theſe Proceſſes, and all that the Petitioners heard inſinuated as an anſwer, being that the Apothecaries Trade is not a meer ſelling but a Compounding of Druggs, which Compoſition is no part of the Gildrie: To which the Petitioners reply, is that this is a miſtake in the Fundamental Conſtitut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n of this Burgh, whereby even the compounding of Drugs is no part of the fourteen Deac nries, and conſequently as before the year 1657, any man whatſomever might have been without tryal ſet up to compound Druggs if he was Burges, ſo after the year 1657 all the priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges given to the Apothecaries was only that none ſhould exerce their Trade till they were found able by the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries and Apothecaries, and therefore if that the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon Apothecaries can ſhow that they were ſufficiently able to underſtand their Trade why may not they be admitted als well as any other Burgeſſes, ſince no Burges can be debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that being his Birthright by the ſet, and to preſs that they may be free of all the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicants Trade, as they are of theirs, was expreſly contrair to the foundamental Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Burgh, who by no means can be free in any of the fourteen Deaconries, but theſe who have either ſerved in an Apprentiſhip to any of them, or have married one of their Daughters when they have gotten a ſufficient Anſwer to that point never as yet anſwered then it will be time to Debate whether the Apprentice which the Petitioners have received, and may receive during our Lifetimes ought to be free of both Trades, their being <hi>jus quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum</hi> to the Petitioners &amp; them thereto prior to this Deciſion, and all ſtatutes ſuch as this of the ſaids Lords ſeems to be having only <hi>tractum futuri temporis</hi> though made by a Parliament, eſpecially when they are correctory of Priviledges <hi>bona fide</hi> acquired prior thereto, and the Petitioners being admitted to both Fraternities in both which the Petitioners have given their Oaths <hi>de fideli,</hi> and by their Conſtitution there can be no meeting except where the two Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors are preſent, and one of the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries muſt be Viſitor; So that either they muſt have a new Erection, which the Petitioners humbly conceive, none can give them, but the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> or elſe the Petitioners muſt of neceſſity be preſent with them, and the Petitioners humbly craved, that the Apothecaries Advocats would ſhow us which way and by what Arguments any Society could meet in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> without an Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the King or the Town, or how men that have a Priviledge and are in Poſſeſſion of it can be deprived and forfeited without a Fault; As alſo how the Petitioners Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices who have payed in their Prentice-fees in Contemplation of both Trades before the ſaids Lords their Act can Forfeit their Fault, upon which and ſeveral other Points never yet debated before the Lords; The Petitioners deſires to be heard in the ſaids Lords their own Preſence which was never refuſed to any Subject whoſe Cauſe was once heard <hi>in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia,</hi> as the ſaid Supplication and deſire thereof more fully bears; To which it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered for the Apothecaries and Chyrurgeon Barbers, <hi>viz.</hi> That neither the tumultary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls of the Trades, nor the tumultuary Petitions which are given in name of the hail Trades, tho' thirteen of them are not in the leaſt concerned, ought to have no other influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Losds, but to deſerve a Cenſure and Reprimand, that after they have taken ſo much p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins and trouble, and has determined the point upon unanſwerable Grounds of Law and Reaſon with all poſſible Tenderneſs and Allowance to the preſent Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, They ſhould in an indiſcreet Way and Manner Caball and run up and down and amuſe ignorant people with Stories of Government and Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which is not in the leaſt concerned. The caſe being a ſingle, Debaſe of privat Rights, and a Controverſy betwixt the Apothecaries and Chyrurgeons, which is no other but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly the ſame, with the Debates and Controverſies which have and may ariſe betwixt other Trades. And as to the Prentices in the Petition, That the Apothecaries are none of the Pendicles of the fourteen Deaconries; and that any Gild-Brother might have exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Employment of an Apothecary, before the Erection in a Fraternity, and may do the ſame, ſince their undergoing the Tryal, and being Qualified. <hi>It was anſwered,</hi> the Interlocutor is opponed, and Grounds whereupon it proceeded: and the Petitioners do
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179812:17"/> ſtrangely forget themſelves, if they diſremember that the ſaid Pretence was both Founded upon in the Declarator, and fully anſwered and ſatisfied. And again to refreſh their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the Anſwer then made was, that albeit the Decreet Arbitral pronounced by His Majeſties Grandfather King <hi>James</hi> the Sixth, had ſettled the fourteen Deaconries in order to the Government of the Burgh, and that the Apothecaries were none of theſe Deacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; yet without the leaſt impinging upon the Decreet Arbitral, it was lawful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent to the Apothecaries to crave by their Declarator, that Pharmacy and Chyrurgery might be declared diſtinct Employments, and ſeparately exerciſed as ſuch, juſt as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Pendicles of one and the ſame Deaconry, might purſue a Declarator of this nature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other. As for Inſtance, if the Bakers of Pyes ſhould tranſgreſs and bake Loaves, which is a diſtinct Employment though belonging to the ſame Deaconry, or if a Lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith ſhould purſue a Black-ſmith if he ſhould uſe both Trades, though under the ſame Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conry of Hammermen, and fourty others which might be inſtanced, by which the ſaids Lords may plainly perceive, that the Decreet Arbitral, or the Settlement of the fourteen Deaconries is not in the leaſt concerned; and beſides, it is certain and undenyable, that the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries are none of the fourteen Deaconries, or ſo much as mentioned in the Sett, but only the ſimple Chyrurgeons, the moſt part of whom do concur with the ſimple Apothecaries in the foreſaid Declarator. And as to that Pretence, that the Caſe was a Matter of Government, and that His Majeſty has granted a Signature in Favours of the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, and that the King's Advocat deſires to be Heard in favours of the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries. It was anſwered, the Inſinuations are moſt frivolous; And it is ſtrange how any man can pleaſe himſelf, or think it poſſible to delude others with ſuch Conceits, and that every little petty Debate betwixt two privat Trades, muſt inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be a great Queſtion of Government. And it were certainly very unſuitable to that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and Duty the Lords of Seſſion owes to His Sacred Majeſty, whoſe Royal Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is taken up with Matters of a Higher Nature, to trouble His Majeſty with ſuch pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Concerns, which are only proper to be Cognoſced and Determined by His Majeſties Judicatures, which are Eſtabliſhed for that very end. And as to the Signature in favours of the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries; it was ſtrange how it comes to be mentioned, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received its Fate before the Lords of Privy Council: and it's great Moderation in the Lords of Seſſion, who were ſo immediatly touched by the Extravagancies of the ſaid Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature, not to have taken notice of it before this time. And as to theſe Pretences, that the Interlocutor can be of no greater Force than a Law, which can only be extended <hi>ad ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus futuros,</hi> and cannot prejudge Apprentices who had <hi>jus quaeſitum</hi> by their Indentures to both Employments. It was Anſwered, the Compariſon is an evident Miſtake; for the Lords Interlocutor is a Sentence <hi>in Jure,</hi> and a Deciſion in Point of Right, that theſe two Employments ought to be ſeparate, and not confounded in the ſame perſon; ſo that it was impoſſible there would be <hi>Jus</hi> for the Confuſion, that being directly inconſiſtent with the Interlocutor, it being certain that the Lords of Seſſion cannot take away Parties Rights, neither <hi>pro praeterito,</hi> nor <hi>futuro:</hi> and therefore the Interlocutor by a neceſſity of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, ſhould have effect againſt the preſent Maſters for the Separation in time coming, though the Lords has been pleaſed ſo far to indulge them as to allow them to Operat in both during their Lifetimes: but there is not the ſame Reaſon to extend the ſame Favour to Apprentices which would indeed evacuat the Interlocutor, and the Lords may as well Retrait what they have done, as ſatisfie the unreaſonable Clamour of the Chyrurgeon-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries, and neither they nor their Apprentices, can pretend to a <hi>Jus quaeſitum,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they ſuppoſe the Interlocutor <hi>in Jure</hi> is unjuſt, which, whatever they think, it were a little too petulant to inſinuat or expreſs. And Laws are of a different nature from In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlocutors <hi>in Jure;</hi> becauſe Laws being <hi>inductivi Juris novi,</hi> are only to be extended <hi>ad negotia futura;</hi> but Interlocutors are Declaratory of Laws already made, and of diſtinct Rights formerly of their own nature eſtabliſhed, and ſo does take effect, and regulat all Caſes which are the Subject of Debates. And the Apothecaries humbly deſire the Lords to take to their Conſideration a former Petition given in by them, and at laſt to put a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to theſe Debates, and to ſecure and render their Interlocutor ineffectual in time co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and that it may not be in the power of the Chyrurgeon Apothecaries, to elude the ſame. And thereafter there was another Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords, by the ſaids Apothecaries &amp; Chyrurgeon-Barbars of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Shewing, that where the ſaids Lords upon Adviſing of the Declarator Raiſed by the Petitioners againſt the Chyrurgeon-Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, has moſt juſtly Found and Declared, that theſe ſhould be ſeparat Employments in time coming. It followed neceſſary, that the preſent Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries who were
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:179812:17"/> allowed to exerciſe both Employments dung their Lifetime ſhould not upon the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the ſaid perſonal Indulgence, be allowed to fall upon Methodso evacuat the ſaid Interlocutor, and perpetuat the Confuſion of theſe Employments. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> therefore the ſaids Lords would expreſly declare, <hi>That it ſhould not be lawful to the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries to receive Apprentices, but as to one of theſe Employments, and that the Prentices be ſo look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; And that the preſent Chyrurgeon Apothecaries may be put to Declare, which of theſe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments they will take themſelves to in time coming, as to that Point of Booking of Prenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; otherways they will receive Prentices one year in Pharmacy, and another year in Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, which is most abſurd.</hi> As likewiſe, <hi>That the preſent Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries may be Reſtricted to ſit at one of the Tables, either of the Deaconrie of Chyrurgeons, or of the Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Apothecaries, there being no more intended by the Interlocutor, than that the preſent Masters may Operat in both Employments during their Lifetime.</hi> And whereas the Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were Informed, that the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries of deſign to evacuat the Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, were to crave, that their Apprentices who are already paſt their Prentiſhip, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of their Indentures, may be allowed to exerciſe both Employments during their Lifetime. The ſaid Pretence is directly inconſiſtent with the Interlocutor, and tends to evacuat the ſame, and continue the Confuſion of theſe Employments, and the Indulgence granted to the preſent Maſters is <hi>ex gratia,</hi> and contrare to the common Grounds of Law, whereupon the ſaids Lords has ſuſtained the Declarator for Separation in time coming. And the ſpecial Conſiderations that the ſaids Lords have gone upon, as to the preſent Maſters, was, that they were in poſſeſſion of both Employments, and had long Experience, and had Shops fitted with the Materials of Pharmacy, and Chyrurgery, which ſpecial Reaſons do not in the leaſt Militat for Apprentices who are not ſet up, many of whom will not be able to be Freemen in the ſaids Employments theſe ten or twelve years, by the Conſtitutions of the Burgh, and the Acts of the reſpective Employments. Thereafter it was humbly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That the ſaids Lords would ſo Enlarge and Declare in the foreſaid Interlocutor, That it may not be in the power of the preſent Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, by their Methods of taking and Breeding of the Prentices in both Employments, to evacuat the ſame; and that they may be Reſtricted to Meet and Conveen only at that Table, at which they ſhall Condeſcend to Book their Prentices; that ſo theſe Points of the Separation being once ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleared, the Lords may at their convenience, proceed to Adviſe the other Points that are not yet Determined, as the ſaid laſt Supplication alſo more fully contains. Which firſt Supplication above written, with the Anſwer made theret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the ſaid Apothecaries, and laſt Bill given in by them in manner above ſpecified, being all read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having Heard, Seen and Conſidered the ſamen: and being therewith well and ripely Adviſed, the ſaids Lords <hi>Decerned</hi> the ſaids Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries Maſters, who by the foreſaid Interlocutor were allowed the exerciſe of both Employments during their Lifetime and the three young Men. <hi>viz. James Mu rhead, John Lauder,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Edgar,</hi> who by the particular Interlocutors, were declared to be in that Condition, albeit they be not as yet actually entered Maſters in both Employments. To make their Election to Meet and ſit at any one of the Tables of the ſaid two Employments, and to declare their Election betwixt and <hi>Tueſday</hi> thereafter: and if they did not Declare betwixt and the ſaid day, the ſaids Lords Decerned them to ſit only at the Chyrurgeons Table, as the eldeſt and firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected Trade: and the ſaids Lords have found, that no Maſter can hereafter take Prentices to make them Freemen in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in any of the ſaids two Employments, except that at which they ſit at the Table, and that all the Prentices already entered, are to be free only in that Imployment and Trade at which their Maſters ſits at the Table. In Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the which Interloquitor, there was an Condeſcendance given in by <hi>John Joſſie</hi> Chyrurgeon-Apothecary, written and ſubſcribed by him, and declaring his Election to be to meet and ſit with the Apothecaries, as the ſaid Declaration and Condeſcendance, dated the day of <hi>March</hi> inſtant, extant in Proces more fully bears: And thereafter there was another Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords, by the Chyrurgeon-Barbers of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> ſhewing, That where in the Erection of their Deaconry, and in the Confirmation thereof by King <hi>James</hi> the fourth, as alſo by the Decreet-Arbitral of King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth, there is not ſo much as any word of concerning or ſignifying ſuch a thing as a Chyrurgeon-Apothecary, which never came to be in practice till the time of the late unhappy Troubles &amp; Confuſions, &amp; was never ſo much as named under that Deſignation in any publict Writ, till the time of the later and more unhappy Uſurpation <hi>anno</hi> 1657, which yet does not any ways Erect or Authorize them as ſuch, and that the foreſaid ancient Deaconry flouriſhed in a good condition, with an oppulent Box, ti l the Chyrurgeon-Apothecary crept in amongſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:179812:18"/> us, who deriving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nſick ends and deſigns, prejudicial to the ancient Deaconry, regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apothecry and his Pharmacy more then the Chyrurgeon, and true eſtabliſhment of the Deaconry: Purſuand to which, they at all Tryals, and all Admiſſions of Intrants, conſtntly more favour their own Apprentices then the Petitioners, wherethrow they have not only become more numerous in the Calling then the Supplicants were, and ſo by Votes overpowered the Petitioners in all their Propoſals; but that alſo, ſince their coming in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Petitioners, much Money hath been expended for Pleas and Suits of Law, to not only the exhauſting of the Box, but burdening of the Calling with conſiderable Debts. And now that the ſaids Lords have moſt juſtly found and declared, that theſe two Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Pharmacy and Chyrurgery are in their natures diſtinct, and ought in their Practice to be ſo far ſeparat, as not to be exerciſed by one ſingle perſon; and tho' the ſaids Lords, have <hi>ex gratia,</hi> upon ſeveral Specialities, indulged the preſent Maſters to operat in both du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Lifetime, yet the Petitioners are informed, that the ſaids Lords are importunate to inlarge the ſame favour to ſome Apprentices, as particularly to <hi>John Lawder</hi> and <hi>James Muirhead,</hi> againſt whoſe Bills the Petitioners (adhereing always to their general Anſwers and Bill jointly of before given in by them with the ſimple Apothecaries,) do humbly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, that theſe Prentices are not ſtated under the Specialities which prevailed with the ſaids Lords to grant the perſonal Indulgence in favours of the preſent Maſters; and as the Conceſſions would altogether evacuat the ſaids Lords their juſt Interloquitor, and perpetuat the Confuſion for ever, ſo would they alſo open a door of great trouble to the ſaids Lords, for no Apprentice (whether he hath not ſerved his time, or is yet ſerving,) but would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuat ſome pretences for enjoying a ſhare in that perſonal Indulgence; and it is a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in the fundamental Conſtitution of this Burgh, to imagine that any one man ought in <hi>Jure</hi> take an Apprentice for two diſtinct Trades and Imployments, for can a Merchant take an Apprentice for the Gildry and a Trade, of ought a Tradeſman in <hi>jure</hi> take an Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice by formal Indentures, and book him equally to his own particular Trade and the Gildry of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e City; yea, can a Tradeſman take a Prentice, and formally book him to any two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Imployments, or Pendicles of one and the ſame Deaconry; as for inſtance, can a Py-Baxter take, and formally book an Apprentice to the baking of Pyes and the baking of Loaves, although the baking of a Loaf is the ordinary Eſſay put to the Py-Baxter at his Tryals. So that as the Maſters impinged upon the Conſtitutions and Order of the Burgh, in confounding of the Gildry with the Crafts, by taking and booking one Prentice to both, ſo the Apprentices cannot found any thing upon this <hi>Corruptela,</hi> to prejudge the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Burgh, whatever recourſe they may have againſt their Maſters for impoſing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them and their Friends by ſuch Indentures. <hi>Secundo,</hi> It is more particularly Anſwered to <hi>John Lawder</hi>'s Bill, that the Action of Declarator was depending long before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> confeſſes himſelfe to have come home, and as <hi>de facto,</hi> he never offered him to his try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als at the Petitioners Table, ſo it is but frivolous to alleadge he had done it, but was delayed upon the depending Declarator, for what ever differences were betwixt the ſimple Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecars, and the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries for the tryal of intrants, at their table during the dependance, yet no ſuch thing was upon that account, betwixt the Petitioners and Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries at the Petitioners Table, and as for <hi>James Mureheads</hi> Petition, he is already an Apothecary, and ſo the Lords Interloquitor is opened. 2. <hi>Eſto,</hi> he were not yet, he cannot by the Acts of the Deacons, be ſo much as yet for a long time receav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his very Tryals, the Petitioners Acts providing that none but qualified Perſon ſhould be admitted, diſcharged the receiving of ſo much as a Bill, from an intrant till eight year <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he is Booked ane Apprentiſe in the Books of their Calling, and which <hi>James Murhead</hi> cannot aleadge. It was therefore humbly beſought, that the ſaids Lords would take the Promiſes to their conſideration, with the Petitioners Anſwers and former Bill abovementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, and ſecure the Lords Interloquitor from being rendered unefectual, and that the Lords would declare that the Box and Calling of the Chyrurgeons, could not be burdened with the Debt lately contracted, for the maintaining of this Plea againſt the Separation, but that the ſame ſhould be payed by the Chyrurgeons-Apothecaries amongſt themſelves, and not upon the Box, which is the Poors Money and the Stock of the Incorporation, ſeing the Petitioners concurred for the Separation, and one of the Petitioners was ſo Illegally In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carcerat by the preſent Deacons (who is a Chyrurgeon Apothecary himſelf) for deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Opinion againſt borrowing of Money for this Plea, that the ſaids Lords did liberate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> without either Caution or conſignation, as the ſaid Petition likeways more fully bears, which being likeways Read in preſence of the ſaid Lords, they ordained the Chyrurgeon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries to have anſwered the ſamen again the next day thereafter, and thereafter there
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179812:18"/> was ane Supplication given in to the ſaid Lords, by <hi>James Turnbul</hi> Chyrurgeon in <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhewing that whereas he had payed an conſiderable Prentiſe Fee, after his Apprentisſhip, went Abroad for ſeveral years. to accompliſh himſelf in the Arts of Chyrurgerie and Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, and after his return upon Application to the Chyrurgeons of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> they upon Tryal have found the Petitioner qualified, and admitted him a Free-man Maſter in their Societie, and he having provided himſelf of all Drugs, Medicamenta and Inſtruments ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſar, not only fit for Exercing of Chyrurgery, but alſo of Pharmacie, the Petitioner hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet up and keeped an open Shop, and done all Diligence for procureing of Freedom in Pharmacy, and did make his Application to the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for their Recomendation to the Fraternity of Chyrurgeon Apothecars, and Apothecaries, the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner was always delayed, becauſe of ſeveral Intrants that had procured their Recomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation before him, but now having procured his Recomendation from the Council to the Brother-hood, the Petioner has gotten in his Bill, which Bill with his Recomendation is accepted of by them, and ſtill lying before them, but by reaſon their metings has not been ſo frequent as formerly, becauſe of their pleas at Law, the Petitioners Tryals hes been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed, and ſeing he is a preſent Maſter in Chyrurgrie, and hes done all Diligence in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Tryal of his qualification in Pharmacie and to that end hes Set up a Shop (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords Interloquitor) Humbly beſeeching therefore, that the ſaids Lords would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſaid Brother-hood of Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, and Apothecaries to admit and receave the Petitioner a Freeman Chyrurgeon-Apothecary, that he may have the benefit of the Lords Interloquitor, eſpecially conſidering the Lords have granted the like Priviledge to other two of late (the one not being yet admitted Chyrurgeon, the other neither as yet admitted Chyrurgeon nor Apothecarie, ſo the Petitioners caſe in all circumſtances being conſidered, is more favourable then theſe. Whereunto it was anſwered for the ſaid Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, it was abſolutly falſe that he payed any Prentiſe Fee, having only ſerved his Father, who was abſolutely ignorant of Pharmacie, having neither been Breed nor Inſtructed therein, although he keeped the Faſhion of an Apothecaries Shop, which afterward he quat, becauſe the Phyſicians would not Imploy a perſon of ſo little Skill. <hi>Secondly,</hi> All his Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vel abroad was only a Ship-board, where he could have no occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of exerciſing, much leſs of Improving himſelf in Pharmacy, which appeared very well when he offered himſelf to Tryal, for there he was found moſt Ignorant and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualified and rejected as ſuch, ſince which time he never had the confidence to offer himſelf to a new Tryal, in reſpect whereof, it was hoped the ſaids Lords would reject his Petition, and that the ſaids Lords would be pleaſed to declare that the Indulgence that they had allowed to the three youg Men, <hi>Lauder, Muirhead,</hi> and <hi>Edgar,</hi> was always upon condition that they be found Qualied at their reſpective Tryals, which laſt Supplication a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove written, being read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, together with the Anſwers made thereto by the ſaids Apothecarie, and they having heard, ſeen and conſidered the ſamen, They refuſed to grant the Deſire thereof; And thereafter there was another Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords by the ſaids Chirurgeon Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhewing that where they being informed that the ſaids Lords has decerned the Petitioners to make their Election preſently, at which of the Tables of Chirurgery or Pharmacy, we are to meet and ſit, whereat the Petitioners are greatly ſurpriſed, and in a manner in a conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſeing the ſaid point was never adviſed with our Lawyers, nor Informations given by the Petitioners to the ſaids Lords thereanent, nor the ſame craved by the Purſuers De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clartor, and in regard many of the Petitioners number are out of Town, and the time allowed very ſhort; and to the effect the Petitioners may deliberat <hi>ſedato animo</hi> in ſo weighty a Point, and not to do the ſame raſhly and in confuſion; Humbly beſeeching therefore, the ſaids Lords would grant the Petitioners ſuch a competent time as they may adviſe and be heard before the ſaids Lords, hopeing that ſome of the Petitioners, their Services in both Imployments to His Majeſty in his greateſt difficulties (when ſcarce one of the Purſuers were ſo much as heard of) and the Petitioners former care and ſucceſsful pains in Curing many of His Majeſties Leidges by exercing theſe Imployments, did prevail with the ſaids Lords to grant the Petitioners this ſo reaſonable and humble deſire; Whereinto it was <hi>Anſwered,</hi> that whereas it is pretended that the Point of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the Tables, and oblidging them to make their Election of what Table they will ſit at, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ook their Apprentices, accordingly was never adviſed with their Lawyers, nor Informations given in by them to the Lords thereanent, nor the ſame craved by the ſimple Apothecaries Declarator. It was Anſwered, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it was their own fault if they did neither adviſe with their Lawyers, nor give Informations to the Lords: The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179812:19"/> Points having been fully Debated ſeveral times, as is well known to the Lords themſelves. But <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Apothecaries and Chirurgeon-Barbars do oppone the ſeveral Bills and Anſwers given in on both ſides, and extant in Proceſs, ſince the Lords did pronounce their firſt Interlocutor for ſeparating the Callings; but eſpecially Sir <hi>George Lockhart</hi> Anſwers to the ſecond Bill, ſince given in for them by the Lord Advocat which is lying in the Clerks hands, by which it clearly appears that the Separation of the Tables was neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſequential to the Saparation of the Callings, and without which the firſt Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor was no perfect; So that it was calumnious for the Chirurgeon Apothecaries to pretend a Surpriſal, it being about a Month as will appear by the Dates of the ſaids Bills and Anſwers ſince they were well acquainted with the Point, in reſpect whereof, and that the Chirurgeon Apothecaries deſign was only to drive off this Seſſion, that thereby they may render the Lords Sentence <hi>eluſory</hi> and of none effect, by hindring the ſamen to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, and ſo to continue and perpetuat the Confuſion; And it was therefore hoped that the ſaids Lords would have no regard to the Petition, nor any other of that nature, but furthwith Order the Extracting of the Apothecaries Decreet, eſpecially ſeing the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices which ſome of theſe Chirurgeon Apothecaries pretend to have done to His Majeſty in his greateſt difficulty were neither ſo great, nor ſo long continued by very far, as they rendered to his Enemies of both Nations, who brought His Majeſties Royal Father and himſelf unto thoſe difficulties, which laſt Supplication and Anſwers above written made thereto, being likeways in read preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having alſo heard, ſeen and conſidered the ſame, refuſed to ſtop the Extracting of the foreſaid Declarator, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that if the Petitioners had any thing in Law to repreſent upon the morrow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, againſt the oblidging them to ſit at one Table, and to have the priviledges of both they would hear them: and thereafter there was an other Supplication given in to the ſaids Lords, by the ſaid <hi>Chirurgeon Apothecaries,</hi> ſhewing, That where they immediatly after ſight of the ſaids Lords their laſt deliverance upon the foreſaid Bill given by them, paſt that ſame Afternoon, which came to the Supplicants hands late at Night: the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners did their utmoſt endeavour to procure meeting of their Advocats, which after all imaginable diligence they could not obtain, in reſpect they were ſurcharged with a crude of Affairs the penult day of the Seſſion, and ſeing there were a great many matters of Fact coming daily to the Petitioners knowledge, whereby the inconſiſtency of the ſeparation of the two Tables of Chirurgery and Pharmacy during the Petitioners lifetimes, even to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Interloquitors will unqueſtionably be made appear, and which requires only the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberat advice of their Lawyers to put in form. It was therefore humbly craved, the ſaids Lords would ordain the Petitioners Advocats to Conſult them therein, to the effect the ſaids Lords might be fully cleared in that point, being confident to aſſert, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Purſuers nor Phyſicians their aſſiſtants has or ſhall be, have more loyaltie towards his Majeſty (ſome of the Petitioners being at <hi>Worcheſter</hi> Fight attending upon his Perſon, and ſequeſtrat for their loyaltie by the Uſurpers) nor has been, nor ſhall be more obſequous and ready to ſerve the ſaids Lords and Leidges with their skill and pains with the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, who has given proof to the whole Nation, how uſeful and neceſſar theſe Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments has been in their perſons, as the ſaid laſt Supplication alſo extant in Proces more fully bears, and which being likeways read in preſence of the ſaids Lords, and they having heard, ſeen, and conſidered the ſamen, found the deſire thereof improper for them to meddle in, and refuſed to give any ſtop upon ſuch pretences: and ordained the Decreet to be given out, <hi>Extractum de libris actorum per me ſic Subſcribitur George Mackenȝie Clerk Regiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Act in Favours of the Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the twenty ſixth day of <hi>March</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred &amp; Eighty four years anent the Supplication given in, and preſented to the Lords of Council an Seſſion, by the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> ſhewing, that where there being a Decreet of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarator pronounced by the Lords, ſeparating the two Callings of <hi>Chirurgerie</hi> and <hi>Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> and ordaining them to ſit at different Tables, and allowing the preſent <hi>Chirurgeon Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries</hi> to make their Election at which Table they will fit, under the certification, that if they did not condeſcend &amp; declare betwixt and a certain day conform to the ſaid Decreet, to be reputed as <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> and to ſit at their Table allanarly; and the Petitioners in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the ſaid Decreet of Declarator, having preſented a Petition to the Town Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> humbly deſiring the Magiſtrats and Council to nominat and appoint to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179812:19"/> them a Viſiter for conveening their Fraternity, and for trying their intrants, and that they would declare the Act of the Town Councis of the Twenty fifth of <hi>March</hi> one Thouſand ſix hundred &amp; fiftyſeven, &amp; all the priviledges therein contained did now properly belong to the Fraternity of <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> and not to the <hi>Apothecarie Chirurgeons,</hi> as being declared by the ſaid Decreet to be ſeparat and diſtinct Callings; the deſire of which Petition being ſo juſt, and the import and effect of the Lords Decreet of Declarator was at the firſt reading paſt <hi>nomine contradicente:</hi> but thereafter by the importunity and influence of the Deacon of the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> was thereafter ſtopped; and albeit the Petitioners has by renewed appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, earneſtly deſired the Magiſtrats and Council to grant the deſire to the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet they are not able to prevail, ſuch is the power and influence of the <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> The preſent Deacon who is a counſeller, being a Chirurgeon Apothecary, and in regard it is juſt and neceſſar for vindication of the Lords own authority, to ſee their own juſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and Sentences rendered effectual, and that the ſeparation of the two Callings of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie</hi> and <hi>Pharmacie</hi> was found by the Lords to be conſonant to Law, and founded upon conſideration of publick utility, and the good of his Majeſties Subjects, and that the ſaid Decreet of Declarator for ſeparating theſe two Callings of Pharmacy and Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery would be rendred Eluſory and of no effect, if the Petitioners ſhall not have a Viſiter nominat who may conveen their Fraternity of Pharmacy, and that it is the juſt import and effect of the ſaid Decreet of declarator, that the whole priviledges and immunities contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the foreſaid Act, declaring the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> in a Fraternity, ſhould be declared Solely to appertain and belong to the <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> as ſeparate and diſtinct from <hi>Apothecaries Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons;</hi> and therefore humbly craving, that the Lords would in vindication of their own authority, as well as the Petitioners Right, ordain the preſent Magiſtrats and Council to nominat and appoint a Viſitor, for conveening the Fraternity of Apothecaries upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and likeways to paſs an Act under the Town Council of <hi>Edinburghs</hi> Seal, declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeng the foreſaid Act dated the twenty fifth of <hi>March</hi> one Thouſand ſix hundred and fifty ſeven, and the priviledges therein contained only to belong to the Fraternity of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, as being now declared by the Lords Decreet, to be a ſeparate Calling from Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon Apothecaries, and that the Lords would be pleaſed to ordain the Magiſtrats and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to do the ſamen, under ſuch certifications as the Lords ſhould think juſt, whilk Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and deſire thereof being conſidered by the ſaids Lords, they ordained the Procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors for the Chirurgeon Apothecaries to ſee and anſwer the ſame the next day, which being accordingly given up to the ſaids Procurators to ſee, they returned the ſamen with the anſwers following, <hi>viz. Primo</hi> That it is ſtrange with what confidence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries can trouble the Lords with ſuch a groundleſs and rediculous Bill, ſeing they are not obliged Summarlie to anſwer upon a Bill, no man being obliged to anſwer upon a Bill where there is no depending Proces, except he be a Member of the Colledge of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and that in things relating properly to his Office and Employment; far leſs can any Incorporation or Community be obliged to anſwer upon a Bill without there were Signet Letters raiſed and the perſons formally cited, and the Proces came in to be called by the courſe of the Roll conform the Act of Regulation, for if it were allowed there ſhould be no uſe of Signet Letters, and would overthrow the foundation of Law and form. <hi>Secundo</hi> This is already depending before the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as appears by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries own Bill, they haveing given in a Petition to the Town Council to the ſame purpoſe, to whom it is proper to cognoſce upon ſuch differences, and to appoint Viſitors as they ſhall think fit, that being the Towns particular priviledge both by their Charters and by their Sett, it being expreſly provided by the Sett, that neither Merchants nor Crafts and their Deacons nor Viſitors, ſhall have or make any general or particular meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but by the advice of the Magiſtrats and Town Council, <hi>Tertio,</hi> It is a ſtrange piece of confidence that the Apothecaries ſhould deſire, that the Magiſtrats and Town Council ſhould be ordained to appoint a Viſitor for conveening their Fraternity, and to grant ſuch priviledges as they ſhall deſire, which is down right centrair to the priviledges of the Town and the Sett, and to crave that that ſhould be done under a certification, and that without ſo much as calling the Magiſtrats, then which there can be nothing more redicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and abſurd, and therefore ſeing the <hi>Chirurgeons</hi> and <hi>Chirurgeon Apothecaries</hi> are not obliged Summarly to anſwer a Bill, and that this Proces is already depending before the Town Council, to whom it properly belongs to cognoſce upon ſuch differences, and that the Magiſtrats whoſe priviledges are principally concerned are not called, the deſire of the Bill as moſt groundleſs and abſurd ought to be refuſed, and when the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> ſhall raiſe any action of Declarator, they ſhall have an anſwer: Whilk Supplication and deſires
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179812:20"/> thereof, and anſwers above written made thereto, being at length read, heard, ſeen, and conſidered by the ſaids Lords, and they being therewith well and ripely adviſed, the Lords of Council and Seſſion upon the eighteen of <hi>March</hi> inſtant, ordained the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to nominat and appoint a Viſitor for conveening the ſaid Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, thereafter the ſaid <hi>Apothecaries</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> gave in an other Supplication to the ſaids Lords, ſhewing that where the Petitioners having applyed to the Lords, repreſenting that albeit they had ſeveral times petitioned the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to nominat and appoint a Viſitor, to the effect the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> might meet and conveen for tryal and Examination of intrants and doing their other affairs, yet notwithſtanding ſuch w s the power and influence of the <hi>Chirurgeons,</hi> that they could not obtain ſo juſt a deſire, and which was done of purpoſe that the Petitioners might be deprived of the benefite of your Lordſhips Decreet of Declarator, ſeparating of the two Callings of Pharmacie and Chyrurgerie. And therefore craving that the Lords would ordain the Magiſtrates and Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to nominate a Viſitor which Petition and Anſwers thereto, being conſidered by the Lords, and they having found the ſamen moſt juſt and reaſonable, they did accordinglie ordain the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to nominate a Viſitor betwixt and the twenty one with Certification, that the ſaids Lords by their own Authority, would nominate and appoint a Viſitor, and which deliverance being intimat to the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> they in place of giving of obedience thereto, have nominate and appointed two Viſitors, whereof <hi>David Pringle</hi> the preſent Deacon of the Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is one which is in plain terms, to continue the conjunction of the two Calling of Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie and Pharmacie, and to render the Lords Decreet of Declarator, ſeparating the ſame, Eluſory and of no effect. And in regaird ſuch Inſolent proceedings, cannot be juſtified as being a contempt of the Lords Authority, to which the Magiſtrats and Council of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> ought to ſubmit and give all obedience. And therefore humbly craving that the Lords without furder delay, would nominate and appoint a Viſitor for conveening the Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of Apothecaries to meet on all occaſions, and in Vindication of their own honour and Authori y to inquire &amp; cenſure ſuch unwarrantable proceedings, whereby notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lords Decreet of Declarator, ſeparating the two Callings of Pharmacie and Cyrurgerie, the Magiſtrats and Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> have preſumed to nominate <hi>David Pringle</hi> preſent Deacon of the Chyrurgeons to be a Viſitor for the Apothecaries, and to diſcharge the ſaid <hi>David Pringle</hi> upon pretence of the ſaid Nommiation, to accept or to act in any ſuch Capacity, he being by the foreſaid Decreet of Declarator altogether incapable to ſit and meet at the Table of the Apothecaries, but only at the Table of the Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which Supplication and deſire thereof, being conſidered by the ſaids Lords, they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the Procurators for the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to ſee and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the ſamen, which being given up to their ſaid Procurators to ſee, they returned the ſame with the Anſwers following, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is ſo great inſolence in the ſaid Apothecaries to offer to trouble the Lords with ſuch a Bill againſt the Magiſtrats, who has been ſo kind to them, as to allow them to meet, whereas without their allowance, they could not meet nor have any Priviledge at all, and yet the Magiſtrats have been moſt ungra efully uſed by them, which was very unbecoming any Burgeſs within the Town, far leſs the Apothecaries to whom the Magiſtrates have done ſo many favours, but in anſwer to the Petition, It was humbly repreſented to the Lords. 1. That it is the undoubted Priviledge of the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> granted to them, by the firſt Erection, that no perſon can convocat and conveen within the Burgh, unleſs by the Authority and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Magiſtrats which was confirmed, to them by ſeveral Charters under the great Seal, granted to them by his Majeſties Royal Prediceſſors. As alſo it is expreſly provided by the Seventeenth Act <hi>Parliament</hi> eighteenth, King <hi>James</hi> the Sixt, that no perſon nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, within the Burgh of whatever Rank or condition they be of, preſume to take upon hand, under whatſomever Colour or Pretext, to Convocat or Aſſemble themſelves together at any occaſion, except they make due intimation of the lawful Cauſe of their Meetings to the Provoſt and Baillies within Burgh, and obtain their Licence thereto. 2. As this is clear from the Towns Charters by ſeveral Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſo it is likeways clear from the Set, and Decreet Arbitral pronounced by <hi>James</hi> his Majeſties Royal Grand-Father of ever bliſſed Memorie, by which it is expreſly provided, that neither Merchands amongſt themſelves neither the Crafts and their Deacons or Viſitors, ſhal have or make any particular or general Conventions, as Deacon with Deacons, Deacons with their Craft or Crafts amongſt themſelves far leſs, to make private Laws or Statuts to Poynd and Diſtringȝie at
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179812:20"/> their own hands, for tranſgreſſions without advice and conſent of the Provoſt, Baillies and Council, which is confirmed by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> by which it is evident, that none of the Crafts can meet among themſelves, nor Deacon with Deacons, can warrantablely meet without warrand from the Magiſtrats, far leſs can any other Perſons that are none of the Crafts meet amongſt themſelves without warrand from the Magiſtrats, who many appoint one to Conveen and proceed among them, and diſolve them at their pleaſure, and appoint a Viſitor, to any that they ſhall allow to be in a Fraternity as they ſhall think fit. 3. The Appothecaries not being any of the Fourteen Trades, which are only allowed by the Set, nor any part of the ſaids Crafts, they upon Applicat on made to the Chyrurgeons in the year, 1657. deſiring to come under their Potection, and that they would interpoſe for them to the Magiſtrats, to allow them to conveen with the Chyrurgeons, and that there may be Viſitors appointed, and to try Intrants, and accordingly the Magiſtrats by an Act of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, did appoint two Viſitors, an Chyrurgeon and Apothecarie, who with one or two of the Baillies and Dean of Gild, might viſit the ſufficiencie of all Drugs within the Burgh and Liberties thereof, which Act of the Town Council, was thereafter ratified by expreſs Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the year 1670. And be that Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> it is provided that if any perſon ſhal find themſelves prejudged and wronged by the determination of either of the ſaids Incorporations and Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her-hood reſpective, contrair to the Laws, Rights, Liberties and Priviledges, and power granted to them or either of them, that then, and in that caſe they ſhall have recourſe to the Magiſtrats and Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> who may determine in theſe caſes for both Parties, ſo that both be the ſaid Act of Councill, and Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> Ratifying the ſamen; It is evident, that the Apothecaries can have no Viſitor, but ſuch as the Town ſhall appoint, that there has allways been a Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of the Viſitors, and the Apothecaries having given in a Petition to the Magiſtrats, Craving that they may have the Sole benefite, and Priviledge of the Act of Council in the year <hi>One Thouſand Six Hundred Fiftie Seven,</hi> and the Chirurgeons have given in a counter Petition, that now ſeing the Apothecaries do ſeparat themſelves from them, and that the Apothecaries were none of the Fourteen Crafts, they ought not to have any Priviledge at all by the ſaid Act of Council in the year <hi>One thouſand ſix hundred fifty ſeven,</hi> and the Magiſtrats that they might do that which was juſt and equal to them both, they did appoint an Apothecarie, and the Deacon of the Chirurgeons to be Viſitors, together with a Baillie and the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Gild,</hi> with Power to the ſaids Viſitors to do every thing as they were formerlie Impowered to do by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Act of Council in the year <hi>One thouſand ſix hundred fifty ſeven,</hi> which is Ratified by Act of Parliament; So that it is ſtrange with what confidence theſe Apothecaries can contravert this new Act of Council made by the Magiſtrats, being conform to the former Act of Council, and Act of Parliament: And whereas it is pretended that the two Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings being now ſeparat by Decreet of the Lords, a Chirurgeon ought not to be one of the Viſitors to the Apothecaries. It is Anſwered, that it being the Priviledge of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats, that no Perſon can meet under the notion of fraternities within the Burgh, unleſs by the Magiſtrats Warrand, they upon that Ground have undoubted Right to appoint one to proceed among them, and to be Viſitors; and the Magiſtrats are not concerned in the Separation of the Tables, for that cannot derogat from their Priviledge, and they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point any Perſon to proceed amongſt them, albeit he were neither Apothecary nor Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon, but any of the Magiſtrats may be appointed to Viſit and proceed; but it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways moſt neceſſary that an Chirurgean be appointed with an Apothecary to be Viſitors; ſeing that it is as neceſſar to conſider the ſufficiency of Drugs as well inward as outward applications; and the Deacon of the Chirurgeons appointed, being an Chirurgeon Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie, he has as good Skill of Drugs as any of the Apothcaries, and the Magiſtrats may appoint any Perſon to viſit that has Skill of Drugs; as alſo, there is an expreſs proviſion in the Patent granted to the Phyſians that all Drugs ſhall be viſite by one of the Magiſtrats of the Town with an Apothecary and Chirurgeon Apothecary, and therefore this being the undoubted priviledge of the Magiſtrats to name Viſitors, and to appoint any perſon they ſhall think fit to conveen and proceed amongſt ſuch Perſons as they ſhall allow to be in a fraternity, and having accordingly named Viſitors, the Deacon of the Chirurgeons ought not to be Excluded, but the Deſire of ſuch an inſolent and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Bill given in againſt the Magiſtrats by the Apothecaries who ows any Liberty they have to the Town, ought to be refuſed, and they ought to reſt ſatisfied by the Nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by the Magiſtrats; And if it were otherways, then any Number of Perſons that pretended to be a Calling, albeit none of them, any part of the Fourteen Trades might
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179812:21"/> upon a Petition to the Lords crave a Viſitor, and one to conveen and proceed amongſt them, and ſo in place of Fourteen Crafts might have erect a hundred without conſent of the Magiſtrats, which is down-right contrair to the Burghs Priviledges and the Set of the Burgh, which is confirmed by Act of Parliament; And it was never yet practiſed that any Viſitor, or any Perſon that was appointed to proceed in a Fraternity was allowed, but ſuch as were appointed by the Magiſtrats; and this being the great Priviledge of the Burgh, which they have by the Set and Golden Charter; It is hoped the Lords will be very tender of the good Towns Priviledge, and not put them in the Ballance with the ſaid few Apothecaries, in a matter that ſo much concerns the Towns Priviledges; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the leaſt difficultie remained with the Lords, humbly craved an hearing in their own preſence; Whilk Supplication, deſire thereof, and Anſwers above-written made thereto being at length read, heard, ſeen and conſidered by the ſaids Lords; And they being therewith well and ripely Adviſed, the Lords of Council and Seſſion do <hi>pro hac vice,</hi> Nominat and appoint, and hereby Nominats and appoints <hi>John Joiſie</hi> Apothecary Burgeſs of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to be Viſitor for conveening the Fraternity of Apothecaries on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and have found, and hereby finds that in time coming the Magiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> ought to nominat one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theſe Perſons, who ſit and meet at the Table of Apothecaries, to be Viſitor of the ſaid Fraternity of Apothecaries, <hi>Extractum de Libris actorum per me,</hi> Sic Subſcribitur <hi>George Mackenȝie, Clericus Registri.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Follows another Act in Favours of the Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the Twenty fifth day of <hi>March, One thouſand ſix hundred eighty five</hi> years, anent the Supplication given in, and preſented before the Lords of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil and Seſſion, by the Apothecaries within the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Shewing that whereas the Lords having by the Decreet of declarator in the Petitioners Favours upon very Rational and important Conſiderations Separat the two Callings of Chirurgery and Pharmacy, and Ordained in time coming, the ſeveral Trades to ſit at different Tables, for making of which Decreet effectual; The Petitioners having thereafter applyed to the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> for the time, that they might appoint a Viſitor for conveening the Petitioners Fraternity, which they having refuſed, by the influence and importunity of the Deacons. The Lords did interpoſe their Authority by Ordaining them to do the ſamen; and thereafter they having in an inſolent manner given in a ſort of a mock Obedience to the Lords Sentence by nominating a Chirurgeon and an Apothecary to be joynt Viſitors of the Petitioners Fraternity, which was in effect a new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction by their own Authority o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e two Trades, which the Lords by ſo ſolemn a Decreet has Separat, upon which high and inſolent contempt of the Lords Sentences; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Petitioners having thereafter preſented a new Petition, Complaining of their ſaid deportment, the Lords were pleaſed, after both the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, and the Town of <hi>Edinb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgh</hi> their Procurators had given in Anſwers to the ſeveral Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, containing a full repreſentation of all their Grounds, and finding that the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> refuſed to give any obedience to ſupply the ſamen, by interpoſing the Lords Authority in vindication of their reiterated Acts and Sentences, and did appoint <hi>John Joiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> to be ſole Viſitor, for conveening the Fraternity of Apothecaries on all occaſions for that year; and did find, that in time-coming the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> ought to nominate one of theſe perſons who ſits at the Table of Apothecaries Viſitor of the Fraternity, And now the Petitioners having applyed to the preſent Magiſtrats for nominating a Viſitor for this enſuing year, conform to the Lords former Ordinance, being one of theſe that ſits at the Petitioners own Table, and to that effect, having given in a Liſt of ſuch perſons, to the effect they might make a choice, they were ſo far from having any regard to the ſaids Lords Sentences and Acts above-mentioned, whereby the Trades were ſeparate, and they appointed to nominat a Viſitor of the Petitioners own Faternity, which were all given in to the Clerk, and produced before them in Council, that in manifeſt contempt thereof, by a previous Combination of the Deacons and Tradeſmen, who influences the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, they have again proceeded for this enſuing year, to nominat a Chyrurgeon and an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary, to be joint Viſitors of the Petitioners Fraternity, and an intrant Apothecary hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing applyed for a Tryal, they have recommended him to the ſaids Viſitors, which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways formerly refuſed; and likewiſe they refuſe to give the Petitioners out an extract of their ſaid Nomination, of purpoſe to protract this Seſſion, that the Petitioners may not have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179812:21"/> to ſeek redreſs from the Lords: And ſeing they have no other remeid, but now to apply to the Lords, for vindication of their ſaids Priviledges, and likewiſe of the Lords own Authority, againſt ſo frequent and reiterated acts of Contempt and Diſobedience; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humbly craving, that the Lords would be pleaſed as formerly, ſo far this enſuing year; to nominat one of theſe who ſit at the Petitioners own Table, to be their Viſitor, out of a Liſt herewith given in or elſe to prevent the Lords trouble in all time-coming, to allow the Petitioners themſelves to meet and choiſe yearly their own Viſitor, and to admit of Intrants by the Petitioners own Authority, ſeing the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> have ſo frequently refuſed the ſame, as the ſaid Supplication bears; which being Conſidered by the ſaids Lords, they Ordained the Procurators for the Magiſtrats and Town-Council of the ſaid Burgh, to ſee the ſaid Supplication, and to anſwer the ſame upon Tueſday next thereafter; which being accordingly given up to the ſaids Prucurators to ſee, they returned the ſamen with the Anſwers following, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is ſtrange with what confidence the Apothecaries can give the Lords the trouble by ſuch an groundleſs and inſolent Bill, which doth ſo highly reflect upon the Magiſtrats, and it does evidently appear, that it ſeems they would ſtate themſelves in an Incorporation, without owning their priviledge or dependance from the Magiſtrats, which is a down right Incroachment upon the Priviledges of the City, that any that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys their Trade and Calling within the Good-Town, and are Burgeſſes, ſhould treat the Magiſtrats at that rate that theſe Apothecaries does, whereas they had never ſo much as an allowance, nor could not meet on their pretended Fraternity, unleſs it had been by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats tollerance; ſo that it is moſt improper for them to call the Towns Priviledges in queſtion. Therefore it is Anſwered to the Petition, 1. That whatever Acts or Decreets they may pretend to have in their favours, ſeparating the two Callings of Chyrurgery and Pharmacy, and appointing diſtinct Tables, the Magiſtrats were not concerned in theſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creets, they not being called thereto, and ſo was <hi>res inter alios acta</hi> as to them; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever theſe Acts or Decreets may take amogſt themſelves, yet that can never prejudge the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Good-Town. 2. By the <hi>Sett,</hi> which is the fundamental Conſtitution of the Burgh, and by many Laws and Acts of Parliament, it is expreſly provided, <hi>That there ſhall be made no Meetings within Burgh, of any Society or Fraternity, but by the Warrand and Authority of the Magiſtrats:</hi> And if theſe Apothecaries, who pretend to a Fraternity, cannot ſo much as meet and conveen without Licenſe from the Magiſtrats, far more has the Magiſtrats Power to name who ſhal proceed amongſt them, or Viſitors who ſhal viſit the Drugs in the Apothecaries Shops, and appoint the method and way and manner thereof within the ſaid Burgh. 3. It is clear by the Patent granted to the Phyſicians, that the Drugs are to be viſited by an Chyrurgeon-Apothecary and an Apothecary, ſo that the Magiſtrats and Town-Council having named Viſitors, conform to the Phyſicians Patent under the Great-Seal, the ſamen can never be queſtioned as being done contrary to the pretended Priviledges, but what the Good-Town is pleaſed to allow them. 4. It is clear by ſeveral Acts of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties privy Council, one in <hi>November</hi> and another in <hi>January</hi> laſt, poſterior to all theſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Acts and Decreets which the Apothecaries founded upon, whereby it is expreſly ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Drugs ſhould be viſited conform to the Phyſicians Patent, and conſequently it ought to be done by an Chyrurgeon-Apothecary and an Apothecary, as is provided by the ſaid Patent: And albeit the laſt Act of Council mentions two Apothecaries to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, yet that can only be underſtood in the terms of the Patent, ſeing that Act ordains expreſly that the Viſitation ſhal be made conform to the Patent. And ſeing that by the Decreet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating the two Callings, it is expreſly provided that the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries that was then in exerciſe of both Callings, ſhould continue in exerciſe of the ſamen during their lifetimes, &amp; that the Magiſtrats &amp; Town-Council has appointed an Chyrurgeon-Apothecary, who by the ſaid Decreet has the liberty and freedom of exerciſing both Callings to be join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an Apothecary for viſiting the Drugs, the ſaid Nomination ſo deliberatly done by the Town-Council ought to be ſuſtained; and it is humbly expected of the Lords Juſtice, that they would be tender of the Priviledges of the Good-Town, and not to take from them that which is their greateſt Priviledge, which they enjoy by the <hi>Sett,</hi> and their ancient Rights, and Golden-Charter, granted to them by the Kings Majeſties Royal Predeceſſors, <hi>That no Society or Fraternity ſhall be allowed to meet within Burgh, but whom the Magiſtrats and Town-Council ſhould allow; and that none ſhall proceed or conveen the ſaid Fraternity, nor be appointed Viſitors, but whom the Magiſtrats and Town-Council ſhall think fit:</hi> For if it ſhould be otherways ſuſtained, it would tend directly to overturn the fundamental and ancient Priviledges of the Burgh, and therefore the deſire of the Bill, as being moſt ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and inſolent and impertinent ought to be refuſed. Which Supplication, and deſire
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179812:22"/> thereof, and Anſwers above-written made thereto, being all at length read, heard, ſeen and conſidered by the ſaids Lords. <hi>The Lords of Council and Seſſion, in regard of the ſaids Magiſtrats and Town-Council their irregular Nomination of Viſitors, contrair to the ſaids Lords their former Act, Do as of before,</hi> pro hace vice, <hi>Nominat and Appoint, and hereby No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minats and Appoints</hi> John Fowlis <hi>Apothecary to be Viſitor for Conveening the Fraternity of</hi> Apothecaries <hi>upon all occaſions: And have found, and hereby finds, that the Magiſtrats in time-coming ought to nominat one of theſe perſons who ſit and meet at the Table of</hi> Apothecaries, <hi>to be Viſitor of the ſaid Fraternity.</hi> Extractum de libris Actorum, per me, <hi>Sic ſubſcribitur,</hi> Geo: Mackenȝie, <hi>Cler. Regiſtr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Follows the Ratification in favours of the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi> At <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the ſixteenth day of <hi>June,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred eighty and five years.</head>
               <p>OUR SOVERAIGN LORD, with Advice and Conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament: Ratifies, Approves, and perpetually Confirms to and in favours of the Fraternity of Apothecaries within the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> all Liberties, Priviledges, Immunities, Seals of Cauſe, or others whatſomever conceived in their favours, or granted to them at any time whatſomever, either by his Majeſty, or the Good-Town of <hi>Edinburgh:</hi> And likewiſe, all Decreets, Acts, Sentences in their favours, either of his Majeſties privy Council, Lords of the Seſſion, or any other Judicatory within this Kingdom, which are relative to their ſaids Privilidges, and ſpecially but prejudice of the generality of an Decreet of Declarator before the Lords, dated the twenty fourth day of <hi>March</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty two years: <hi>Declaring,</hi> That the Imployments of <hi>Chyrurgery</hi> and <hi>Pharmacy</hi> are diſtinct, and that the ſamen ſhould not be exerciſed by one perſon within the City of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties thereof, and all other Heads, Articles and Interloquitors conceived in their favours contained in the ſaid Decreet; And likewiſe, two ſeveral Acts of the Lords of Seſſion, one dated the twenty ſixth day of <hi>March</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty four years, and the other the twenty fifth day of <hi>March</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty five years, whereby the ſaids Lords, upon the Town of <hi>Edinburghs</hi> refuſal, did themſelves nominat one who ſits at the Table of the Apothecaries to be Viſitor to their Fraternity, and likewiſe found, that the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> ought in all time-coming to nominat ſuch a perſon to be their Viſitor. Extracted furth of the Records of Parliament, by <hi>George</hi> Viſcount of <hi>Tarbat,</hi> Lord <hi>Mackleod</hi> and <hi>Castlehaven,</hi> Clerk to his Majeſties Parliament, Council, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters and Rolls, <hi>&amp;c. Sic ſubſcribitur,</hi> TARBAT, <hi>Cler. Regiſtr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>ACT in Favours of the Fraternity of the Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the ninth Day of <hi>March,</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty ſix years, anent the Supplication given in and preſented to the Lords of Council and Seſſion by the Fraternity of Apothecaries within the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Shewing, that where the ſaids Lords by the Decreet of Declarator in the Petitioners favours upon very Rational and Important Conſiderations, ſeparate the two Callings of Chirurgery and Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and ordained in time coming the ſaids two Trades to ſit at different Tables, for making which Decreet effectual, the Petitioners having thereafter applyed to the Magiſtrats and Town-Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> for the time that they might appoint a Viſitor for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening the Petitioners Fraternity, which they having then refuſed, the ſaids Lords did interpone their Authority by ordaining them to do the ſame, and thereafter they having in an inſolent manner, to elude the ſaids Lords Sentence, nominate an Chyrurgeon and an Apothecary to be joynt Viſitors of the ſaids Petitioners Fraternity, upon which the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners did preſent a new Petition complaining of the ſaid Deportment, the ſaid Lords were pleaſed upon Conſideration of the Bill and Anſwers, whereby it appeared that the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> did refuſe to give any Obedience to interpoſe their own Authority by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing <hi>John Joisſie</hi> to be ſole Viſitor for conveening the Fraternity of the Appothecaries for that year on all Occaſions, and did find by their Interloquitor that in time coming, the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> ought to nominate on of theſe Perſons who ſit at the Table of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries Viſitor of the Fraternity, and notwithſtanding of which Nomination and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance in the Petitioners Favours, they having for the next enſuing year again applyed to the Magiſtrats and Town-Council that they would nominat a Viſitor of their own Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179812:22"/> and having for that effect given in a Liſt of ſeveral Perſons of their own number that they might choice, they had ſo little regard to the ſaids Lords their former Ordination, that for that year they did again proceed in manifeſt contempt and Deriſion of the ſaids Lords Authority to nominat an Chirurgeon and an Apothecary to be joynt Viſitors of the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners Fraternity which the ſaids Lords at the end of the laſt Seſſion did ſo far reſent, that upon a new Petition given in by the Petitioners, repreſenting, that the ſaids procedure did Nominat and appoint <hi>John Fowlis</hi> Apothecary to be Viſitor for that year, and found by their Interloquitor, that in all time coming, the Magiſtrats ought to nominate one who ſits at the Apothecaries Table to be Viſitor of the Fraternity, and that the Nominations made by the Magiſtrats at that time were irregular, as the ſeveral Acts therewith produced will teſtify; and likewiſe in farder Teſtimony of the ſaids Lords Diſpleaſure, they did call in the Town Aſſesſors for the time, and did publickly cenſure them for giving ſuch unreaſonable Advice in Contempt of the ſaids Lords Sentences, and although the Petitioners might now have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that the Lords ſo frequent reiterated Ordinances would have met with very punctual Obedience, yet now the third time they have proceeded to that pitch of Contempt and Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to the ſaids Lords their Authority, that the Petitioners having applyed for a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor for this enſuing year, and conform to the ſaids Lords their Decreet and Ordinances, and having given in a liſt for that effect, they have conform to their former Cuſtom again proceeded to Nominate an Apothecary and Chirurgeon to be Viſitors of the Petitioners Fraternity, which to the high and manifeſt contempt of the ſaids Lords Authority, that tho' the Petitioners ſhould be ſilent the ſaids Lords are concerned to vindicate the ſame, and to fall upon ſome expedient for the Future for making the ſaids Lords Decreets in the Petitioners Favours effectual, and preventing ſuch Incroachments upon the Petitioners priviledges, that it may not be in the power of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to reunite theſe two Trades which the ſaids Lords has ſeparat by ſo ſolemn a Decreet which is all upon the matter as to aſſume to themſelves the power of reducing the ſaids Lords Sentences; and therefore humbly crav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſaids Lords would be pleaſed as they did for theſe two years preceeding to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat <hi>pro hac vice</hi> one of the Petitioners own Fraternity conform to a Bill given in; And likewiſe ſeing that every year the ſaids Lords met with this trouble, and the Magiſtrats ſeem to be obſtinate in their Diſobedience to the ſaids Lords Decreet, that therefore the ſaids Lords in time coming for preventing ſuch trouble, would allow the Petitioners to choice their own Viſitor in all time comeing, as in the ſaid Supplication is at more length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, whilk Supplication and deſire thereof being conſidered by the ſaids Lords, they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> their Procurators to ſee the Petition and to anſwer there to againſt the next day thereafter <hi>peremptorie;</hi> And the ſaids Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> their Procurators having failȝied to give in Anſwers to the ſaid Petition, the ſaids Lords in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect thereof granted warrand to Macers to cite the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to compear and anſwer to the Petiton above-written, upon <hi>Tueſday</hi> next being the day and date of thir preſents, and appointed them this day to produee the Act mentioned in the foreſaid Petition, whereby they did Nominat an Apothecary and a Chyrurgeon Viſitors of the Fraternity of Appothecaries for this year by vertue whereof, upon the eight day of <hi>March</hi> inſtant, <hi>William Maxwell</hi> one of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers before the Lords lawfully Cited the Provoſt, Baillies, Dean of Gild, and Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the ſaid Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> preſent Magiſtrats thereof, to Compear before the ſaids Lords this day, bringing with them the foreſaid Act, in obedience whereunto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared the ſaids Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in preſence of the ſaids Lords by Sir <hi>John Lauder</hi> Advocat their Procurator, who for them produced two Acts of Council, the one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is dated the twenty ſixth day of <hi>February</hi> laſt by paſt, whereby the ſaids Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> Elected and choiſed <hi>John Joiſie</hi> Apothecary to be Viſitor for this enſuing year, for conveening of the ſaid Fraternity of Apothecaries upon all occaſions, and the other of the ſaids Acts dated the third day of <hi>March</hi> inſtant, whereby the ſaids Magiſtrats up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Petition given in by the Chirurgeon Apothecaries of the ſaid Burgh, appointed <hi>David Pringle,</hi> Chirurgeon Apothecary to be Viſitor for the Chirurgeon Apothecaries for this enſuing year, providing it be agreeable to the Lords Decreet, and Acts made anent the Apothecaries and Chirugreon Apotheciares; and the Patent granted by his Majeſtie to the Colledge of Phyſicians and no otherways, as the ſaids two Acts bears, which Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deſire thereof, with the foreſaids two Acts produced by the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> in obedience to the ſaids Lords their Ordinance above-expreſt, by the firſt of which they did nominat <hi>John Joiſie</hi> Viſitor, and by the laſt <hi>David Pringle</hi> Chirurgeon Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie, Viſitors for the Chirurgeon Apothecaries, being all at length heard, ſeen and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:179812:23"/> by the ſaids Lords, and they therewith being well and reaply adviſed; The ſaids Lords have found, and hereby finds the laſt Nomination of <hi>David Pringle</hi> to be void &amp; null, and declares the ſamen to bear no Faith in Judgement, nor out with the ſame in time coming, and have appointed, and hereby appoints <hi>John Joiſie</hi> to be ſole Viſitor for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veening the Fraternity of Apothecaries this year at all Occaſions, and the ſaids Lords de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that if the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhall at any time hereafter contraveen the former Act by nameing a Chirurgeon Apothecary Viſitor for the Fraternity of the ſaids Apothecaries yearly, they will allow the ſaids Apothecaries to name their own Viſitor in all time coming. <hi>Extractum ex Libro actorum per me,</hi> Sic Subſcribitur. TARBAT. <hi>Clk.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>One other Act in Favours of the Fraternity of the Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the Thirty day of <hi>June, One thouſand ſix hundred and eighty ſeven years,</hi> anent the Petition given in, and preſented to the Lords of Council and Seſſion by the Fraternity of Apothecaries within the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhewing that whereas the Lords after the Decreet of Separation of the two Callings of Pharmacy and Chirurgery did appoint them to ſit at different Tables, and likeways did appoint the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by ſeveral Acts and Deliverances to nominat one of their Fraternity to be Viſitor o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Calling, &amp; the Town being ſo influenced by the Chirurgeon Apothecaries who are one of the Trades, as always to Nominat one of their own Number to be their Viſitor in manifeſt contempt of the Lords frequent and reiterated Acts, which the Lords did find ſo unreaſonable, and inconſiſtent with the ends of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>paration, that now for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe five or ſix years laſt by paſt, when the Town did nominat an Chirurgeon Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be Viſitor, the Lords did moſt juſtly Reſcind the ſaid Nomination, and every year ſince the ſaid Separation in reſpect of their contumacy and diſobedience did nominat one of the Petitioners number to be Viſitors, and by an Act in the Petitioners Favours, in <hi>March, One thouſand ſix hundred</hi> and <hi>eighty ſix years,</hi> the Lords did not only Reſcind the Nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>David Pringle,</hi> and did nominat <hi>John Joiſie</hi> in his place who is a ſimple Apothecarie to be Viſitor of the Fraternity for the then enſuing year, but likeways declared that if the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhould at any time thereafter nominat an Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon Apothecary to be the Petitioners Viſitor, that they would devolve upon the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners themſelves, the Nomination in all time coming of their own Viſitor; And likeways the Petitioners having applyed to the Lords in <hi>December</hi> laſt, upon the Illegal Nomination of <hi>John Baillie,</hi> and Mr. <hi>James Mackmath,</hi> the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and the Chirurgeon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries did give in an Anſwer founded upon an Patent from His Majeſtie in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, taking off the ſaid Decreet of Separation and reuniting the Trades, and the Lords by their Deliverance after they were three or four times Ordained to produce the ſaid Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, did at length in reſpect of their refuſeal to produce the ſamen Diſcharge the two Perſons then Nominat to Officiat, and did appoint <hi>John Joiſie</hi> to conveen who was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Nominat by the Lords until the expiring of the year for which he was Nominat, and now the year being elapſed, and the Petitioners having again applyed to the Town Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and gave in a Liſt of theſe of the Petitioners Fraternity, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats by their Deliverance, have not only refuſed the Deſire of the Bill, in reſpect of the Patent granted in Favours of the Chirurgeon Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, but have appointed the two perſons whom the Lords formerly diſcharged to Officiat, to be again received, <hi>viz. John Baillie,</hi> and Mr. <hi>James Mackmath.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humbly craving, that ſeing the Lords by their Deliverance in <hi>March</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty ſix years, declared, if the Town-Council would proceed to nominat an Chyrurgeon-Apothecary to be the Petitioners Viſitor in time-coming, the Lords would allow the Petitioners to nominat their own Viſitor; and likewiſe they have refuſed to produce their Patent to the Lords in <hi>December</hi> laſt, though they founded their Anſwers thereupon to the Petitioners Petition, that therefore the Lords would be pleaſed upon the Conſiderations foreſaid, in the firſt place to diſcharge <hi>John Baillie,</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>James Mack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>math</hi> to Officiat in the ſaid Office, as the ſaids Lords did formerly in <hi>December</hi> laſt, and to Nominat one of the Petitioners number, according to the Liſt given in, or to free the Lords of this perpetual trouble, that the Lords would allow the Petitioners the Nomination of their own Viſitor in all time-coming, as the ſaids Lords declared by their Deliverance in <hi>March</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and eighty ſix years. Whilk Petition and deſire thereof,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:179812:23"/> being read in Audience of the ſaids Lords, and they being therewith well and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſed: The Lords of Council and Seſſion, have diſcharged, and hereby diſcharges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons Nominat Viſitors by the Town-Council of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> to Officiat, and have Nom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> and Appointed, and hereby Nominats and Appoints <hi>Hugh Neilſon</hi> to be Viſitor of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ternity of the Apothecaries for this year. <hi>Extractum ex libro actorum, per me, ſic ſubſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bitur.</hi> Al Gibſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>One other Act in Favours of the Fraternity of Apothecaries of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the Ninteen day of <hi>July,</hi> 1683, years, Anent the Petition given in, and preſented to the Lords of Council and Seſſion, be the Fraternity of the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries within the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi> Shewing that whereas the Lords having by their Decreet ſeveral years ago, upon very rational and Important Grounds, ſeparat the two Callings of Pharmacy and Chyrurgerie, and for makeing the ſaid Separation effectual, did appoint them to Sit at two different Tables, and the Lords having afterwards appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by ſeveral Acts and diliverances to nominat, one of their Fraternity to be Viſitor of the Calling, and the Town having always complyed with the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, who are one of their Trads, to nominat one of their Number to be Viſitors to the Apothecaries, which the Lord did find ſo unreaſonable, and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the ends of the ſeparation, that now for theſe four years by paſt, when they did nominat an Chyrurgeon-Apothecarie, the Lords did moſt juſtly reſcind the ſaid Nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in reſpect of their Contimacie and diſobedience, did themſelves nominat, ane ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Apothecarie for theſe ſeveral years by paſt, and did ſo far reſent the diſobedience that in <hi>March,</hi> 1685, years, Sir <hi>Patrick Hume</hi> the Towns Aſſeſſor, for the time was called in before the Lords, and publickly rebuked, for giving the Town ſo unreaſonable an advice, and particularlie in <hi>March,</hi> 1686, years, the Lords by their Act in the Apothecaries fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which is produced in Proces, ſand that the Nomination of <hi>David Pringle</hi> a Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon-Apothecarie, was void and null, and in his place appoint <hi>John Joiſie</hi> a ſimple Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie, to be ſole Viſitor for that year, and farder declared, that if the Magiſtrats and Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> ſhould at an time thereafter nominate ane Chyrurgeon-Apothecarie to be Viſitor of the Apothecaries Fraternity, that the Lords would allow the Petitioners, to name their own Viſitor in all time coming, likeas the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>December,</hi> 1686, years, upon pretence of a Patent lately obtained from his Majeſty, in favours of the Chyrurgeons-Apothecaries, taken upon them to Nominat a Viſitor to the Petitioners Fraternity, notwithſtanding that <hi>John Joiſie,</hi> was at the time Viſitor be the Lords own appointment, and that this year was not expired, the Lords were pleaſed by their Interloquitor upon the eighteen of <hi>December,</hi> the ſaid year to Diſcharge the Viſitor, appointed be the Town Council, and to continue the ſaid <hi>John Joiſie</hi> Viſitor of the Petitioners Fraternity, until the expiring of the year, for which he was nominat by the Lords. And farder in <hi>Anno</hi> 1687, the Petitioners did apply to the Town Council, to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat a Viſitor which they having delayed, the Petitioners were neceſſitat again to mean themſelves to the Lords, and after hearing all the anſwers given in by the Town Council, the Lords did appoint <hi>Hugh Nilſon</hi> to be Viſitor for that year, as is evident by the Act pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in Proces, and now the Petitioners having again applyed to the Magiſtrats and Town Council, to appoint a Viſitor to the Petitioners Fraternity for this year, they have after their uſual manner delayed to give any anſwer, and ſince the Petitioners have no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of Redreſs, againſt ſo frequent and reiterated Acts of contempt, and diſobedience to the Lords Authority, and incroachments upon juſt Priviledges, but to make a new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint and Repreſentation of the ſaids abuſes, and therefore humbly Craving the Lords would conſider the former Acts for theſe ſeveral years by paſt, and particularly that in <hi>March,</hi> 1686, whereby the Lords nominate <hi>John Joiſie</hi> for that year, and declaired that if the Town did nominat in any time thereafter a Chyrurgeon-Apothecarie, that the Lords would allow the Petitioners to choiſe and nominat their own Viſitor, as the laſt Act in <hi>June,</hi> 1687. appointing <hi>Hugh Neilſon</hi> to be Viſitor for that year enſueing, and to ſave the Lords from all furder trouble, to declair that in all time coming, that the Petitioners ſhall have liberty to Choiſe, and nominat their own Viſitor, as in the ſaid Petition at more length, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teained whilk Petition being Read in Audience of the ſaids Lords, they ordained the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curators of the Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> to ſee the ſaid Petition, and anſwer the ſame the next day peremptorie, according whereinto the Procurators of the ſaid Town of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> having got up the Petition to ſee, they reproduced the ſamen, and gave in the anſwers
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179812:24"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as follows, <hi>viz.</hi> It is anſwered that their being a Petition given in to the Town <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>cil of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> by the ſimple Apothecaries, the beginning of this Moneth of <hi>July,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ving that the Magiſtrats would nominat one of their Number, to be Viſitor for this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eing year, the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> did moſt warrantably and Moderatly carie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erein, by ordaining the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries, to ſee and anſwer the foreſaid Petition, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut before their anſwers could be given, or the Magiſtrats could medle with it, the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on of Burrows, and the Lord Provoſt his going to Court ſo Interveened, that the Town Council could give no anſwer to the foreſaid Petition, while that now after mature deliber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and takeing his Majeſties Royal Gift, reſtoring the Chyrurgeon-Apothecaries to their former Priviledges, notwithſtanding of ane previous Decreet of Separation, with a Letter from the Secretary of State, direct to the Lord High Chancellour, bearing his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Inclinations, that his Lordſhip and the Preſident of the Seſſion, ſhould conſider both Patents, Decreets of Separation, and all other differences betwixt the Phyſitians, Chyrurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons-Apothecaries, and ſimple Apothecaries, that the ſame Might be reported to his ſacred Majeſtie, and the determination might be made by his Majeſtie, as might end theſe Debats betwixt them, and in the mean time Stopping all Proceſs relating thereunto, until his Majeſties further pleaſure ſhould be known therein, they have upon ſuch unquarrellable grounds, and his ſacred Majeſties Pleaſure and Command ſo often repeated to them, declared that they can do no Deed prejudicial there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, until the will of the ſaid Letter be fulfilled, or the new Gift in favours of the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon Apothecaries be reduced, as the Double of the ſaid Letter from the Secretary of State direct to the Lord High Chancellor, with the double of the ſimple Apothecaries Petition to the Town Council of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and their Deliverance on the back thereof produced teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; by all which it appears that the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> have not been <hi>in mora,</hi> as is falſly ſuggeſted, but they as all their Predeceſſors have ſtill given ready Obedience to his Majeſties Commands, and did not think it fit after ſo full and ample a Gift to ſuch a diſtinct &amp; clear Letter, to meddle with either Parties therein, but the Truth is, this Affair is managed by a Company of ſome head-ſtrong People, who make it their Buſineſs to creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Diviſion, and make Parties in all the Societies and Incorporations of the Town, and who being ſworn Burgeſſes thereto, for which calumnious Petitions as they have given in theſe ſeveral years bygone againſt the Magiſtrats of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> their Patrons, they ought not only to be ſever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed therefore, but in all time coming be diſcharged to give in ſuch Petitions, or at leaſt while the Lords gave their final Sentence in the whole matter as his Majeſty requires, otherways this may be an incouragement to the meaneſt Inhabitant of the Town to miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Magiſtrats, who are acting and doing nothing but by his Majeſties Command, eſpecially ſeing the whole Affair is managed but by two or three diſcontented Apothecaries, the major part refuſing to comply therein, as the ſaid Anſwers bears, which Petition and Anſwers made thereto being all at length heard, read, ſeen and conſidered by the ſaids Lords, and the Copy of the Secretaries Letter given in theirwith, &amp; they therewith being well &amp; ripely adviſed. The Lords of Council and Seſſion have Nominat and Appointed, and thereby no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minats and appoints <hi>John Joiſie</hi> ſimple Apothecary, Viſitor to the Fraternity of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries for that enſuing year. <hi>Extractum de libro actorum per me, Sic ſubſcribitur</hi> Al. Gibſon.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:179812:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
